<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-19T15:31:54-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Cutting-Edge Zotero</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/19/cuttingZotero.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cutting-Edge Zotero" /><published>2021-03-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/19/cuttingZotero</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/19/cuttingZotero.html">&lt;p&gt;There’s exciting news on the Zotero front!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zotero just announced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/support/pdf_reader_preview&quot;&gt;preview of their new tab system, complete with a built-in PDF reader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone living the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream, this is huge news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zotero.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Zotero Logo&quot; title=&quot;The Zotero Logo&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Zotero logo is in the public domain.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They plan on releasing these features to the public in Version 6, but anyone itching to try it can use the development version of Zotero. This post will discuss how to install Zotero’s beta in Ubuntu Mate 18.04, though the approach should be similar for other Linux distros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;NB: Note, I would have found this sooner or later, but credit to Sean Lawson for alerting me!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-shut-zotero-down-and-back-it-up&quot;&gt;Step 1: Shut Zotero Down and Back It Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, make sure you’re not running Zotero. You can still have your browser open, however – the Zotero plugin will not affect this step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After shutting down, navigate to your Zotero profile folder. You should see a zotero.sqlite file. Because switching to the Zotero Beta could cause irreversible changes to this database, it’s best to back it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zoterosqlite.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the Zotero folder and zotero.sqlite file&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Zotero folder and zotero.sqlite file in Caja, Mate's file browser&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also backed up my installation of Zotero’s program files. Out of habit, I put them in a folder called “zoteroStandalone” in /.local/share. I simply created an archive of that folder and then deleted its contents. This is going to be my target for the Beta version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-get-the-beta&quot;&gt;Step 2: Get the Beta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then downloaded the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/support/dev_builds&quot;&gt;beta version of Zotero&lt;/a&gt; from their Dev Builds page. It’s in a compressed archive. I unpacked the archive in my now-empty /.local/share/zoteroStandalone folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zoterostandalonebackup.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of my .local/share folder with zoteroStandalone's directory in it&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;I store Zotero's executable files in /.local/share/zoteroStandalone&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, since I’ve been using Zotero for a while, I could then just launch Zotero from Mate’s Brisk menu and it was up and running. But, in case any of you want to know how to add Zotero to your menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-step-add-to-the-brisk-menu&quot;&gt;Optional Step: Add to the Brisk Menu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add Zotero to Mate’s Brisk menu, right-click on your menu and choose “Edit Menus.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to add Zotero to the “Office” subcategory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/briskmenu.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Mate's Brisk menu editor&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Brisk Menu editing starts with selecting where you want to add your menu items.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, select “Add Item.” You will see a menu like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/addingmenuitem.png&quot; alt=&quot;Adding an individual item to the Brisk menu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I stored Zotero in my /.local/share folder, the command path is /home/robert/.local/share/zoteroStandalone/zotero. To add an icon, I click on that springy Mario Brothers-looking icon and navigate to /home/robert/.local/share/zoteroStandalone/chrome/icons/default/default256.png.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I can launch Zotero from the menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve done all this and installed the Zotero beta, perhaps you’re as curious as I am about the new tabbed interface and PDF reader. To get those features, you have to opt-in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/betaoptin.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Zotero's general preferences menu&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Brisk Menu editing starts with selecting where you want to add your menu items.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do that, go to Edit -&amp;gt; Preferences and use the General Tab. There’s an option about halfway down the menu to opt in. After a restart, Zotero will have the new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just did this process minutes ago, so expect a follow-up post on using the new features soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, if you’re looking for Zotero tricks and tips, &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/12/01/Zotero-Tips-and-Tricks.html&quot;&gt;check out this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Zotero" /><category term="FALD" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">There’s exciting news on the Zotero front! Zotero just announced a preview of their new tab system, complete with a built-in PDF reader. For anyone living the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream, this is huge news. The Zotero logo is in the public domain. They plan on releasing these features to the public in Version 6, but anyone itching to try it can use the development version of Zotero. This post will discuss how to install Zotero’s beta in Ubuntu Mate 18.04, though the approach should be similar for other Linux distros. NB: Note, I would have found this sooner or later, but credit to Sean Lawson for alerting me!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GDPR Compliance</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/11/GDPR.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GDPR Compliance" /><published>2021-03-11T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-03-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/11/GDPR</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/11/GDPR.html">&lt;p&gt;A quick note to any readers in GDPR regulated areas: I’m in the USA, and I don’t really do business in Europe. I don’t really do business anywhere, to be honest. Anyway, I also really respect privacy concerns. So, in the interest of transparency, I want to note that I use a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com&quot;&gt;Statcounter&lt;/a&gt; script to help track traffic to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the Javascript in the page source for the blog, and I’ve also &lt;a href=&quot;https://statcounter.com/p5832197/summary/?account_id=1462290&amp;amp;login_id=3&amp;amp;code=6a0a1540cdf3119c0be6e16464d0d1fe&amp;amp;guest_login=1&quot;&gt;made the stats public&lt;/a&gt; (marvel at my traffic!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you block Javascript, I not only don’t mind, nothing should change for you. The site will function just fine with Javascript blocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, if you have a better way to get basic traffic data for a Github.io-hosted static Jekyll blog, let me know in the comments or via Mastodon (@robertwgehl@scholar.social).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><summary type="html">A quick note to any readers in GDPR regulated areas: I’m in the USA, and I don’t really do business in Europe. I don’t really do business anywhere, to be honest. Anyway, I also really respect privacy concerns. So, in the interest of transparency, I want to note that I use a Statcounter script to help track traffic to this blog. You can see the Javascript in the page source for the blog, and I’ve also made the stats public (marvel at my traffic!). If you block Javascript, I not only don’t mind, nothing should change for you. The site will function just fine with Javascript blocked. Moreover, if you have a better way to get basic traffic data for a Github.io-hosted static Jekyll blog, let me know in the comments or via Mastodon (@robertwgehl@scholar.social).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PDF Hell</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/10/PDFhell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PDF Hell" /><published>2021-03-10T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-03-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/10/PDFhell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/10/PDFhell.html">&lt;p&gt;Why in the year 2021 is it hard to edit PDFs in Linux?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/acdchell.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;An image of a PDF of the musical notation to AC/DC's Highway to Hell.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;This is an image of a PDF of sheet music for AC/DC's &quot;Highway to Hell.&quot; Please enjoy the music, but don't ask me to edit the PDF.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don’t tell me to use Okular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don’t tell me to use LaTex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m barely keeping things together using Atril and pdfunite in the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I popped over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://itsfoss.com/pdf-editors-linux/&quot;&gt;It’s FOSS&lt;/a&gt; to see their list of top applications. When your list starts with LibreOffice Draw… I don’t know what to say. It gets worse from there, going to a bunch of commercial, proprietary solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now work for an organization that makes heavy use of PDF forms. I lament the lost hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Printing and scanning seems like the most efficient thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, feel free to tell me to switch to Windows.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><summary type="html">Why in the year 2021 is it hard to edit PDFs in Linux? This is an image of a PDF of sheet music for AC/DC's &quot;Highway to Hell.&quot; Please enjoy the music, but don't ask me to edit the PDF. Please don’t tell me to use Okular. Please don’t tell me to use LaTex. I’m barely keeping things together using Atril and pdfunite in the command line. I popped over to It’s FOSS to see their list of top applications. When your list starts with LibreOffice Draw… I don’t know what to say. It gets worse from there, going to a bunch of commercial, proprietary solutions. I now work for an organization that makes heavy use of PDF forms. I lament the lost hours. Printing and scanning seems like the most efficient thing to do. At this point, feel free to tell me to switch to Windows.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Lost Weekend of Lost Posts</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/28/LostPosts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Lost Weekend of Lost Posts" /><published>2021-02-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/28/LostPosts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/28/LostPosts.html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream can hurt you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the weekend installing &lt;a href=&quot;https://manjaro.org/&quot;&gt;Manjaro&lt;/a&gt; on a laptop. I’m starting to really like Manjaro after years of using Debian-based things like Ubuntu and Mint. I know using Manjaro doesn’t really allow me to say “&lt;a href=&quot;https://us-browse.startpage.com/av/anon-image?piurl=https%3A%2F%2Fpbs.twimg.com%2Fmedia%2FDplToN8UwAAVKrG.jpg&amp;amp;sp=1614633024Td5a5c55f91dbaa7f113abecead862dd2c93f7b804f24473957dcb450b1f72a9e&quot;&gt;I use Arch btw&lt;/a&gt;” but it’s really fun, nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/manjaro.png&quot; alt=&quot;Manjaro Linux Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my Manjaro box to write up a post for the blog, but then I had the bright idea of trying to install a second OS on it, I borked it, and then re-installed… losing the post I wrote. Ah, well. Such is FALD life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have Manjaro up and running (with MATE, of course), though – I’m starting to think it could be my next working distro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[That said, I’m writing this on an Ubuntu box.]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="FALD" /><summary type="html">Sometimes, the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream can hurt you. I spent the weekend installing Manjaro on a laptop. I’m starting to really like Manjaro after years of using Debian-based things like Ubuntu and Mint. I know using Manjaro doesn’t really allow me to say “I use Arch btw” but it’s really fun, nonetheless. I used my Manjaro box to write up a post for the blog, but then I had the bright idea of trying to install a second OS on it, I borked it, and then re-installed… losing the post I wrote. Ah, well. Such is FALD life. I have Manjaro up and running (with MATE, of course), though – I’m starting to think it could be my next working distro. [That said, I’m writing this on an Ubuntu box.]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Linux on Mars</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/21/LinuxMars.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Linux on Mars" /><published>2021-02-21T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/21/LinuxMars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/21/LinuxMars.html">&lt;p&gt;Bowie wanted to know: is there Linux on Mars?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bowieLinuxMars.png&quot; alt=&quot;A modified version of David Bowie's Life on Mars, made to say Linux on Mars&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Yes, David, there's Linux on Mars. Made with &lt;a href=&quot;https://glimpse-editor.github.io/&quot;&gt;Glimpse.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://spectrum.ieee.org/automaton/aerospace/robotic-exploration/nasa-designed-perseverance-helicopter-rover-fly-autonomously-mars&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;IEEE Spectrum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcmag.com/news/linux-is-now-on-mars-thanks-to-nasas-perseverance-rover&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;PC Magazine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Linux is now on Mars. Specifically, the drone copter is running the Linux kernel on an off-the-shelf Qualcomm Snapdragon processor. Perhaps this marks the beginning of the end of proprietary operating systems on the Red Planet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good to see the people of NASA are living the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="FALD" /><summary type="html">Bowie wanted to know: is there Linux on Mars? Yes, David, there's Linux on Mars. Made with Glimpse. According to IEEE Spectrum and PC Magazine, Linux is now on Mars. Specifically, the drone copter is running the Linux kernel on an off-the-shelf Qualcomm Snapdragon processor. Perhaps this marks the beginning of the end of proprietary operating systems on the Red Planet? Good to see the people of NASA are living the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Survey for Mastodon Developers, Admins, and Users</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/09/MastodonSurvey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Survey for Mastodon Developers, Admins, and Users" /><published>2021-02-09T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/09/MastodonSurvey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/09/MastodonSurvey.html">&lt;p&gt;A quick note: I’m conducting a survey with a colleague of mine, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cla.purdue.edu/facultyStaff/profiles/new/newfaculty-18/Zulli_Diana.html&quot;&gt;Dr. Diana Zulli&lt;/a&gt;. We’re interested in learning from Mastodon developers, admins, and users about “freedom of expression.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will post the link to the survey in Mastodon, rather than here. If you use Mastodon, I hope you see it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to note one thing about the survey: we’re offering a small bit of compensation for people’s time (at least, the first 75 or so people – after that, the funding runs out.) Because of where we work, we are using Qualtrics for the survey, and the only real way to compensate people and protect people’s private information is by using Amazon gift cards. We realize you may not share the same values as Amazon. We talked about this problem at length and decided to go ahead with the incentives. If you have interest in doing the survey but no interes in Amazon, you can skip the final questions of the survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this survey, hit me up on Mastodon (@robertwgehl@scholar.social) or via the email address listed here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">A quick note: I’m conducting a survey with a colleague of mine, Dr. Diana Zulli. We’re interested in learning from Mastodon developers, admins, and users about “freedom of expression.” I will post the link to the survey in Mastodon, rather than here. If you use Mastodon, I hope you see it there. I wanted to note one thing about the survey: we’re offering a small bit of compensation for people’s time (at least, the first 75 or so people – after that, the funding runs out.) Because of where we work, we are using Qualtrics for the survey, and the only real way to compensate people and protect people’s private information is by using Amazon gift cards. We realize you may not share the same values as Amazon. We talked about this problem at length and decided to go ahead with the incentives. If you have interest in doing the survey but no interes in Amazon, you can skip the final questions of the survey. If you have questions about this survey, hit me up on Mastodon (@robertwgehl@scholar.social) or via the email address listed here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Asked Mastodon About FOSS for Academics. Here’s What They Said</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/07/CloudAcademic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Asked Mastodon About FOSS for Academics. Here’s What They Said" /><published>2021-02-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/07/CloudAcademic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/02/07/CloudAcademic.html">&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.social/@robertwgehl/105675026053096230&quot;&gt;posted a question to Mastodon&lt;/a&gt; (specifically, scholar.social):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ok! If you had a good budget to build a cloud infrastructure to support small teams (2-5 people) collaborating on projects, with a special focus on academic writing projects, what would you recommend?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’m thinking Linux-based cloud stuff, so I have in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Nextcloud&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jitsi&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Matrix&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;and…? Any recommendations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked this question in all seriousness. I am lucky enough to have a small amount of research funding, I want to promote the world of software beyond Google and Microsoft, and so I’m really keen on building a FOSS Academic Laboratory in the cloud and using to for any collaborative projects I’m a part of. After all, it’s my &lt;a href=&quot;/about.html&quot;&gt;Goal #1&lt;/a&gt;: to use FOSS for as much of my academic work as is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/penquinquestions.png&quot; alt=&quot;A penguin with question marks above its head&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;This penguin's got questions.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The response I got to the questions was &lt;em&gt;freakin’ awesome!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be a good idea to catalog it here. I’ll start with the least-recommended things and work my way up to the most-recommended. That’s not to say this is a ranking – things mentioned only once might be really valuable. I’m really just noting what was mentioned most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll also note which ones I am considering deploying – again, this is not a commentary on the quality of any of these systems. It’s more related to my own specific use cases forged in the past decade of academic collaborations.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fidus-writer&quot;&gt;Fidus Writer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one I hadn’t heard of. Per their website, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fiduswriter.org/how-it-works/&quot;&gt;Fidus Writer&lt;/a&gt; is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;an online collaborative editor especially made for academics who need to use citations and/or formulas. The editor focuses on the content rather than the layout, so that with the same text, you can later on publish it in multiple ways: On a website, as a printed book, or as an ebook. In each case, you can choose from a number of layouts that are adequate for the medium of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds intriguing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it looks like its Zotero support is limited to drag-and-drop. I’d definitely want something closer to LibreOffice’s level of Zotero integration (cite while you write, editing citations, etc). But Fidus looks like it’s developing quickly, so it may be one to watch, especially since it puts collaboration first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pubpub&quot;&gt;PubPub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pubpub.org/about&quot;&gt;PubPub&lt;/a&gt; is a means to publish academic work online and to continue the iterative editing of it even after publication. It solves a problem – after publication, I might find a mistake in my work, or want to update it, or to allow someone else to build on it. But I have no real way of doing that. PubPub solves that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen books published in this manner, and I always value the easy access to them. I don’t have as much experience with giving or receiving feedback in this manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be a bit of FOSS to explore later on – perhaps as a way to share my work outside of normal publishing channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;Latex&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several in the thread made recommendations for LaTex collaborative systems, citing ShareLatex and Overleaf. Looks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sharelatex.com/&quot;&gt;the two are one and the same now&lt;/a&gt;, having joined forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a thing to confess: I’ve never used LaTex, and I haven’t worked with anyone who has, either. So I’m going to note these for the record, but I can’t say too much about them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;homebase&quot;&gt;Homebase&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One person mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://joinhomebase.com/&quot;&gt;HomeBase&lt;/a&gt;. At first glance, this may seem odd, since it’s geared towards small businesses. But it’s really a suite of team collaboration applications, like scheduling and time tracking, group chats, and tools for “onboarding.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could actually see using something like this if I needed to hire student assistants, assuming my university’s HR does not require me to use the university’s HR system. In my experience I’ve seen both with student workers – “do it yourself” contracts and hiring procedures and university-mandated HR systems. I prefer the latter for legal reasons, but if I had to do it on my own, HomeBase might solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jupyter&quot;&gt;Jupyter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For collaborative code writing and notetaking, there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;. Per their website, “The Jupyter Notebook is an open-source web application that allows you to create and share documents that contain live code, equations, visualizations and narrative text. Uses include: data cleaning and transformation, numerical simulation, statistical modeling, data visualization, machine learning, and much more.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not often a pressing need for the work I do, which is mainly interpretive, humanities work. However, my research area of interest is Internet cultures, broadly speaking, and I have had to come up with or modify web scraping scripts in Python. I could easily see collaborating with someone to build such scripts. Maybe Jupyter is too powerful for that, but if the need arises, I would take a look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writefreely&quot;&gt;WriteFreely&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://writefreely.org/&quot;&gt;WriteFreely&lt;/a&gt; is something I keep hearing about, which is not surprising since I spend so much time on Mastodon! It’s a minimalistic blogging platform that integrates well with ActivityPub, allowing people in the fediverse to follow and share one’s posts. It’s meant to be so light it could run on a Raspberry Pi, which is a great feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could see integrating this into a project, since many of my projects have a public-facing, blogging component. I’m definitely considering this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bookstack&quot;&gt;BookStack&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bookstackapp.com/&quot;&gt;BookStack&lt;/a&gt; is a self-hosted wiki system. Similar to what I said about WriteFreely, this could underpin the public-facing part of any given project. There are times when the presentation of information calls for blogs, and there are times when a wiki is a good way to go. I only ever thought of MediaWiki as a solution, but BookStack looks like it has a lighter server footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rocketchat-or-mattermost&quot;&gt;Rocket.chat or Mattermost&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rocket.chat/&quot;&gt;Rocket.chat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattermost.com/&quot;&gt;Mattermost&lt;/a&gt; were cited as alternatives to Slack.  Of the two, Mattermost is touting its security aspects, which is always a good emphasis. This is especially the case for academics dealing with sensitve data (interviews, HIPAA-protected data, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’ve not really used Slack, so I’m not sure what I’m missing in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arkisto&quot;&gt;Arkisto&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arkisto-platform.github.io/&quot;&gt;Arkisto&lt;/a&gt; is meant for data management, particularly at the end of research projects. As the website says, “The basis of Arkisto is that the long-term preservability of well-described data is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; the first consideration.” It looks to me as if they’re thinking long-term about storing data for future use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sort of work I do may not fit what they have in mind. If I gather, for example, ethnographic data from participant observation (such as I did for my book &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/weaving-dark-web&quot;&gt;Weaving the Dark Web&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;, I actually destroy the data after a period of time to protect people’s privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my other work, the data I rely on is bibliographic – I collect sources and interpret them in a more humanistic/historical approach. To have that data live on, I’m hoping that using &lt;a href=&quot;https://zotero.org&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; creates the necessary metadata (let me know if I’m wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I sometimes get invited to join teams working with data in the way Arkisto envisions. Thinking long-term about such data as a public good is a laudable goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jitsi&quot;&gt;Jitsi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several people agreed with my interest in &lt;a href=&quot;https://jitsi.org/&quot;&gt;Jitsi&lt;/a&gt;, the self-hosted video conferencing system. I am strongly inclined to try it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried it in mid-2020 and experienced glitches. I was very keen on getting it working, though, because I was (and remain) opposed to the sudden explosion of Zoom use. Jitsi struck me as a potentially easy alternative for students to talk to me. I had trouble running it, but a few months is a long time where well-maintained FOSS projects are concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;xmpp-based-solutions&quot;&gt;XMPP-Based Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://xmpp.org/&quot;&gt;XMPP&lt;/a&gt;. I think I heard of that once upon a time! In all seriousness, I was once an avid &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pidgin.im/&quot;&gt;Pidgin&lt;/a&gt; user (with OTR encryption, of course). I went away from it, for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But XMPP is making a comeback, not just for me, but for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://pleroma.social/&quot;&gt;Pleroma&lt;/a&gt;, a federated server that can connect to Mastodon, Pixelfed, and other projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I could see, no one in the thread mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://movim.eu/&quot;&gt;Movim&lt;/a&gt;, an XMPP-based federated social networking system getting a lot of attention these days, but I’m pretty sure someone will mention it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m starting to lean towards installing one of these, at the very least to experiment with them and see where they take me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matrix&quot;&gt;Matrix&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matrix was mentioned a great deal, but people were less supportive of this option. Instead, they pointed to other ways to chat. I was surprised by this – some of the Linux podcasts I listen to are all-in on &lt;a href=&quot;https://matrix.org/&quot;&gt;Matrix’s Synapse&lt;/a&gt;, so I figured it was a necessity. But, maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to set that one aside to reduce my workload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nextcloud&quot;&gt;Nextcloud&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly everyone agreed on &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextcloud.com&quot;&gt;Nextcloud&lt;/a&gt;. It would end up being the beating heart of a collaborative academic cloud setup. It has file version control and file sharing. And I could easily add calendars and task lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to agree: I have a small Nextcloud server of my own, and I collaborated with a colleague on a book project using it. While the project went smoothly, there were a couple times the version control of Nextcloud saved us from losing work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nextcloud.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Nextcloud Logo&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Nextcloud Logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that collaborative project, we mainly used &lt;a href=&quot;https://signal.org/en/&quot;&gt;Signal&lt;/a&gt; for chatting, mostly via or text and on occasion via voice. Signal worked fine, but I would like something more persistent to keep track of ideas (for privacy, we set our Signals to delete after a set period.) This is why I mentioned something like Matrix or Jitsi in my initial post. One person noted that Jitsi or Matrix would not even be necessary, thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextcloud.com/talk/&quot;&gt;Nextcloud’s text and video chat support&lt;/a&gt;. Another disagreed, essentially, arguing that people are by now used to the capabilities of a Jitsi-like video conferencing application. In any case, Nextcloud is a possible chat channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several pointed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaboraoffice.com/&quot;&gt;Collabora&lt;/a&gt;, the system that allows for collaborative editing of Libreoffice docs (in a manner similar to Google Docs.) Assuming Collabora supports &lt;a href=&quot;https://zotero.org&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; as well as client-side Libreoffice does, it seems like a no-brainer to add to the mix. The book project I just completed did not use Collabora, instead passing ODTs back and forth, so I’m curious to see how well Collabora could work in a future project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add it all up and Nextcloud is the single most important app in the stack, so I’m definitely going to fire it up. I may see if I can use it for all the things – invest in a more powerful server with a good amount of storage, rather than multiple VMs. It may be easier to administer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like Nextcloud is definitely in the future, and Jitsi &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be. Something federated and XMPP-based might be, as well. The others are good to keep in mind for more specialized use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nextcloud gets the nod simply because it could cover all the bases, so administering would be easier – that’s a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final thought, but an important one. I did not ask specifically about security. If anyone has recommendations there, I’m all ears. I know that I’d want to use SSH keys for server administration, two-factor authentication on both my hosting provider and Nextcloud, and insiste on 2FA for any collaborators. Beyond that, any tips out there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who offered suggestions!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">I posted a question to Mastodon (specifically, scholar.social): Ok! If you had a good budget to build a cloud infrastructure to support small teams (2-5 people) collaborating on projects, with a special focus on academic writing projects, what would you recommend? I’m thinking Linux-based cloud stuff, so I have in mind: Nextcloud Jitsi Matrix and…? Any recommendations? I asked this question in all seriousness. I am lucky enough to have a small amount of research funding, I want to promote the world of software beyond Google and Microsoft, and so I’m really keen on building a FOSS Academic Laboratory in the cloud and using to for any collaborative projects I’m a part of. After all, it’s my Goal #1: to use FOSS for as much of my academic work as is possible. This penguin's got questions. The response I got to the questions was freakin’ awesome! I thought it would be a good idea to catalog it here. I’ll start with the least-recommended things and work my way up to the most-recommended. That’s not to say this is a ranking – things mentioned only once might be really valuable. I’m really just noting what was mentioned most. I’ll also note which ones I am considering deploying – again, this is not a commentary on the quality of any of these systems. It’s more related to my own specific use cases forged in the past decade of academic collaborations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Staticman Comments Test Post</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/24/Staticman.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staticman Comments Test Post" /><published>2021-01-24T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-24T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/24/Staticman</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/24/Staticman.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is to test &lt;a href=&quot;https://staticman.net/&quot;&gt;Staticman&lt;/a&gt; comments. I’ll edit this post later to update my progress. For now, if anyone stumbles across this and wants to add a “test” comment or something helpful, feel free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/staticman.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Staticman Logo&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Staticman Logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m basing this process of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://travisdowns.github.io/blog/2020/02/05/now-with-comments.html&quot;&gt;helpful blog post&lt;/a&gt; from Travis Downs of Performance Matters. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update 1: There are clearly problems in my configuration, and so I must keep debugging. But it’s time for a walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update 2: Success in posting a comment after turning ReCaptcha off. However, not sure if I set things up to &lt;em&gt;display&lt;/em&gt; the comment…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update 3: Success in getting a comment posted! But the workflow is very convoluted. I know Staticman uses Github pull requests to work, so I have to merge each comment. That’s fine. However, after I do so, I will have to move the data from my local version of my static site and then rebuild it via Jekyll. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=INX-KrjaNOo&quot;&gt;There has to be a better way&lt;/a&gt;! And I will figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I do know I will have to style the comments, as well. One thing at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update 4: I think it’s done! Comment forms are styled for desktop and mobile, and the workflow is now improved. I initially set up my Github repository to be only the contents of the _site folder, but now the whole thing (warts and all) is in Github, which makes moderating comments much easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, thanks go to Travis Downs for his exhaustive post on how to get Staticman going, as well as some of his code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have a few more tweaks – most notably, to de-Google-ify the whole thing, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JwZwkk7q25I&quot;&gt;system is not down&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Staticman" /><summary type="html">This post is to test Staticman comments. I’ll edit this post later to update my progress. For now, if anyone stumbles across this and wants to add a “test” comment or something helpful, feel free! The Staticman Logo I’m basing this process of this helpful blog post from Travis Downs of Performance Matters. Thank you!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">20 Years of Wikipedia</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/20/20-years-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="20 Years of Wikipedia" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/20/20-years-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/20/20-years-wikipedia.html">&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia is 20 years old this year. Congratulations! Celebrations abound across the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a scholar of Wikipedia and a FOSS Academic, I wanted to weigh in on the birthday and provide a short history lesson. (This is, therefore, a &lt;a href=&quot;/tags/goal 2.html&quot;&gt;Goal 2 post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/20yearsWP.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia's 20 year celebration page&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reporting on the 20th birthday of Wikipedia (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.msn.com/en-us/news/world/as-wikipedia-turns-20-it-aims-to-reach-more-readers/ar-BB1cLIVf&quot;&gt;MSN&lt;/a&gt;) suggests that Wikipedia was always going to be non-profit. That’s not exactly true. Wikipedia’s URL was initially wikipedia.com, and it was intended to be a for-profit site. As I discuss in my book &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/books/reverse-engineering-social-media-software-culture-and-political-economy-in-new-media-capitalism/9781439910344&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reverse Engineering Social Media,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a key event in 2001, dubbed “The Spanish Fork Labor Strike,” pushed Jimmy Wales to make the site into a non-profit instead of a commercial venture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a mailing list discussion, Wales noted that Wikipedia would start selling ads around its content. He was a veteran of this type of venture, having &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bomis&quot;&gt;sold ads on a porn search engine back in the mid-1990s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The specter of ad sales around voluntarily-provided content upset many Wikipedians, most notably a growing community of Spanish-speaking editors who were working to make Wikipedia an international project. Because Wikipedia was licensed with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Licensing_update&quot;&gt;GFDL&lt;/a&gt;, Spanish-speaking Wikipedians could take the articles they were writing and port them to another site. They did so, moving to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://enciclopedia.us.es/index.php/Enciclopedia_Libre_Universal_en_Espa%C3%B1ol&quot;&gt;Enciclopedia Libre Universal en Español&lt;/a&gt; in protest over Wales’s announcement about ads (as well as their discontent with Larry Sanger’s management style).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales heard their grievances and agreed with them: there would be no ads, Sanger would be fired, and Wikipedia would be a non-profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edgar Enyedy and his colleagues deserve a great deal of credit for pushing the nascent Wikipedia to become a non-profit. And to be fair, credit should go to Wales for recognizing the legitimacy of the &lt;em&gt;Enciclopedia&lt;/em&gt; editors’ greivances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this important event is getting lost to history. Nathaniel Tkacz documented it well during the 10 year anniversary &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.co.uk/article/wikipedia-spanish-fork&quot;&gt;with his interivew with Enyedy&lt;/a&gt;, but since then, the Spanish Fork seems to be overlooked. It’s mentioned only in passing in the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikipedia20.pubpub.org/&quot;&gt;MIT Book W&lt;em&gt;ikipedia @ 20&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First, Wikipedia was conceived by Wales as a likely commercial undertaking. Wikipedia was originally hosted at wikipedia.com, and by 2002 Sanger and Wales were hinting that Bomis might start selling ads on Wikipedia, in part to pay Sanger’s salary. Wikipedians objected—Spanish Wikipedians even left to create their own. Given these objections and the deflation of the dot-com bubble, Sanger was laid off. Wales changed the site over to a .org domain and began work to establish the non-profit Wikimedia Foundation, which happened in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we should thank the Spanish Wikipedians for the site’s current non-commercial status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their strike has brought about many benefits. Unlike so many other websites, Wikipedia has no real infrastructure for behavioral advertising profiling. The Firefox plugin NoScript shows that it’s not tracking – a refreshing change of pace when compared to contemporary sites that are larded with tracking scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/noscriptWP.png&quot; alt=&quot;a screenshot showing that Wikipedia uses very few scripts&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;These are the two scripts Noscript finds on any given Wikipedia article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike many other sites, which are constantly tweaked to increase click-through rates on ads (a practice now dubbed “dark patterns”), Wikipedia’s  interface is remarkably stable. It looks pretty much the same as it did 20 years ago. Rather than seeing this as stagnation, those of us who decry changes in interfaces should celebrate Wikipedia’s now intuitive interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Wikipedians are not interested in tweaking the interface to increase attention on ads, they are constantly tweaking the social structures that help administer pages, with debates over policies, efforts to include more articles about women, efforts to translate the encyclopedia into yet more languages, and a de-facto social networking system where fixing grammar is celebrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Wikipedia did change its licence from GFDL to Creative Commons, the change has only cemented its place as a bastian of open cultural production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my part, I’ve donated to Wikipedia. I’ve contributed to it. I’ve encouraged students to edit it. I rely on it all the time. The FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream would be incomplete without it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a point that I don’t think we’re making enough as misinformation spreads like a deadly virus across corporate social media. Wikipedia was once the  poster child of misinformation. Back in the mid-2000s, Wikipedia-bashing was a popular sport. It was the wild and wacky Wikipedia where vandals and trolls reigned and misinformation was rampant. But very early on in its history, Wikipedia demonstrated the adage about many eyes and bugs: vandalism and uninformed opinion is rooted out rather quickly on Wikipedia, rather than being allowed to spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, I think back to the Spanish Fork and their labor strike: pushing the site to be non-profit and to never have ads has rescued it from the logic of corporate Web 2.0. While other sites mire in the muck of misinformation, while other sites track us, while they constantly develop more pernicous dark patterns, and while the commercial web exploits our emotions and attention, Wikipedia has just carried on, with people writing articles and citing their sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kudos.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Wikipedia" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">Wikipedia is 20 years old this year. Congratulations! Celebrations abound across the Internet. As a scholar of Wikipedia and a FOSS Academic, I wanted to weigh in on the birthday and provide a short history lesson. (This is, therefore, a Goal 2 post).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In Praise of Mastodon After an Insurrection, or, What if Donald Trump Had Joined Mastodon?</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/08/PraiseMastodon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Praise of Mastodon After an Insurrection, or, What if Donald Trump Had Joined Mastodon?" /><published>2021-01-08T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/08/PraiseMastodon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/08/PraiseMastodon.html">&lt;p&gt;In a previous post, I disparaged 2020. But hey, just wait: 2021 has already become pretty bad. As you probably have seen, pro-Trump supporters decided to invade the U.S. Capitol on January 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a tech determinist, which means that I do not seek to explain complexity by only considering changes in technology. So I am not going to say that corporate social media – including Facebook and Twitter – caused what happened yesterday. In other words, I am not going to say that the spread of misinformation was the reason for people to blithely walk past the cops and into the Rotunda. To do so would ignore a host of other factors, such as the history of racism in the United States and the desire for politicians to aggrandize themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m not saying Facebook and Twitter are to blame. What I will say, however, is that one contributing factor to the events of January 6, 2021 – not the sole determining factor – is corporate social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mastodon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Mastodon Logo&quot; title=&quot;The Mastodon Logo&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Mastodon Logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thus I come in praise of Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-attention-economy&quot;&gt;The Attention Economy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporate social media platforms like Facebook and Twitter have for years been developed to monetize the content that spreads the farthest keeps people’s attention – no matter what that content is. We all may have thought it was cute cat videos, but it’s turned out that the stuff that spreads wildly and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/money/2020/08/04/898596655/are-conspiracy-theories-good-for-facebook&quot;&gt;keeps eyeballs are beguiling conspiracy theories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn’t the only monetization happening. Corporate social media also privileges paid content – that is, advertising, and political actors have paid billions in order to get their messages out to their masspersonal audiences. After all, for a few bucks, you can have your message privileged in corporate social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combine the two and you get politicians paying to stoke conspiracy theories, which are spread by misinformed people, who flag their support for politicians, who pay for more ads ad infinitum, ad nauseam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As media studies scholar Gavin Mueller quipped (unfortunately, on Twitter in a Tweet I can’t find), the QAnon conspiracy was mired in a degree of obscurity on places like 4chan, but once it got to Facebook and its audience of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/internet-baby-boomers-misinformation-social-media_n_5f998039c5b6a4a2dc813d3d&quot;&gt;boomers with computers&lt;/a&gt;” started “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Conspiracy-Theorist-Just-Research-Shirt/dp/B07DG2NKXQ&quot;&gt;doing the research&lt;/a&gt;,” it exploded. And right-wing politicians gleefully amplified the messages, from Georgia’s Marjorie Taylor Greene all the way up to Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this week, Facebook and Twitter de-platformed Trump. It was intriguing to watch each corporation one-up the other. Twitter flagged Trump tweets as disputed. Facebook took down a Trump video. Twitter suspended Trump for 12 hours. Facebook banned Trump for the remainder of his time in office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem solved, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should have happened a long, long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it couldn’t have. Because these platforms &lt;em&gt;monetize content.&lt;/em&gt; And that means what’s popular, what spreads, what keeps attention is privileged. Full stop. And who or what has been the single greatest corporate social media sensation arguably of all time? Donald J. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;donaldjtrumpmagainstancesocial-a-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;@donaldjtrump@magainstance.social: A Thought Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with FOSS Academics? And with Mastodon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Trump would have been kicked off Mastodon ages ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, properly speaking, he would have been &lt;em&gt;defederated&lt;/em&gt; ages ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s do a thought experiment. In 2017, Trump (or one of his assistants) noticed the hype about Mastodon and decided to mirror his Twitter content there. Why not explore a new social network and reach more of the MAGA Nation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know how Mastodon works – how federation works – you immediately ask: &lt;a href=&quot;https://instances.social/&quot;&gt;which instance&lt;/a&gt; would Trump have used?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a big question. Many Mastodon instances have Codes of Conduct that Trump would have found to be abhorrent: no homophobic, transphobic, racist, fascist content allowed. So a triumphant post about Trump’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/trump-s-controversial-transgender-military-policy-goes-effect-n993826&quot;&gt;ban on openly transgender people serving in the military&lt;/a&gt; wouldn’t have been just flagged; it would be &lt;em&gt;blocked&lt;/em&gt; and Trump would be informed by the admin that he was violating the Code of Conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump might have just stopped there. Social media that would ban me? But I’m the greatest President ever! The First Amendment! These liberal Mastodons need to be put in jail!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s say he persisted. There are Mastodon instances out there that are more “free speech absolutist.” Trump could have found one – let’s call it magainstance.social – and started his account, and his posts would have spread across the Fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except, they wouldn’t have. The same Mastodon instances who would have blocked or outright banned Trump would avoid federating with the instance Trump joined, citing the fact that doing so would violate their local standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Trump would have kept posting anyway. After all, he’s shown an ignorance of how &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/think/opinion/trump-senate-gop-s-electoral-college-vote-objections-betray-conservative-ncna1252927&quot;&gt;federation works&lt;/a&gt;. But he’d probably not get his precious dopamine rush from seeing a bunch of reposts and likes, because, again, &lt;em&gt;his posts wouldn’t spread across the Fediverse&lt;/em&gt; – they would not get the eyeballs and accolades the man clearly needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe then he’d retreat back to Twitter and Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps, even after all this, Trump wanted to stick with Mastodon, believing that it was the next big thing, or perhaps enjoying the love of sycophants on magainstance.social. And maybe he figures, I can fix this, as I always have, with lots of money. I’ll just buy a bunch of ads on Mastodon and that will remind them of who’s paying the bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then he looks for a place to buy ads on Mastodon and finds… nothing. &lt;em&gt;Because it’s not made for advertisers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To be fair, there’s probably no reason individual Mastodon instances couldn’t have advertising. But again, those instances probably won’t get much federation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in a fit of Trumpian rage, he grabs a laptop and says, Mastodon’s open source! I will fork the code! I will make my own! And he fires up Notepad in Microsoft and furiously starts coding. (What coding language would Trump use? I’m not going to answer that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tildes.net/~tech/e0o/gab_is_throwing_away_their_existing_code_and_switching_to_a_modified_version_of_mastodon&quot;&gt;that doesn’t work, either&lt;/a&gt;. Same problem. magainstance.social – or Gab, or whatever you want to call it – would again just be shut out of the federation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;foss-is-political&quot;&gt;FOSS Is Political&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this is a blog about being a FOSS Academic, and I have &lt;em&gt;Goal 2&lt;/em&gt; – I want to write a new book about FOSS. And this is decidedly a Goal 2 post, because I’m talking about FOSS culture and politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come to praise projects like Mastodon, because I would argue they were designed to avoid the problems that Facebook and Twitter have helped contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know very well that many people in the FOSS world would bracket off these comments, arguing that they are political, that they have no relevance for a discussion about FOSS, and that all FOSS is about is making neutral tools. I’ve interviewed people in the FOSS world who make that argument, and I get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people make tools of &lt;em&gt;any kind,&lt;/em&gt; they are embedding cultural, political, and ethical assumptions into the tools. They might claim the tools are neutral – as in the observation that “a hammer can be used to build a house or to hurt someone.” But even the simplest tool reflects the cultural, economic, and political assumptions of its maker. A hammer extends our ability to apply powerful force in a concentrated area, reflecting a different relationship building than, say, thatching implies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the level of cultural, economic, or political embeddness goes up greatly with complex tools, like an open souce, federated social networking site with built-in moderation tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The production of FOSS tools is inherently political. Some FOSS developers recognize this, engaging in what I call “critical reverse engineering” – making tools that are meant to ameliorate the social, economic, and political problems we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others don’t recognize this, concentrating on the existential pleasures of making tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s fine, but think about this: Twitter started out as simply a way to centralize SMS for a large audience. Facebook started out as a way to rate pictures of girls and built some social stuff around that task. They didn’t think much then about what they wrought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, however, tech is not the sole determinant of what happens in society. But that doesn’t mean tech plays no part. So, it’s important for us to consider which technologies contribute to a better world. Mastodon, the federated, open source alternative social media platform that was &lt;em&gt;literally designed&lt;/em&gt; to disallow advertising and allow people to moderate the content, achieved from its conception what corporate social media are only just now blindly groping towards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Mastodon" /><summary type="html">In a previous post, I disparaged 2020. But hey, just wait: 2021 has already become pretty bad. As you probably have seen, pro-Trump supporters decided to invade the U.S. Capitol on January 6. I am not a tech determinist, which means that I do not seek to explain complexity by only considering changes in technology. So I am not going to say that corporate social media – including Facebook and Twitter – caused what happened yesterday. In other words, I am not going to say that the spread of misinformation was the reason for people to blithely walk past the cops and into the Rotunda. To do so would ignore a host of other factors, such as the history of racism in the United States and the desire for politicians to aggrandize themselves. So I’m not saying Facebook and Twitter are to blame. What I will say, however, is that one contributing factor to the events of January 6, 2021 – not the sole determining factor – is corporate social media. The Mastodon Logo And thus I come in praise of Mastodon.</summary></entry></feed>