<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-02T10:02:16-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">New Book, Old Book</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/03/26/NewBookOldBook.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Book, Old Book" /><published>2022-03-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/03/26/NewBookOldBook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/03/26/NewBookOldBook.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve not written much about my most recent book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/social-engineering&quot;&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/a&gt; (MIT Press, 2022) on this blog. It didn’t seem like a good topic for this FOSS-centric blog. When I did write about it, I focused on the fact that my co-author, Sean Lawson, and I were able to use FOSS (particularly Nextcloud) to write it. In the parlance of this blog, that’s a decidedly Goal 1 topic – about using FOSS tools to do academic work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ve focused instead on my next project, the Goal 2 project of writing a book about FOSS alternative social media. My idea is to use this blog to publicly write that book. Such public writing is new to me – it’s even a bit intimidating – but seems appropriate for this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the more I’m digging into what it means to envision, make, and realize ethical, FOSS, alternative social media, the more I realize my latest book, &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering,&lt;/em&gt; is directly relevant to the project. So, this post is a way for me to make those connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/secover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover of book Social Engineering by Gehl and Lawson&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was prompted by the explosion of disinformation and manipulation we’ve observed over the past 10 years. The big events here, of course, were the Russian interference campaign and Cambridge Analytica, both reaching prominence during the 2016 US presidential election. (We also write about more recent events, but these are two very well-documented instances of attempts at mass manipulation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a better understanding of Russian disinformation or Cambridge Analytica “micro-targeting,” Sean and I turned to the concept of social engineering. We note that this term has been used in two distinct communicative contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First was the early 20th century propagandists who drew on the language of social reform and social science of their time. They proposed to adjust society using scientific techniques and mass persuasion, a process glossed as “engineering of consent” (to use Edward Bernays’s famous phrase).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there were the mid-20th century phone phreaks and hackers, who use the term “social engineering” to describe their practice of conning people out of passwords. This is an interpersonal sort of manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We argue that both the mass social engineering of propaganda and the interpersonal social engineering of hacking merge in contemporary corporate social media in a form we call “masspersonal social engineering.” We define &lt;a href=&quot;https://watermark.silverchair.com/c000400_9780262368926.pdf?token=AQECAHi208BE49Ooan9kkhW_Ercy7Dm3ZL_9Cf3qfKAc485ysgAAAsIwggK-BgkqhkiG9w0BBwagggKvMIICqwIBADCCAqQGCSqGSIb3DQEHATAeBglghkgBZQMEAS4wEQQMYRnDz0chEg8p6ccQAgEQgIICdeFTnQWL17PMR9vfCgwJHJa9mUSadJGxEZGbQ55WiOpspJXi-nE2GHUh-JJvtcwSpeWi5QYTPZ_uSyH7QtFX9z06Dukk9NxStvdw6D7eBGHQdgbFtz0_FkXoEhvJRdsvVoJnwwwO-vu3fvRdkHWjlX-Qdr5bMlNH_HQJxKW7TOvFkXolVhz0w9XEnGvEcE5npx1KLzlFPiCmHero5cufwHKB7d8im_4Q7zpPvHrZSDtJB5i1zjleafXz_UL28vM9JhjHeEurgOf-raryGnepdJqxvvZqqrHraRWghk9T90beKO-BDCCiMKy9qCp100OSNf9BB9a_STvST0PcPdpoy12vP5ZSwXE-9QaxP6I8PguUwXRm9Gb-Bos8n4WtHqgJZIPPUyVXe4Pwzlr0s7SHFO7K7NG866vjfJ3tWefx4fkQBFxKAJMaIGq3VoULFl0cT12XVdkK0sxJt_xRRDDzUi-s0fhW1SBEjRNnAhe_EpdBpmDVUjJLU5V4TCv1Y9p7h0ubLKcyc8JwPjanaUmLvd-t5k0UqImqHiFbVu68fzSFqsehqPt56UrnknXlc6HqFjB10EHzmQgxk4cJR46uhohOpyyysIr3RxwNwx_Zs4uOqYZo-9zdvsMcCLVNLMXAU4mu3x1PDTY3z1ututpvDf-m3UkRmEngvqe1ve7v6cwE9MWJ-NaYQvrdJ53QzsZ5muuoiJTEAjYI8PptRclByNJj5UMQ3i7uYoC_wVDzYivtleynpi66aEN0_2GQsNawYCvEGeLGzTt4ZLudF18AUnfawOxhcpkWJxpaP9jTNIma5bbPqR3uea5SQFTWV_MfC43MPlrF&quot;&gt;this concept in the book as&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;an emerging form of manipulative communication enabled by
the unique affordances of the internet and social media platforms.
It brings together the respective tools and techniques of hackers
and propagandists, interpersonal and mass communication, in
an attempt to shape the perceptions and actions of audiences. To
manipulate, masspersonal social engineers gather data on their
targets; create fake personas to share messages; mix deception,
accuracy, and friendliness as they engage with targets; and penetrate
communication systems. Manipulation, in this case, can involve a
range of goals, which might include attempts to change actions and
beliefs. But it could also include discouraging action (e.g., voting)
and amplifying or intensifying preexisting beliefs (e.g., racism,
sexism, or other social divisions) when doing so is in the perceived
interests of the masspersonal social engineers or their clients.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The connection to my current project on ethical alternative social media is now very obvious to me. Part of what we have to do when making a better suite of social media technologies is to remove the technologies, policies, and practices that aid and abet masspersonal social engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are obvious things, such as eliminating behavioral advertising, which encourages the use of reductive consumer profiling and links those profiles to viral messaging – a perfect breeding ground for the spread of misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also less obvious things that have to be done – such as bringing media control closer to the end users. I wonder how much disinformation and misinformation spread is aided by a lack of a sense of shared responsibility for the health of the “community” in corporate social media. Contrast this with smaller, federated social media systems, where users may feel that they have more ownership over the health of the instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this post is merely my flagging the fact that my old book may end up more important to the new one. I may refer to the ideas from &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/em&gt; more often here. Rest assured, this is not in an attempt to sell my book, but is rather a way to think about how ethical alternatives may help alleviate the scourge of manipulative communication (or, and let’s be honest, how they also might become vectors for manipulation in their own right).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of that, if you’re curious about the connections between the history of manipulative communication and what alternative social media might do to undermine such manipulation, keep watching this blog, and perhaps you should check out &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/em&gt; – it’s in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.powells.com/book/social-engineering-9780262543453&quot;&gt;finer bookstores now&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://direct.mit.edu/books/oa-monograph/5281/Social-EngineeringHow-Crowdmasters-Phreaks-Hackers&quot;&gt;you can get it for free from MIT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">I’ve not written much about my most recent book, Social Engineering (MIT Press, 2022) on this blog. It didn’t seem like a good topic for this FOSS-centric blog. When I did write about it, I focused on the fact that my co-author, Sean Lawson, and I were able to use FOSS (particularly Nextcloud) to write it. In the parlance of this blog, that’s a decidedly Goal 1 topic – about using FOSS tools to do academic work. So, I’ve focused instead on my next project, the Goal 2 project of writing a book about FOSS alternative social media. My idea is to use this blog to publicly write that book. Such public writing is new to me – it’s even a bit intimidating – but seems appropriate for this topic. But the more I’m digging into what it means to envision, make, and realize ethical, FOSS, alternative social media, the more I realize my latest book, Social Engineering, is directly relevant to the project. So, this post is a way for me to make those connections.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/03/07/FOSSFinds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds" /><published>2022-03-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-03-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/03/07/FOSSFinds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/03/07/FOSSFinds.html">&lt;p&gt;This week’s FOSS finds: The big news – or maybe non-news – in this space is the pathetically inept rollout of Truth Social, Donald Trump’s $1,000,000,000 social networking site built on the free-as-in-beer but also free-as-in-freedom Mastodon software base. I watched Truth go online and I have thoughts, but here I will just share some resources I’ve gathered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;primack-dan-2022-trump-is-blowing-truth-socials-launch-axios-march-2-2022&quot;&gt;Primack, Dan. 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.axios.com/trump-blowing-truth-social-launch-c2d4f1f0-5440-478a-acfa-b9462b64568c.html&quot;&gt;“Trump Is Blowing Truth Social’s Launch.”&lt;/a&gt; Axios. March 2, 2022.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article summarizes the financial aspects of Truth Social, which received quite a bit of investment. Primack notes, however, that Trump has done little to nothing to promote Truth. (What else is new?) so that investors will start to get nervous that this might fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cramer-ruby-2022-the-emptiness-inside-donald-trumps-new-social-media-platform-politico-march-5-2022&quot;&gt;Cramer, Ruby. 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2022/03/05/truth-social-emptiness-donald-trump-00014355.&quot;&gt;“The Emptiness Inside Donald Trump’s New Social Media Platform.”&lt;/a&gt; POLITICO. March 5, 2022.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big problem with the Truth rollout was that they failed to meet the demand of new user signups. Instead, people were put on long waitlists. Ruby Cramer of Politico was one such waitlisted person and, as she reports, once she got into Truth, it seems to be a ghost town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caelin-derek-2020-decentralized-social-networks-vs-the-trolls&quot;&gt;Caelin, Derek. 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yZoASOyfvGQ&quot;&gt;“Decentralized Social Networks vs the Trolls.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start of Truth reminded me of course of the alt-right Christian nationalist Gab.com’s entry into the Fediverse – an entry quickly mitigated by fediblocking. It prompted me to study this video presentation from Derek Caelin, who unpacks the Gab/Mastodon incident with survey and interview data. If you want to understand the fediverse’s reaction to Truth, look to what happened with Gab.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">This week’s FOSS finds: The big news – or maybe non-news – in this space is the pathetically inept rollout of Truth Social, Donald Trump’s $1,000,000,000 social networking site built on the free-as-in-beer but also free-as-in-freedom Mastodon software base. I watched Truth go online and I have thoughts, but here I will just share some resources I’ve gathered.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coding Freedom, by Biella Coleman</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/02/15/CodingFreedom.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coding Freedom, by Biella Coleman" /><published>2022-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/02/15/CodingFreedom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/02/15/CodingFreedom.html">&lt;p&gt;As part of Goal 2 of this blog, I’m writing a book about FOSS, specifically FOSS alternative social media. Like any good academic, I need to review the literature. I want to do so a bit more publicly than I have in the past – hence this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I’ve already started the process a bit: early on this blog went a bit viral &lt;a href=&quot;2020/12/06/Dreaming-In-Code.html&quot;&gt;thanks to my post about Scott Rosenberg’s &lt;em&gt;Dreaming in Code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was linked by Hacker News. I also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;2021/03/28/RMMess.html&quot;&gt;a review of sorts of Sam Williams’s &lt;em&gt;Free as in Freedom,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a biography of Stallman. I just so happened to finish reading that book when Stallman was reinstated to the FSF, which made my post a bit more polemical than review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I’m going to turn to a modern classic: Gabriella Coleman’s &lt;em&gt;Coding Freedom: The Ethics and Aesthetics of Hacking.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/coleman.gif&quot; alt=&quot;coleman.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coleman is a trained anthropologist, engaging in deep hanging out, and in the early 2000s she turned her attention to one of the most important FOSS projects out there: Debian. She focuses on the full range of Debian’s activities, from gathering at conventions to online networking to the common conception of the self as hacker. Her analysis of conventions as lifeworlds is very powerful. As she argues, “the hacker con is a condensed, weeklong performance of a lifeworld that hackers usually build over decades of experiences and interactions connected to various media, institutions, and objects” (57). Her observation is an antidote to the idea that FOSS hackers only interact virtually – they crave in-person meetings like any sociable human would (which is probably easier to understand in these days of Zooming and distancing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, she discusses the politics of licensing at great length, tracing the now-familiar history of proprietary software on one hand and the sharing of code (and eventual copyleft approach) on the other. And yet, which she notes the idealism of the Free Software crowd, she also documents the pragmatism of many FOSS users: “The majority of hackers I interviewed… came to free software at first merely for the sake of affordable, better-built technology and had little knowledge about the existence, much less the workings, of intellectual property law” (71). (Indeed, this echoes &lt;a href=&quot;2020/12/15/FOSS-Journey.html&quot;&gt;my own FOSS journey&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although people may have come to FOSS without thinking too much about the politics, Coleman also observed how pushback against sharing – particularly the crackdown on DeCSS and the arrest of Dmitry Skylarov – forced many FOSS users into a more political stance. I believe &lt;em&gt;Coding Freedom&lt;/em&gt; is best known for Coleman’s incisive analysis of what might be called “legal hacking,” or the treatment of law as a system susceptible to being tinkered with. For example, a well-known way that FOSS advocates drew attention to the strangeness of criminalizing code was to convert DeCSS into poems and printing it on t-shirts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-big-takeway-for-goal-2&quot;&gt;My Big Takeway for Goal 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to draw on from Coleman’s analysis. But I wonder if her work has become so influential that we take many of her arguments for granted. In some ways, she’s helped create the FOSS world we find ourselves in. Read her book to see what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One area that I think is only now being addressed in FOSS – an area I think Coleman was prescient of – is calls for diversity and concerns about Freedom 0. One of the surprises she experienced was that both Free Software advocates and Open Source, pro-corporate advocates were largely &lt;em&gt;apolitical.&lt;/em&gt; That is, as she discusses, they avoided Left/Right distinctions (pp 185-186). To be certain, there were the activists defending free speech, but little in the way of the left or right politics to be found among FOSS developers. She argues that this political neutrality was central to the growth of FOSS – it turns out to be software that socialists and big corporations see great potential in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of neutrality is tied to Freedom 0, of course, the first of the “Four Freedoms” of Free Software. For example, she quotes a Debian developer, who says, “I can’t control if the person using my software is racist” (187). (I’ve found similar sentiments among the FOSS people I have interviewed, who note their work is not activism, and it isn’t political – they’re just making neutral tools that anyone can use and contribute to.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as we’ve learned in the past decade, corporations and governments will readily adopt FOSS for unethical ends, whether it be manipulative forms of communication, the exploitation of free labor, or to monitor and incarcerate populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, there is currently a revolt against corporate and government surveillance and exploitation but the revolt takes many forms. The revolt against these practices can also be aided by FOSS – but it can also be unethical, with the use of FOSS for hate speech platforms being one example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, there is a call for FOSS &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; Freedom 0, and instead with the ability to prevent, for example, racists from using one’s code. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethicalsource.dev/&quot;&gt;Ethical Source&lt;/a&gt; is one example. Another is the network power of federation (and subsequently, de-federation). In both cases there is a very clear reaction against &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; corporate control &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Freedom 0. These projects, however, are arguably not Free Software by definition. As I think Coleman shows, the only advocacy in Freedom 0 is Freedom – again, no ability to stop bad actors from using one’s code. And, as diversity advocates are pointing out, the politics of “freedom” is often the politics of whiteness, masculinity, and economic exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like so many other aspects of where we are now, Coleman’s work anticipates this debate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Despite their official stance on licensing, some leftists have trouble accepting the formulation of nondiscrimination lying at the heart of F/OSS legal agreements. Some express discomfort or dismay that nondiscrimination, as articulated in F/OSS licensing, bars the type of control that would allow Indymedia to keep its work from being exploited for purposes of oppression (by the military, say) or corporate profit. In this guise, they echo the Marcusian critique of liberalism’s “pure tolerance” of free speech (Marcuse 1965).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that my work is taking me through code to running instances of alternative social media, I must necessarily understand this debate. Coleman’s work grounds the conversation, but I will need to read more. Watch this space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Lit Review" /><summary type="html">As part of Goal 2 of this blog, I’m writing a book about FOSS, specifically FOSS alternative social media. Like any good academic, I need to review the literature. I want to do so a bit more publicly than I have in the past – hence this blog. In fact, I’ve already started the process a bit: early on this blog went a bit viral thanks to my post about Scott Rosenberg’s Dreaming in Code., which was linked by Hacker News. I also wrote a review of sorts of Sam Williams’s Free as in Freedom, a biography of Stallman. I just so happened to finish reading that book when Stallman was reinstated to the FSF, which made my post a bit more polemical than review. This time, I’m going to turn to a modern classic: Gabriella Coleman’s Coding Freedom: The Ethics and Aesthetics of Hacking.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Have Settled on Zettlr</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/02/03/Zettlr.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Have Settled on Zettlr" /><published>2022-02-03T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-02-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/02/03/Zettlr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/02/03/Zettlr.html">&lt;p&gt;About a week ago, I took to my home Mastodon instance, scholar.social, and asked whether people preferred &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zettlr.com/&quot;&gt;Zettlr&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsidian.md/&quot;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt;. Both are Markdown editors which also provide valuable features on top, including linking together Markdown notes and varying degrees of Zotero support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked because I’m using Markdown more and more. I use it regularly to plan my weeks, I obviously use it for this blog (which is a static Jekyll site), and I started using it to jot down ideas in a journaling program called &lt;a href=&quot;https://rednotebook.sourceforge.io/&quot;&gt;RedNoteBook&lt;/a&gt;. I was hoping to streamline blogging, note-taking, and other Markdown tasks in one system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have tried both Zettlr and Obsidian – and I also tried a third system, &lt;a href=&quot;https://logseq.com/&quot;&gt;Logseq&lt;/a&gt; – and have decided to adopt Zettlr. It meets my needs quite well, which are probably a bit more minimal than people might expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, given what these projects are doing, I do not feel locked into my choice. In fact, I have all three installed and may hop between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-chose-zettlr&quot;&gt;Why I Chose Zettlr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought about writing up comparisons between these systems, but I think those sorts of posts abound – just DuckDuckGo “obsidian vs zettlr” or “zettlr vs logseq” and you’ll see what I mean. Moreover, I get the sense that all of them have some very zealous adherents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/80777352f93ad1f40b45edf2022a55e9.png&quot; alt=&quot;80777352f93ad1f40b45edf2022a55e9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obsidian in particular has a lot of fans on Youtube (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=njibNuFQwjw&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;), who share their complex workflows and talk about how network graphs reveal new ways of thinking. Logseq is based on “block-level” linking, which itself builds on RemNote. As its name implies, Zettlr is inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/introduction/#luhmann-s-zettelkasten&quot;&gt;“Zettlekasten” method of Niklas Luhmann&lt;/a&gt;. If you start searching those terms, be prepared for lengthy manifestos about how to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for me, I guess I’m keeping it simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take notes on things in Zotero, I jot down thoughts in Markdown (previously in the aforementioned RedNoteBook), and then I synthesize the lot in Libreoffice with the Zotero plugin. What was missing in the middle – the Markdown phase – was linking between notes as well as tagging, which is why I’m trying out Obsidian/Zettlr/Logseq in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three of them do wiki-style linking between Markdown files. They also allow for easy octothorpe (#) tagging. The differences appear in how they show those links to me – Obsidian and Logseq show network graphs, and Zettlr just shows backlinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much I think the graphs are cool, I don’t really see much value in them in my day-to-day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead, I’ve opted for the one with the most comfortable interface, and that is Zettlr. The Workspaces layout reminds me of good text editors, the autocomplete on links works quite well, and the right-hand sidebar gives me all the information I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the biggest reason I’m choosing Zettlr is that &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Zettlr/Zettlr&quot;&gt;it’s FOSS&lt;/a&gt;. Since I’m adopting the pose of the FOSS Academic – and since &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/01/06/Goal2.html&quot;&gt;Goal 2&lt;/a&gt; of this blog is to write a book about FOSS – I really have to choose it. Logseq is also FOSS. Obsidian, however, is not, and does not appear to be going in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with Zettlr in the mix, I use FOSS across the board, from my underlying OS (various Linux flavors) to Firefox to Zotero to Zettlr to Libreoffice to this blog. I’m really happy to be able to write like this while I write about FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-i-might-switch-at-any-moment&quot;&gt;But I Might Switch at Any Moment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while I’m using and enjoying Zettlr, the real power of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these systems is that I don’t have to choose. I’m not locked in. All three promise not to lock me in, and they are true to their word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because they’re built on top of simple text files, I can simply jump from Zettlr to Logseq to Obsidian, adding new notes to my collection, and not have the underlying file structure be damaged in any way. So, if I do want to see a network graph of my notes, I could fire up Logseq and take a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan on keeping Logseq and Zettlr on my system indefinitely. (I’m on the fence about Obsidian, since it’s not FOSS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for those of you interested in these systems, give ‘em a try.’&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="Zettlr" /><summary type="html">About a week ago, I took to my home Mastodon instance, scholar.social, and asked whether people preferred Zettlr or Obsidian. Both are Markdown editors which also provide valuable features on top, including linking together Markdown notes and varying degrees of Zotero support. I asked because I’m using Markdown more and more. I use it regularly to plan my weeks, I obviously use it for this blog (which is a static Jekyll site), and I started using it to jot down ideas in a journaling program called RedNoteBook. I was hoping to streamline blogging, note-taking, and other Markdown tasks in one system. So, I have tried both Zettlr and Obsidian – and I also tried a third system, Logseq – and have decided to adopt Zettlr. It meets my needs quite well, which are probably a bit more minimal than people might expect. However, given what these projects are doing, I do not feel locked into my choice. In fact, I have all three installed and may hop between them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/29/FOSS-Finds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds" /><published>2022-01-29T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/29/FOSS%20Finds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/29/FOSS-Finds.html">&lt;p&gt;This week’s FOSS finds: I’m starting to look back at the early days of ActivityPub, and chat apps get some coverage. So once again, don’t count on these posts as a news feed, but more a window into my thinking as I research my FOSS alternative social media book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;w3c-launches-push-for-social-web-application-interoperability-2014-w3c-blog-july-21-2014-httpswwww3orgblognewsarchives3958&quot;&gt;“W3C Launches Push for Social Web Application Interoperability.” 2014. W3C (blog). July 21, 2014. https://www.w3.org/blog/news/archives/3958.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the press release from the W3C announcing the start of the Social Web Working Group, which I understand gave us ActivityPub, the protocol that supports contemporary federated social media systems such as Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sv_meeting_title--14-may-2014-2014-may-14-2014-httpswwww3org20140514-social-minuteshtml&quot;&gt;“SV_MEETING_TITLE – 14 May 2014.” 2014. May 14, 2014. https://www.w3.org/2014/05/14-social-minutes.html.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This somewhat innocuous-looking site is the start of something big – the transcript first meeting of the Social Web Working Group, held over IRC. What immediately catches my eye is the forceful statement from Tantek Çelik, of Mozilla: “we don’t want to see a big company or 2-3 get a monopolistic control in this space.” Thinking about that from the outset likely affected the ultimate design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;massochin-manuela-2022-why-choose-rocketchat-for-your-open-source-chat-tool-opensourcecom-january-24-2022-httpsopensourcecomarticle221rocketchat-data-privacy&quot;&gt;Massochin, Manuela. 2022. “Why Choose Rocket.Chat for Your Open Source Chat Tool.” Opensource.Com. January 24, 2022. https://opensource.com/article/22/1/rocketchat-data-privacy.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is essentially a press release from RocketChat and published on Opensource.com. What caught my eye is that this system appears to be federated. I’m getting more curious about federated chat applications – it feels like a very active area of development, and yet chat feels so &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; – how long as XMPP been around? So it’s interesting to me that chat apps are cropping up in my news feeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;smithee-alan-2022-software-privacy-day-use-delta-chat-an-open-source-chat-tool-opensourcecom-january-28-2022-httpsopensourcecomarticle221delta-chat-software-privacy-day&quot;&gt;Smithee, Alan. 2022. “Software Privacy Day: Use Delta Chat, an Open Source Chat Tool.” Opensource.Com. January 28, 2022. https://opensource.com/article/22/1/delta-chat-software-privacy-day.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case in point. Here’s another chat app, Delta Chat. This one is intriguing. The author mentions Mattermost, Signal, and RocketChat and then points to the major differentiating feature of Delta Chat: it uses &lt;em&gt;encrypted emails&lt;/em&gt; to send the messages. So the backend is email, while the frontend appears to be chat application. It’s so crazy it just might work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">This week’s FOSS finds: I’m starting to look back at the early days of ActivityPub, and chat apps get some coverage. So once again, don’t count on these posts as a news feed, but more a window into my thinking as I research my FOSS alternative social media book.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Very Kool + Jellyfin</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/26/Very-Kool.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Very Kool + Jellyfin" /><published>2022-01-26T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-26T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/26/Very%20Kool</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/26/Very-Kool.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;kde&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a quick note to say that I took the plunge: after many, many years of using MATE desktops, I’ve tried KDE Plasma. I really, really like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’ve also had some fun with Jellyfin – so much so it’s goodbye, Plex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote about in a post about &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/12/27/Workflow.html&quot;&gt;my workflow&lt;/a&gt;, for years I used Devilspie to sort applications into various workspaces. After posting that, I half expected to get a comment that this would be natively possible in another desktop environment – and I expected someone to say “use KDE!” That didn’t happen, but I still suspected it might be the case – and that KDE would be the one to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/92acf6d56dbcc6b6824d7ee33117267e.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image not found: /assets/images/92acf6d56dbcc6b6824d7ee33117267e.png&quot; title=&quot;Image not found: /assets/images/92acf6d56dbcc6b6824d7ee33117267e.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I tried Manjaro’s KDE on a partition and… I haven’t switched back. And I put another installation on a second computer. I was concerned because the word on the street is that KDE is a death-by-a-thousand-options system, but after only an hour of figuring out lingo, I was able to get things set up the way I pleased. I can much more easily set up my preferred virtual workspace environments than mucking about with Devilspie – even on a two-screen setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, now I get better integration with KDE Connect, a great application. Running it over Wireguard makes for seamless connections between my phone and computer. KDE Connect worked in MATE, but it was always somewhat clunky to get going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And other KDE apps are quite good, too – Kate is a great text editor. Okular works far better than I remembered from the last time I tried it. Manjaro’s KDE has Online Accounts (either a fork or implementation of Gnome Online Accounts) so setting up Nextcloud was a breeze. And while I expected to use Kmail, Manjaro opted for Thunderbird for email. I gave up on Thunderbird in favor of Evolution a few years back because Thunderbird seemed resource-intensive, but I was pleasantly surprised to find Thunderbird is very snappy – and those tab views are great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jellyfin&quot;&gt;Jellyfin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been watching Jellyfin for a long time, but I kept using Plex to serve movies and TV shows from my Raspberry Pi to my TV and other devices. Lately, however, Plex stopped working as it used to – I recall seeing something about reinstalling it. (Maybe they made some sort of change and I didn’t notice?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/7eb77281fb804b4437507a7e39811b72.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jellyfin Logo&quot; title=&quot;Jellyfin Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I thought I’d try Jellyfin and… wow! Between it and Wireguard, I can serve movies, TV, and music to any of my devices, anywhere. It’s like my own personal streaming system. Jellyfin makes a nice app in F-Droid for Android devices, or I can use the web interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while I work on the new book project (by flipping through virtual workspaces in KDE) I can listen to Herbie Hancock’s magnificent album [&lt;em&gt;Maiden Voyage&lt;/em&gt;](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maiden_Voyage_(Herbie_Hancock_album).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very Kool. (sorry.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="KDE" /><category term="Manjaro" /><summary type="html">KDE Just a quick note to say that I took the plunge: after many, many years of using MATE desktops, I’ve tried KDE Plasma. I really, really like it. And I’ve also had some fun with Jellyfin – so much so it’s goodbye, Plex.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds, Environment and Labor Edition</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/21/FossFinds2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds, Environment and Labor Edition" /><published>2022-01-21T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/21/FossFinds2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/21/FossFinds2.html">&lt;p&gt;In this week’s FOSS finds, I’m thinking about the environmental impact of tech and I gathered sources on Marak’s refusal to keep giving away code. I’m including a few examples here to show my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keilbach-judith-and-michał-pabiś-2021-greening-media-studies-european-journal-of-media-studies-10-2-10512&quot;&gt;Keilbach, Judith, and Michał Pabiś. 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://mediarep.org/bitstream/handle/doc/18203/NECSUS_2021_10_2_105-112_Keilbach_Pabis-Orzeszyna_Greening_Media_Studies_.pdf?sequence=2&quot;&gt;“Green(Ing) Media (Studies).”&lt;/a&gt; European Journal of Media Studies 10 (2): 105–12.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this journal article, Keilback and Pabiś note that “Various [media studies] authors are pointing out that every media product (content or device) is based on the extraction of raw material and creates an enormous amount of waste, thereby emphasising the finite nature of Earth’s resources.” However, “While there is no doubt that these publications are extremely valuable, the state of our planet leaves us wondering if this is all media scholars can do. Given the climate emergency, we both consider the transition of media studies towards a more environmentally aware discipline imperative.” They go on to distinguish eco-modernism, the idea that we can use technology to avoid the climate catastrophe while still maintaining economic growth, with degrowth thinking, which suggests that the imperative to grow is the reason why we’re in this mess, and that de-growing the use of technology has to be on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tags: environment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-file-media-festival-nd-small-file-media-festival-accessed-january-17-2022&quot;&gt;“Small File Media Festival.” n.d. &lt;a href=&quot;https://smallfile.ca/&quot;&gt;Small File Media Festival&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed January 17, 2022.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This media festival, which celebrates videos that weigh in at less than 5MB, is cited by Keilbach and Pabis as an example of degrowth. Rather than making HD movies – and hence taking up more and more bandwidth and energy – the Small File approach is to make small art that can still move audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tags: environment, alternative cultural production&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sharma-ax-2022-dev-corrupts-npm-libs-colors-and-faker-breaking-thousands-of-apps-bleepingcomputer-january-9-2022&quot;&gt;Sharma, Ax. 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/dev-corrupts-npm-libs-colors-and-faker-breaking-thousands-of-apps/&quot;&gt;“Dev Corrupts NPM Libs ‘colors’ and ‘Faker’ Breaking Thousands of Apps.”&lt;/a&gt; BleepingComputer. January 9, 2022.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a big story in the past few weeks. A Javascript library developer named Marak has corrupted his own code and pushed it to Github, causing applications to break. Marak’s stated reason is that corporations are making a fortune by using his code, but he himself cannot pay his bills. There’s a lot to discuss, but this incident is interesting to me in that it’s at once a story about #politicaleconomy – how can devs get compensated for their work? – and also about #security. In this sense, human security. Can we have FOSS security if developers can’t eat? (Hint: I don’t think so).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tags: political economy, security&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dodrill-christine-2021-open-source-is-broken-or-why-i-dont-write-useful-software-unless-you-pay-me-xe-blog-december-11-2021&quot;&gt;Dodrill, Christine. 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://christine.website/blog/open-source-broken-2021-12-11&quot;&gt;“‘Open Source’ Is Broken, or, Why I Don’t Write Useful Software Unless You Pay Me.”&lt;/a&gt; Xe (blog). December 11, 2021.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, Xe discusses why they won’t code unless it’s for money. Why not? Because to provide free software is to be exploited by large corporations. The Marak case wasn’t even on the radar at this point (at least, I don’t think it was); rather, Xe is referring to the work of patching the Java vulnerability in Log4j2, which was done at a fast pace over the holidays and was not compensated. Xe argues that, if a corporation is so dependant on a FOSS library, they ought to at least donate money to the devs who maintain the library. As they write, “I’ve had this kind of conversation with people before and I’ve gotten a surprising amount of resistance to the prospect of actually making sure that the random smattering of volunteers that LITERALLY MAKE THEIR COMPANY RUN are able to make rent. There is this culture of taking from open source without giving anything back. It is like the problems of the people who make the dependencies are irrelevant.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tags: political economy, security&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="FOSS Finds" /><summary type="html">In this week’s FOSS finds, I’m thinking about the environmental impact of tech and I gathered sources on Marak’s refusal to keep giving away code. I’m including a few examples here to show my work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/11/FOSSFinds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds" /><published>2022-01-11T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/11/FOSSFinds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/11/FOSSFinds.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently announced my &lt;a href=&quot;2022/01/06/Goal2.html&quot;&gt;new book project&lt;/a&gt;, focusing on ethical FOSS social media, and I’m trying an experiment in writing it openly. That’s Goal 2 of this blog (Goal 1 being discussions of my actually using FOSS to complete this task). To that end, I’ve decided to share items I’ve found as I do my research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m calling it FOSS Finds, because alliteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/detective_penguin.png&quot; alt=&quot;A cartoon penguin doing an impression of Sherlock Holmes&quot; title=&quot;A cartoon penguin doing an impression of Sherlock Holmes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are typically going to be websites, blogposts, podcasts, or academic research. They may or may not be very recent. I plan on including a citation (exported, of course, from Zotero) and a brief note about each, a la an annotated bibliography, and versions of my Zotero tags. The notes won’t be exhaustive – it’s really about what I’m collecting at this stage, rather than analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;broadcasting-jupiter-nd-saving-podcasting-from-centralization-linux-unplugged-accessed-january-11-2022&quot;&gt;Broadcasting, Jupiter. n.d. &lt;a href=&quot;https://linuxunplugged.com/440&quot;&gt;“Saving Podcasting from Centralization.”&lt;/a&gt; Linux Unplugged. Accessed January 11, 2022.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this 9 January 2022 podcast episode, Chris Fisher interviews Dave Jones of Podcastingindex.org. They discuss the threats of centralization happening to podcasting, not only from existing corporations such as Apple or Spotify but also Alphabet (by way of Youtube). Jones talks at length of updates to RSS that provide independent podcasters with features, such as soundbytes, transcripts, and payments. Jones talks at length about using blockchains for push notifications and for payments to independent podcasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tags: alternative cultural industries; political economy; non-centralization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;balkan-aral-2020-what-is-the-small-web-aral-balkan-august-7-2020&quot;&gt;Balkan, Aral. 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ar.al/2020/08/07/what-is-the-small-web/&quot;&gt;“What Is the Small Web?”&lt;/a&gt; Aral Balkan. August 7, 2020.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, Balkan uses an interesting metaphor: we are renting space on the corporate servers of Facebook et al. We pay our rent with our attention, privacy, and data. In contrast, we can and should own our own servers, much as we would our own homes. But unlike home ownership, running a server should be as easy as renting. This is thus an abstract for a design of self-hosting software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tags: identity; political economy; scale&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linux-lounge-2021-the-story-of-xenia---linuxs-forgotten-mascot&quot;&gt;Linux Lounge. 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0b4eW1KAuWE&quot;&gt;The Story of Xenia - Linux’s Forgotten Mascot!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, an artist was unhappy with Tux being the Linux mascot and designed a fox named Xenia. 20 years later, someone rediscovers Xenia and draws her as a girl. The original artist noted Xenia was initially a boy, but that the transition makes sense in the light of trans Linux users. Xenia thus becomes not just a Linux mascot, but a trans rights in tech mascot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tags: identity; Linux; Xenia (Linux Mascot)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="FOSS Finds" /><summary type="html">I recently announced my new book project, focusing on ethical FOSS social media, and I’m trying an experiment in writing it openly. That’s Goal 2 of this blog (Goal 1 being discussions of my actually using FOSS to complete this task). To that end, I’ve decided to share items I’ve found as I do my research. I’m calling it FOSS Finds, because alliteration. These are typically going to be websites, blogposts, podcasts, or academic research. They may or may not be very recent. I plan on including a citation (exported, of course, from Zotero) and a brief note about each, a la an annotated bibliography, and versions of my Zotero tags. The notes won’t be exhaustive – it’s really about what I’m collecting at this stage, rather than analysis.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goal 2, Initiate</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/06/Goal2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goal 2, Initiate" /><published>2022-01-06T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/06/Goal2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/06/Goal2.html">&lt;p&gt;For about a year I’ve been teasing at Goal 2 for this blog, which is to write a book about FOSS. It’s probably not surprising to hear that I needed to narrow that focus down. FOSS is a massive phenomenon, and any given area within it deserves lengthy analysis. For example, Biella Coleman’s classic book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.powells.com/book/coding-freedom-the-ethics-aesthetics-of-hacking-9780691144610&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Coding Freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; focuses heavily on the Debian distribution. One could imagine similar books about the Linux Kernel, or Canonical, or Arch, or web servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given my background as a scholar, however, it makes sense that I should pursue a &lt;strong&gt;book-length project focusing on FOSS social media.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beyond-corporate-social-media&quot;&gt;Beyond Corporate Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has read my previous scholarship knows I’ve been critical of corporate social media (e.g., Meta/Facebook/Instagram, Twitter, Pinterest, Youtube) and what we once called “web 2.0” applications (e.g., Google search) since before it was cool. However, I have also consistently called for critics to explore alternatives to corporate media. In my view, it’s not enough to critique – we have to find ways forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been studying alternative social media for almost a decade now, and until recently it’s felt like a lonely field of research. After all, as loudly as I play the role of Old Man Shaking Fist at (the Corporate) Cloud, no one seemed to listen. Everyone is still using Facebook et al, despite years of emotional manipulation, whistleblowing, and data leaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, lately, the alternatives are getting a lot of attention. And it seems to be the wrong kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alternative-social-media-becomes-alt-tech&quot;&gt;Alternative Social Media becomes Alt-Tech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my concerns about corporate social media – namely, its power to manipulate what we see – seems to be shared by the alt-right. I’m talking, of course, of Gab.com and the forthcoming Trump social network, Truth. However, in many ways, the alt-tech social media platforms simply replicate many of the features of corporate social media (most notably centralization and monetization) while wallowing in hate speech and misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thus don’t see them as true alternatives. But what would make a true alternative? That, it seems to me, is the heart of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;towards-ethical-citizens-social-media&quot;&gt;Towards Ethical, Citizens’ Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If alternative only means not-Facebook, it’s not really an alternative. And if alternative means “speak your mind, fascists!,” I’m not interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t have to flee from fascists into the cold bosom of Mark Zuckerberg just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are alternatives that not only help us get away from surveillance capitalism, but also actively push out fascists and hate-speech mongers. They aren’t just decentralized; they are &lt;em&gt;non&lt;/em&gt;-centralized. They can be run by any of us with the technical abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the people running them have values such as collective ownership, democratic control, and concern with environmental impact of media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And arising from these platforms are artists and creators who are helping imagine a better mediascape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These social media may well adhere to media scholar Clemencia Rodríguez’s call for “citizens’ media,” media that we not only participate in, but own and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a key example of this is Mastodon, the federated Twitter alternative. However, the fediverse is bigger than Mastodon, so I will have to explore systems such as PeerTube or Pixelfed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-foss&quot;&gt;What about FOSS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a big part of this equation is FOSS. Free and open source software provides a necessary – but not sufficient – ingredient. After all, Gab and Truth run on FOSS (specifically, forks of Mastodon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this book is going to be about FOSS alternative social media, and if I adhere to my critical orientation towards citizens’ media, then the book will have to explore how activists are taking FOSS and associating it with other elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I see it, the elements would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;political economy: how are these media governed? How are they paid for?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;environment: how are FOSS alternative operators addressing the environmental impact of networked media?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ethics: what sort of ethical standards do these systems adhere to?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cultural production: what forms of cultural production emerge from FOSS alternative social media?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;security: how do these media address security concerns? Not just cybersecurity, but insecurity arising from disinformation and manipulative communication?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identity: how do these media map onto or influence how we conceive of ourselves?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;relation to other media: how do the FOSS alternatives relate to other media, such as corporate social media, broadcast media, or “alt-tech”?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-plan-of-the-book&quot;&gt;The Plan of the Book&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My plan for the book, then, is to look at FOSS-based, ethical alternative social media through the above categorical lenses. I don’t imagine that each of the above points would be chapters, but any one of them or combinations of them might.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the points above are now tags in my Zotero library, allowing me to start sorting the materials into folders that might just give rise to chapters. I plan to blog about these categories here on FOSS Academic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also plan on publicly doing a lit review – offering thoughts on key texts that are relevant to the project. I mentioned Biella Coleman’s book &lt;em&gt;Coding Freedom&lt;/em&gt; above – that’s definitely on the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, watch this space as Goal 2 proceeds!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments? I’m currently using Mastodon to handle them, so if you have a Mastodon (or other federated) account, feel free to leave a comment!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">For about a year I’ve been teasing at Goal 2 for this blog, which is to write a book about FOSS. It’s probably not surprising to hear that I needed to narrow that focus down. FOSS is a massive phenomenon, and any given area within it deserves lengthy analysis. For example, Biella Coleman’s classic book Coding Freedom focuses heavily on the Debian distribution. One could imagine similar books about the Linux Kernel, or Canonical, or Arch, or web servers. Given my background as a scholar, however, it makes sense that I should pursue a book-length project focusing on FOSS social media.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Test post for Mastodon Comments</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/12/16/CommentsTest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Test post for Mastodon Comments" /><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/12/16/CommentsTest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/12/16/CommentsTest.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been struggling with having comments on this Jekyll-based static site for a while. For a bit, I used Staticman, but that died for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, it hit me: so many sites use Facebook comments. Why can’t I use Mastodon, the FOSS alternative social media system, to do something similar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.xmgz.eu/jekyll-mastodon-comment/&quot;&gt;this guide&lt;/a&gt; provided all the code I could need to do exactly that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is a test run. Feel free to comment on it using your Mastodon account. (I think other federated accounts might work, but not sure – if so, let me know in the comments!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a Mastodon account, don’t worry! You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://joinmastodon.org&quot;&gt;sign up for an instance&lt;/a&gt; and join the federated fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-1&quot;&gt;UPDATE #1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tested it a bit and have found a few things that give me pause:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It does not respect the distinction between Unlisted and Public privacy settings. Both will show up here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; respect DM – that is, DMs do not show up as comments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;It does not respect Content Warnings.&lt;/del&gt; This has been fixed; see Update #3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that in mind, I think I may keep it (pending further testing) and include a warning in the “Comments” section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-2&quot;&gt;UPDATE #2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to another Mastodoner, I found that if anyone who uses Mastodon to comment on a blog post deletes said comment, then it will also no longer appear on the blog. I think that’s a cool feature, but I’m thinking that I have be &lt;em&gt;extremely clear&lt;/em&gt; about what happens when people comment on my blog. It’s going to be public – very public – not just in the federation, but also on my website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’m not 100% certain this is wise. I’d love to get more opinions from Mastodon users. Feel free to leave them in the comments – or, to be certain that your opinion is expressed privately, DM me (@robertwgehl@scholar.social).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-3&quot;&gt;UPDATE #3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://mastodon.acc.sunet.se/@ashwinvis&quot;&gt;@ashwinvis&lt;/a&gt;, the comments system now supports Content Warnings. @ashwinvis wrote a few lines of Javascript that did the trick, resulting in CWs appearing with a small dropdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">I’ve been struggling with having comments on this Jekyll-based static site for a while. For a bit, I used Staticman, but that died for some reason. Then, it hit me: so many sites use Facebook comments. Why can’t I use Mastodon, the FOSS alternative social media system, to do something similar? Fortunately, this guide provided all the code I could need to do exactly that! So this is a test run. Feel free to comment on it using your Mastodon account. (I think other federated accounts might work, but not sure – if so, let me know in the comments!) If you don’t have a Mastodon account, don’t worry! You can sign up for an instance and join the federated fun. UPDATE #1 I’ve tested it a bit and have found a few things that give me pause: It does not respect the distinction between Unlisted and Public privacy settings. Both will show up here. It does respect DM – that is, DMs do not show up as comments. It does not respect Content Warnings. This has been fixed; see Update #3. With all that in mind, I think I may keep it (pending further testing) and include a warning in the “Comments” section. UPDATE #2 Thanks to another Mastodoner, I found that if anyone who uses Mastodon to comment on a blog post deletes said comment, then it will also no longer appear on the blog. I think that’s a cool feature, but I’m thinking that I have be extremely clear about what happens when people comment on my blog. It’s going to be public – very public – not just in the federation, but also on my website. However, I’m not 100% certain this is wise. I’d love to get more opinions from Mastodon users. Feel free to leave them in the comments – or, to be certain that your opinion is expressed privately, DM me (@robertwgehl@scholar.social). UPDATE #3 Thanks to @ashwinvis, the comments system now supports Content Warnings. @ashwinvis wrote a few lines of Javascript that did the trick, resulting in CWs appearing with a small dropdown. I love FOSS.</summary></entry></feed>