<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-30T21:53:17-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>First, one goal is to explore life as a “FOSS Academic” – someone who uses Free and Open Source technologies to do academic work. I’m hoping that my discussions of FOSS technologies in an academic setting help others – students, professors, university administrators – understand the benefits and values of FOSS in the academy. I’m not a developer, but I am a professor who’s been using FOSS to do his job for over a decade. I call this goal of exploring FOSS tools in the academy Goal 1. Second, this blog has Goal 2: writing a book about a FOSS topic. After some consideration, I decided to write a book about Mastodon and the fediverse. It should be out in 2025. Sometimes, the two topics will collide in a single post. My intent here is to be more open about my own research process and writing.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Sharing my book, one random bit at a time</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/06/30/book-bot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sharing my book, one random bit at a time" /><published>2025-06-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-06-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/06/30/book-bot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/06/30/book-bot.html"><![CDATA[<p>No one will accuse me of being a Python expert, but I have increasingly been using it to take care of tasks. For example, if I build a website, I now often use Markdown or CSV files to store the data for the site, process it with Python, and then push it to whatever server its hosted on. This time, however, I made something that certainly was a challenge for me: a bot to post random bits of <a href="https://academic.oup.com/book/60528">my new book</a> to the fediverse.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="hard-stuff-made-easier-by-others">Hard Stuff Made Easier By Others</h2>
<p>I say this was challenging for me, and it was, but I think people with Python skills will see this as relatively easy.</p>

<p>I drew on the template provided by <a href="https://codeberg.org/stfn/mastodon-bot-template">stfn on Codeberg</a>. This approach is built for Mastodon and relies on the <a href="https://mastodonpy.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">Mastodon.py project</a>, which itself provides a wrapper around the Mastodon API.</p>

<p>The first step is initialization, where I get an access token from my <a href="https://aoir.social/@rwg">Mastodon account</a> and add that to a .env file. (This is a secret key, so if you do this, as well, don’t share your key!). I used my AoIR.social account because I am reasonably confident this bot would not run afoul of our Code of Conduct. In fact, I’m one of the admins there, so I am pretty sure we’re cool with this sort of thing – but of course, some fediverse instances don’t allow bots, so be sure to check on that.</p>

<p>As for the Python code itself, stfn’s approach breaks things down into to Python scripts: main.py and services.py. The main.py script is the one to run to actually post to the Mastodon account and really doesn’t need much modification.</p>

<p>The services.py account, by contrast, needs quite a bit. Here’s my version:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>import os
import csv
import random
from mastodon import Mastodon


class ConfigService:
    """Service for validating environmental variables"""
    def validate_config(self) -&gt; bool:
        return all(
            [
                os.getenv("CLIENT_ID"),
                os.getenv("CLIENT_SECRET"),
                os.getenv("ACCESS_TOKEN"),
                os.getenv("API_BASE_URL"),
            ]
        )


class BotService:
    """Service for generating the toots"""
    def prepare_toot_body(self):
        # opening the book CSV file and processing a quote
        with open('book.csv') as f:
          reader = csv.reader(f)
          bookquote = random.choice(list(reader))
          bookquote = str(bookquote)
          bookquote = bookquote.replace('\', \'', ',')
          bookquote = bookquote.replace('[\'', '')
          bookquote = bookquote.replace('\']', '')
          # trimming the quote back in characters to the nearest full stop
          bookquote = bookquote[:297]
          reversesearch = bookquote.rfind('. ')
          if(reversesearch != -1):
            bookquote = bookquote[:reversesearch+1]
          # writing out the post
          spoiler_text = "Daily random quote out of context from my academic book about Mastodon"
          body = '''The following is a random quote from my next book, Move Slowly and Build Bridges:

''' + bookquote + '''...

#MoveSlowlyAndBuildBridges #bot'''
          return body
          return spoiler_text


class MastodonService:
    """Service for handling comms with Mastodon"""
    def __init__(self):
        self.mastodon = Mastodon(
            client_id=os.getenv("CLIENT_ID"),
            client_secret=os.getenv("CLIENT_SECRET"),
            access_token=os.getenv("ACCESS_TOKEN"),
            api_base_url=os.getenv("API_BASE_URL"),
        )

    def post(self, body, **kwargs):
        self.mastodon.status_post(body, spoiler_text="Daily random quote out of context from my academic book about Mastodon", language="en", **kwargs)
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>As you can see, I used Python’s CSV and Random modules. I took the raw text of my book and converted it into a .CSV file, where each paragraph becomes a row. The Python reads the CSV file. Then I took the random module to select a random paragraph. After that, I trimmed the quote back to 297 characters to the nearest period. That way the “toot” would stay within the character limit.</p>

<p>I added a Content Warning because, although my instance might be OK with bots, I wanted to make sure it was crystal clear to other fediverse folks that these posts are automatically generated.</p>

<p>Finally, I copied the scripts over to a Raspberry Pi server I run and set it to post every day at 9.00 am EST.</p>

<h2 id="stuff-i-wish-i-did-differently">Stuff I Wish I Did Differently</h2>

<p>The bot is working well, but I wish I had done a few things differently.</p>

<p>First, I should have simply randomly sorted the CSV rows and then had the bot post them in that random order. That’s because the bot has already posted a couple passages twice.</p>

<p>Second, I should have double-checked the paragraphs. There are a few block quotes in the book – lengthy quotes, typically from interviewees. When those get posted, it appears I’m claiming their words as my own. When that happens, I use Mastodon’s edit feature to fix it, and I add a reply comment specifying where the quote comes from.</p>

<p>Finally, sometimes the bot doesn’t run, and I suspect it’s because the quote plus content warning and link are all over the character limit. I should have built in some logging to see when this happens and fix it.</p>

<p>However, over all this has been a fun project – a way to share bits of my book with the fediverse while also learning a bit more about Python and Mastodon bots.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="publications" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[No one will accuse me of being a Python expert, but I have increasingly been using it to take care of tasks. For example, if I build a website, I now often use Markdown or CSV files to store the data for the site, process it with Python, and then push it to whatever server its hosted on. This time, however, I made something that certainly was a challenge for me: a bot to post random bits of my new book to the fediverse.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Move Slowly and Build Bridges Cover Reveal</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/06/02/move-slowly-cover.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Move Slowly and Build Bridges Cover Reveal" /><published>2025-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/06/02/move-slowly-cover</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/06/02/move-slowly-cover.html"><![CDATA[<p>The cover for <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/move-slowly-and-build-bridges-9780197776681?lang=en&amp;cc=ca"><em>Move Slowly and Build Bridge: Mastodon, the Fediverse, and the Struggle for Democratic Social Media</em></a> has been revealed!</p>

<!-- more -->

<figure>
  <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/move-slowly-and-build-bridges-9780197776681?lang=en&amp;cc=ca"><img src="/assets/images/moveSlowly.png" alt="the cover of Move Slowly and Build Bridges, a book by Robert W. Gehl" /></a>
</figure>

<p>This cover features artwork, “Untitled no 7,” from the <a href="https://artistmarciax.com/">artist Marcia X</a>. In addition to being an artist, Marcia is a key figure in the development of the <a href="https://subscribers.artistmarciax.com/fediblock-a-tiny-history-2/">#fediblock hashtag</a>, which is an essential tool for moderation on the fediverse. Marcia was one of the first folks to talk to me about the fediverse, right at the start of my planning of this book, and their insights into its history – including its troubling history for people of color and Black folks – had a massive impact on the shape of <em>Move Slowly</em>.</p>

<p>Oh, and Marcia is a DJ, as well. I’ve had writing sessions listening to her <a href="https://artistmarciax.com/dj-sets/">Afro-Caribbean techno jams</a>.</p>

<p>I selected “Untitled no 7” because I felt the kaleidoscopic image held connections and fragmentation – I hope it’s clear how this kind of tension is a key part of the book, as well as fediverse history. I see the fediverse as existing between individuals’ ability to link to each other and the ability for communities to sever connections, and often the decision to connect or defederate hinges on deeply-seated aspects of identity. Marcia and their experience figure heavily into a chapter that dives into that tension, so I was very happy she agreed to let Oxford use their art for the cover.</p>

<p>The book isn’t out yet but you can <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/move-slowly-and-build-bridges-9780197776681?lang=en&amp;cc=ca">preorder it</a> as a hardcover, paperback, or e-book directly from Oxford.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Move Slowly and Build Bridges" /><category term="publications" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The cover for Move Slowly and Build Bridge: Mastodon, the Fediverse, and the Struggle for Democratic Social Media has been revealed!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Ain’t Gonna Work on ChatGPT’s Farm No More</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/05/08/ai-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Ain’t Gonna Work on ChatGPT’s Farm No More" /><published>2025-05-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-05-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/05/08/ai-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/05/08/ai-review.html"><![CDATA[<p>I think I’m going to get a reputation – if I don’t have it already – of being one of <em>those</em> people. Those people who really don’t like generative AI.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>My latest ponderings about the problems of generative AI center on academic publishing – specifically, performing service as a peer reviewer. By my count, over the past 15 years, I’ve reviewed 150 items – journal article submissions, conference papers, and book manuscripts. That’s an average of 10 a year.</p>

<p>Until recently, my biggest worry about this process was the fact that I am doing free labor that <a href="https://tidsskriftet.no/en/2020/08/kronikk/money-behind-academic-publishing">benefits highly profitable corporations</a>. To mitigate this, I’ve tried hard to do more peer reviews for genuinely nonprofit organizations, rather than the SAGEs and Taylor Francises of the world. But then again, I often do reviews for journals owned by those companies, so I am also very supportive of calls to <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736\(21\)02804-X/fulltext">pay for peer reviews</a>.</p>

<p>Now, however, I’m adding a new concern: that I’m not always reviewing the arguments, ideas, and thoughts of my fellow academics – some of the time I’m reviewing the outputs of machines.</p>

<h2 id="improving-the-methods-section-generated-by-chatgpt">Improving the Methods Section Generated by ChatGPT</h2>
<p>I’m talking of course of generative AI. ChatGPT, which has largely kicked of this craze, is already being used to generate text that is making it into academic journals. <em>Retraction Watch</em> <a href="https://retractionwatch.com/papers-and-peer-reviews-with-evidence-of-chatgpt-writing/">has found over 100 articles</a> with material obviously generated by that system. Alex Glynn’s tracker has <a href="https://www.academ-ai.info/">700+ suspected papers</a>.</p>

<p>That sounds like a lot. But David Crotty of <em>Scholarly Kitchen</em> <a href="https://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2024/03/20/the-latest-crisis-is-the-research-literature-overrun-with-chatgpt-and-llm-generated-articles/">is tamping down a bit on the panic</a>, doing some analysis in 2024 and finding that only a tiny percentage of articles have material generated by ChatGPT, and even those are <em>about</em> ChatGPT. (Indeed, <a href="https://www.degruyterbrill.com/document/doi/10.1515/9783110792270-007/html">I’ve written something that quotes ChatGPT purposely</a> to make a point about generative AI.) But even so, he concludes by stating, “there’s no room for complacency” in relation to generative AI language being published in academic journals, “and research integrity vigilance will only become more and more demanding.”</p>

<p>I agree. LLMs are a new phenomenon, and academic publishing is slow. I imagine that the number of submitted articles that include LLM-generated material will only increase. And it will be less obvious than the 100 clumsy examples <em>Retraction Watch</em> found – LLM-generated academic articles will be nearly indistiguishable from human-written papers.</p>

<p>That means peer reviewers like me will increasingly have to read, analyze, and comment upon computer-generated ideas. I might be asked to read a ChatGPT-generated methods section and critically consider if… what? If ChatGPT’s methods are sound? If the researchers’ methods are sound? Whose work am I analyzing?</p>

<p>I think that’s a major problem.</p>

<h2 id="existing-policies-sound-good-until-they-dont">Existing Policies Sound Good Until They Don’t</h2>
<p>It seems that publishers are thinking about this, and there are policies in place. But the problem I see is that the positions of publishers are contradictory.</p>

<p>Take for example <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/home/nms"><em>New Media &amp; Society</em></a> (NMS), a journal that has published my work and counts me as a member of the editorial board (which means I do a <em>ton</em> of reviews for them).</p>

<p>NMS is a member of the Committee on Publication Ethics (COPE). COPE <a href="https://publicationethics.org/guidance/cope-position/authorship-and-ai-tools">has a policy on generative AI</a>. This <a href="https://publicationethics.org/guidance/cope-position/authorship-and-ai-tools">policy states</a> that authors</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>who use AI tools in the writing of a manuscript, production of images or graphical elements of the paper, or in the collection and analysis of data, must be transparent in disclosing in the Materials and Methods (or similar section) of the paper how the AI tool was used and which tool was used. Authors are fully responsible for the content of their manuscript, even those parts produced by an AI tool, and are thus liable for any breach of publication ethics.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I can get with this. If authors who use generative AI disclose what corporate entity’s tool they used and how they used it, I can make a decision about doing the work of reviewing the article.</p>

<p>However, <em>New Media &amp; Society</em> is published by SAGE. In its <a href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/artificial-intelligence-policy">policy on AI</a>, SAGE itself echoes COPE in stating</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>The use of AI tools that can produce content such as generating references, text, images or any other form of content must be disclosed when used by authors or reviewers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It also says authors who use generative AI should</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>clearly indicate the use of language models in the manuscript, including which model was used and for what purpose. Please use the methods or acknowledgements section, as appropriate.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So far, so good.</p>

<p>But SAGE also carves out a space for “assistive AI,” stating,</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>AI tools that make suggestions to improve or enhance your own work, such as tools to improve language, grammar or structure, are considered assistive AI tools and do not require disclosure by authors or reviewers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Man, that’s a <em>thin</em> line. So, authors don’t have to say they used generative AI to improve their language, but they do have to disclose if they used it for generating text? What’s the distinction here?</p>

<p>In fields like mine, <em>words matter.</em> Think of all the digital ink spilled about terms like “platforms” or “networks” or “influencers” or “surveillance.” Think of all the adjectives applied to them over the years – <em>generative, lateral, sharing, fast, micro, ubiquitous,</em> etc, etc. Then think of ways to define these terms, operationalize them as concepts to analyze social practices, and present one’s findings. It’s language all the way down. “Improve” (which is to say, “alter”) any bit of that with an assistive device and the meanings change – sometimes subtly, sometimes overtly, often profoundly.</p>

<p>So the “help with language but don’t generate text” distinction doesn’t really work for me. And this is not to mention “structure” – I read that and think about the overall organization and coherence of the article, which is actually an area many of my reviews end up addressing.</p>

<p>I would say that, if an author uses a generative AI tool, even for “language help,” I ought to know about it before I review. Disclose if you used generative AI for editing and grammar. Oh, and tell me what corporation’s product you’re using. I deserve to know.</p>

<h2 id="whom-am-i-reviewing-and-for-whom-am-i-working">Whom Am I Reviewing? And for Whom Am I Working?</h2>
<p>That’s my main point: I want to review the ideas of fellow humans, not the outputs of machines. Therefore, I need to know from journals and authors whether or not generative AI was used at <em>any</em> point in the process of writing the article. Then I can make a decision. Otherwise, I think it’s inevitable that I will be doing the work of improving the output of a machine rather than offering guidance and ideas to a fellow researcher. That cheapens the whole process.</p>

<p>And beyond the insult of having to improve the logic of machines instead of helping my academic peers, I also am concerned that my reviews – which take hours of work to write – will be fed into machines without my consent. This could be done by the authors, who want an LLM to help them figure out how to revise based on my review. I’m assuming any authors who use LLMs to write their articles would do this, so, again, I want to know.</p>

<p>Or it could be done by the press, which is interested in making a review machine.</p>

<p>On that last note, I can’t help but think that this explains the language/text distinction SAGE is proposing in their policy. It may well reflect a <a href="https://www.thebookseller.com/news/sage-confirms-it-is-in-talks-to-license-content-to-ai-firms">desire to sell the text of its publications to generative AI firms</a>. Their AI policy is quite celebratory:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Sage recognises the value of artificial intelligence (AI) and its potential to help authors in the research and writing process. Sage welcomes developments in this area to enhance opportunities for generating ideas, accelerating research discovery, synthesising, or analysing findings, polishing language, or structuring a submission.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No doubt these deals might result in “assistive technologies” that are marketed to authors, “tools” that can help improve a text but (so it is claimed) won’t do the thinking for the author, peer reviewer assistance, and so on.</p>

<p>There are already <a href="https://consensus.app">services that claim to use AI</a> to find sources and generate text. <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/ca/acrobat/using/ai-generated-summaries.html">Adobe offers</a> to generate a summary based on an article. Jenni.ai offers <a href="https://jenni.ai/">“AI autocomplete”</a> to “beat writer’s block.”</p>

<p>Again: where’s the line? At some point “assistance” becomes “generation.” Or rather, maybe everything becomes mere “assistance.”</p>

<p>And then peer reviewers like me have to review it.</p>

<h2 id="postscript-since-i-know-youre-thinking-it">Postscript, Since I Know You’re Thinking It</h2>
<p>Oh, and in case you’re wondering: no, I will not use generative AI to assist me with my reviews.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="goal 1" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I think I’m going to get a reputation – if I don’t have it already – of being one of those people. Those people who really don’t like generative AI.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Copyediting: The Bane of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/04/06/copyediting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Copyediting: The Bane of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream" /><published>2025-04-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-04-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/04/06/copyediting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/04/06/copyediting.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m starting this post with a specific passage from my upcoming book. It’s important for context.</p>

<p>I conducted interviews as part of the research for <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/move-slowly-and-build-bridges-9780197776681"><em>Move Slowly and Build Bridges</em></a>. In my “Research Note,” I write:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I stored the interview data and notes on a self-hosted Nextcloud server, and I transcribed interviews myself. I did this to avoid storing data or passing interview audio through third-party cloud services, because I am quite certain few if any fediverse members consent to have their ideas supplied to train large language models, as is now happening to data stored in Google or Microsoft services. I realize that this book will be digitally scanned, and thus AI companies may be tempted to use it in their training data. For what it’s worth: I do not consent to have any portion of this book be used to train a large language model (LLM) or similar system. I do not believe any of my interviewees would consent to have their ideas used to train LLMs, either.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I worked very hard to maintain this position throughout the writing process. My notes were stored on self-hosted infrastructure (or, in the case of Zotero, in a non-public library). I drafted much of the document in Zettlr and LibreOffice on local files. I never ran anything through corporate cloud services. I was going to once again write a book without relying on corporate infrastructure.</p>

<p>But then I faced copyediting.</p>

<h2 id="the-copyediting-phase">The Copyediting Phase</h2>
<p>Copyediting a book is a major part of the process of writing one. After <em>years</em> of note-taking, drafting, writing, refining, responding to peer reviews, refining further, copyediting is the moment when someone other than the author – the copyeditor – goes through the manuscript line-by-line and corrects small errors, revises ackward sentences, and clarifies.</p>

<p>For <em>Move Slowly</em>, Oxford hired <a href="https://reedsy.com/leslie-anglin">Leslie Anglin</a>. Leslie did a superlative job. I’m really, really happy with the results – it’s my writing but improved and with far less errors. (Thank you, Leslie!)</p>

<p>Copyeditors of course need tools to do this work. Over the course of my four books, the tool I’ve seen copyeditors use again and again is, unsurprisingly, Microsoft Word. I get it – it’s ubiquitous.</p>

<p>Normally, if someone I’m working with uses Word, I have little trouble editing .DOCX files with LibreOffice. It’s not always perfect but it’s very, very workable.</p>

<p>But in the case of copyediting, copyeditors do some stuff with Word that I do not comprehend. Paragraphs, phrases, and even individual words get coded (with corresponding colors). Endnotes are handled in a specific manner. Author Queries, where the copyeditor asks the author about something to be fixed, are handled in special ways (even if they are based on standard document comments). There are track changes to consider. As savvy as I might be, copyeditors clearly have a whole other level of fluency with a word processor than me.</p>

<p>LibreOffice simply doesn’t handle the special formatting practices of copyeditors well. In the case of <em>Move Slowly,</em> I tried to review and respond to copyedits with LibreOffice Writer and it got mangled quickly. (At one point Writer was deleting words seemingly at random – not good!) As a result, as with all my prior books, I’ve had to find a way to deal Microsoft Word to complete the copyediting phase.</p>

<p>Over the years, this hasn’t been too big an issue. After all, Microsoft Word has been ubiquitous for years – I would just find a computer running it. I vividly remember sitting in a University of Utah lab during a 2014 weekend to engage with copyedits for my first book. I’ve repeated the process in computer labs at a variety of universities for the next few books.</p>

<h2 id="this-time-was-different">This Time Was Different</h2>
<p>But copyediting with Microsoft Word in 2025 is a very different matter than in 2014. Back then, Microsoft Word was installed on the computer. Now Word is a <em>service</em>. You basically need an account to use it. It’s in the cloud. And since 2023, <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/business/microsoft-ai-copilot-office-suit-1.6780630">Microsoft began adding generative AI to Word</a>.</p>

<p>And that’s a problem. I pledged to avoid running my work through cloud services or through anything associated with an LLM. Finding a machine with a “local” Word installation is not a thing these days. Uploading my book to Word 365 would have broken my heart. I’ve made it <em>so far</em> without having done this sort of thing. Would I be forced to now?</p>

<h2 id="what-about-softmaker-office">What about Softmaker Office?</h2>
<p>Then it hit me: Softmaker Office.</p>

<p>I had used Softmaker Office in the past on occasions when I simply couldn’t work with Microsoft Office files in LibreOffice. Particularly in the case of Powerpoint files, which invariably get utterly mangled in LibreOffice Impress. I had purchased a copy of Softmaker in the past – maybe it would be the solution here. It isn’t FOSS - it is proprietary. But (at least in the past) it was local to my machine.</p>

<p>So I looked at <a href="https://www.softmaker.com/en/softmaker-office">Softmaker’s site</a> and <em>almost</em> paid for a new license. And then I saw it: <a href="https://www.pcmag.com/reviews/softmaker-office">Softmaker now includes ChatGPT</a>.</p>

<p>Maaaaaybe the use of ChatGPT is optional and I could avoid it? But I wasn’t willing to risk it.</p>

<p>It seems like we can’t escape from the AI mania.</p>

<h2 id="this-one-weird-trick">This One Weird Trick</h2>
<p>I was full on despair mode at this point.</p>

<p>Look, I know for a fact my book will be fed into generative AI. I have no illusions that the passage I quoted above will help. Here’s what we’ve already seen:</p>
<ul>
  <li>In the time since I signed the contract with Oxfor UP and now, they have <a href="https://www.thebookseller.com/news/wiley-cambridge-university-press-and-oxford-university-press-confirm-ai-partnerships">entered into agreements</a> with generative AI companies. (I have not heard from the press about this, so I cannot say if my book will be included).</li>
  <li>Regardless, my book will likely be pirated, which means it will be out there with little in the way of restrictions. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2025/03/libgen-meta-openai/682093/">Meta has simply gone to pirate libraries to train LLaMA</a>. My previous work is included.</li>
  <li>And of course, during this copyediting process, surely someone at the press, or my copyeditor, moved my manuscript into a cloud service – it seems unlikely my book escaped being turned into an LLM input.</li>
</ul>

<p>But despite these facts I <em>do not want to simply give in.</em> I do not want to be forced to contribute directly to the generative AI machine.</p>

<p>It seemed that the copyediting phase would be my downfall – whether using Word or Softmaker Office, there would be a chance that my materials would feed some LLM.</p>

<p>Then, I remembered: I still have an old copy of Softmaker Office, one I bought in 2018. It’s stored on my machine as a .DEB package. Could I use that?</p>

<p>Turns out, I could. Thank you, Linux! I installed and ran that seven-year-old binary on a modern machine and it worked flawlessly. Softmaker’s compatibility with Word held up. I was able to do the copyediting queries successfully – the proof is in the proofs I just received from the press.</p>

<p>I suppose in the future I could even run this old version of Softmaker in a virtual machine and replicate this trick.</p>

<h2 id="copyediting-and-the-fald">Copyediting and the FALD</h2>
<p>Copyediting continues to be a major hurdle to the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream. While I’ve written many papers with collaborators over the years, when it comes to the peculiarities of copyediting, I have been repeatedly compelled to throw my workflow out the window and adapt. In the past, this was a minor inconvenience – just use Word for a weekend!</p>

<p>But now? Now it means agreeing to have my work be the property of Microsoft’s cloud services. Companies like Microsoft are simply claiming more and more power over the things we make. And given everything going on – particularly in the USA – I don’t see that changing before I finish up my next book.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="workflow" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m starting this post with a specific passage from my upcoming book. It’s important for context.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Academic Workflow, 2025 Edition</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/03/15/workflow2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Academic Workflow, 2025 Edition" /><published>2025-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/03/15/workflow2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/03/15/workflow2025.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a while since I blogged about how I do all my academic work using free and open source software – otherwise known as the “FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.” In fact, the last time I wrote about this was <a href="/2020/12/27/Workflow.html">2020</a>!</p>

<p>I am now wrapping up my latest book, <em>Move Slowly and Build Bridges</em>, which is a critical study of Mastodon and the fediverse. That book is the culmination of years of academic research. In this post, I will focus on how I wrote that book.</p>

<h2 id="linux">Linux</h2>
<p>I have not done anything productive with a Windows or Mac machine for… a very long time. Since 2013, probably? Anyway, <a href="/2024/05/24/fald.html">I use Linux</a>. These days I’m using <a href="https://fedoraproject.org/spins/kde">Fedora with KDE Plasma</a>, but by the time you read this I could be using something else. In any case, it’s the OS for the FALD.</p>

<h2 id="zotero">Zotero</h2>
<p>No surprises here. For me, since about 2008, it’s always begun with <a href="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</a>. So much of my work requires documenting websites, blog posts, journal articles, and other digital artifacts, and Zotero makes that easy. It integrates with my web browser, <a href="https://librewolf.net/">LibreWolf</a> – which makes sense, because LibreWolf is based on Firefox.</p>

<p>Zotero also is essential for adding citations to documents. In terms of my latest book, it has made life very easy. Usually, copyeding book manuscripts involves <em>hours</em> of editing citations – adding missing page ranges, missing cities (for books), that sort of thing. Not this time. I think Zotero has improved in how it grabs metadata from the web. My copyeditor had very few author queries for citations in <em>Move Slowly</em>.</p>

<h2 id="zettlr">Zettlr</h2>
<p>For many years, Zotero was the only Z-software for me. (Zoom <em>definitely</em> does not count). But over the course of writing my latest book, <a href="https://www.zettlr.com/">Zettlr</a> elbowed its way into the workflow.</p>

<p>Previously, I would use Zotero to take notes on artifacts. I still do. But note-taking in Zotero isn’t very synthetic – it focuses on single artifacts. That’s great for taking detailed notes on a book or article, but not so good for working out thoughts based on several artifacts.</p>

<p>Zettlr fills that role very well. It’s Markdown-based, so I can just fire it up and start writing down thoughts. It supports #hashtags, so I replicate the tagging I do in Zotero to start linking ideas together.</p>

<h2 id="libreoffice-writer">LibreOffice Writer</h2>
<p>However, while Zettlr promises that you can go from notes to publishable documents, I’m not quite there with it yet. For writing up polished documents, I turn to <a href="https://www.libreoffice.org/">LibreOffice Writer</a>. It integrates extremely well with Zotero, so I use it to compose the drafts and final drafts of books and journal articles.</p>

<h2 id="nextcloud">Nextcloud</h2>
<p><a href="https://nextcloud.com/">Nextcloud</a> is the Swiss Army knife of the FALD. I run my own Nextcloud server, and there’s <em>so much</em> I can do with it:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Nextcloud Talk</strong>: This video chat system was central to my <a href="/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html">interview-based research process</a>. Since I was interviewing people who build, run, and participate in federated social media, I did not want to use Zoom or Teams – we’ve already seen those systems invade people’s privacy and turn everything into AI. Nextcloud Talk is under my control and so I can ensure my interviewees that our conversations are private.</li>
  <li><strong>Nextcloud Appointments</strong>: I’ve <a href="/2021/09/25/Appointments.html">already written</a> about how great this system is. For scheduling interviews, I can just share a link to my Appointments page, they can pick a time that works for them (and doesn’t conflict with my Nextcloud calendar), and they automatically get a Nextcloud Talk link via email. It’s brilliant.</li>
  <li><strong>Sharing</strong>: Nextcloud makes sharing files – like informed consent documents or drafts – super easy. It also helps with collaborating with other authors.</li>
  <li><strong>Sync</strong>: Obviously, this is central. My files are ready to go on any of my computers, whether at home or at the office. In addition, if I’m away from either but able to get online, I can login to Nextcloud and edit Markdown files if I need to take notes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="marp">MARP</h2>
<p>Very often I need to present my work to audiences. For years I’d use LibreOffice Impress or – ugh! – Google Docs to make slides. Not now. <a href="/2024/12/07/marpbeautifulsoup.html">Now I use MARP</a>, which generates slides from Markdown files. I’ve written scripts that automate turning files I edit in Zettlr into slides and notes, and these can be easily shared online – with accessibility features like alt text!</p>

<h2 id="tuba">Tuba</h2>
<p>These days, you gotta promote your work. <a href="https://aoir.social/@rwg">I’m on the fediverse</a>, of course, and I traditionally have posted using Mastodon’s web interface. Lately, however, I’ve been using a desktop client called <a href="https://github.com/GeopJr/Tuba">Tuba</a> to post. It’s great – I can set it to “slow mode” where posts come in only when I refresh the interface, and it’s easy to switch between multiple accounts.</p>

<h2 id="jekyll-over-git">Jekyll over Git</h2>
<p>Finally, you’re reading this on a static <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> blog pushed to the web via Git. While I’ve had some issues with Jekyll, when it’s working, it’s very easy: just type out a Markdown file, push it via Git, and it’s online.</p>

<h2 id="back-it-up">Back It Up</h2>
<p>As the wisdom goes, if your files are in less than three different places, they’re nowhere. I use <a href="https://syncthing.net/">Syncthing</a> to sync files across my network (which itself runs over a <a href="https://www.wireguard.com/">Wireguard</a> VPN). I also pay for a <a href="https://www.borgbase.com/">Borg Base</a> account, using <a href="https://vorta.borgbase.com/">Vorta</a> to encrypt and back up my files.</p>

<h2 id="foss-academic-lifestyle-dream-still-in-effect">FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream Still In Effect</h2>
<p>It’s 2025. A lot of stuff is going wrong. But while tech oligarchs seek to run our lives, there are paths of escape. You don’t have to replicate my entire workflow. But if you want to explore escape routes from Microsoft, X, Apple, or Google, try one of the above. Try out Zotero, or maybe take a chance on running a Nextcloud server. Maybe try using LibreOffice instead of Google Docs or Microsoft Office.</p>

<p>Take a step in the direction of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream. It won’t fix the world, but it’s a start.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="fald" /><category term="workflow" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been a while since I blogged about how I do all my academic work using free and open source software – otherwise known as the “FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.” In fact, the last time I wrote about this was 2020!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Standards War?</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/03/05/standardsWar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Standards War?" /><published>2025-03-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/03/05/standardsWar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/03/05/standardsWar.html"><![CDATA[<p>While I was not surprised by the announcement, it was still sad to read the news that <a href="https://about.iftas.org/2025/03/03/iftas-service-shutdowns/">IFTAS is shutting down several of its services</a> for lack of funding. It is hard for me not to see this as another aspect of a potential “standards war” between ActivityPub and ATProto.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/railroads.jpg" alt="a collection of railroads, each clearly with different gauges" />
  <figcaption>Different standards.</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="whats-iftas">What’s IFTAS?</h2>

<p>What is (or was) IFTAS? IFTAS is the Independent Federated Trust and Safety organization,* a non-profit that was inspired by the 2022/2023 influx of people into the fediverse after Elon Musk purchased Twitter. As they wrote in an <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230816114557/https://about.iftas.org/2023/08/09/iftas-federated-trust-and-safety/">introductory blog post</a>, “More and more people were joining [Mastodon and the fediverse], and more and more people were wondering ‘if this keeps growing, how does moderation scale?’”</p>

<p>IFTAS’s founder, <a href="https://jaz.co.uk/">Jaz-Michael King</a>, successfully raised initial funds to bring the organization online. The organization ran fediverse moderator needs surveys and later developed a space for moderators to share knowledge (IFTAS Connect) as well as various blocklists that fediverse admins could import.</p>

<p>Full disclosure: <a href="https://about.iftas.org/first-50/">I gave money to IFTAS</a>. I also asked the Association of Internet Researchers (AoIR) to <a href="https://about.iftas.org/our-supporters/">give money to IFTAS</a>, since AoIR’s <a href="https://aoir.social">Mastodon server</a> has benefited from ITFAS’s services.</p>

<p>I know AoIR.social has benefited because I’m one of AoIR.social’s admins, and thus I do a lot of content moderation on that server. While we did not really use IFTAS’s blocklists specifically, we certainly have <a href="/2023/09/20/blocklists.html">benefited from the use of blocklists</a> in general. We did directly benefit from IFTAS Connect – I have an account there and read threads about moderation challenges, learning from the experiences of others.</p>

<p>While IFTAS was providing a valuable service to the fediverse, <a href="https://about.iftas.org/2025/02/06/funding-challenges-and-the-future-of-our-work/">they recently announced</a> that they were struggling to get funding:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Despite our best efforts to secure sustainable funding, IFTAS is now facing a critical financial shortfall. Without immediate support, we will be forced to severely curtail our activities in the next 60 days. With our current commitments we will be unable to pay our bills in April.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That was one month ago, and indeed IFTAS just announced <a href="https://about.iftas.org/2025/03/03/iftas-service-shutdowns/">they are shutting down several services</a>.</p>

<p>This is going to be a big loss. As Laurens Hof at <a href="https://fediversereport.com/fediverse-report-106/"><em>The Fediverse Report</em> notes</a>, noncentralized social media needs some forums where folks can gather to discuss the the challenges they face:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>IFTAS, as a grassroots fediverse organisation, is one of the best-placed organisations to have build trust and provide a nexus around which such infrastructure could be build. IFTAS got pretty far with their rollout of FediCheck, which was building such a place for collaboration between server admins. Now that IFTAS will not be the center around which shared moderation infrastructure can be build [sic], will there be another organisation in the future to do so? Especially when IFTAS found out that getting funding for such a project is so difficult?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But is getting funding so difficult? I wonder.</p>

<p>That brings me to the provocation I dropped in the first paragraph: there may be a standards war brewing. To see that, let’s look at another organization that is spinning up as IFTAS is winding down.</p>

<h2 id="free-our-feeds">Free our Feeds</h2>
<p>In January 13 of this year, a consortium of actors, bloggers, academics and tech luminaries <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250113141611/http://freeourfeeds.com/">launched “Free Our Feeds”</a>, a new foundation based on the idea that “we can no longer let billionaires control our digital public square.” The announcement included a call for donations. As of March 5, Free our Feeds’s GoFundMe <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/help-us-free-social-media-from-billionaires">has raised $90K USD</a> – not quite the four million they wanted, but certainly not nothing.</p>

<p>What would Free Our Feeds do? Well, for one thing, “re-grant [money] to the community of innovators,” including folks doing content moderation. Another thing is to help develop an open protocol (namely ATProto, which is currently being developed by the Bluesky corporation).</p>

<p>Right as this group made this announcement, a lot of folks asked a basic question: <em>doesn’t this sort of thing already exist?</em> They were referring, of course, to ActivityPub, which has existed since 2018 and is an open standard (governed by the W3C) with a thriving ecosystem of applications.</p>

<p>But there’s another thing that existed at the time of the Free Our Feeds launch, an organization that was already innovating content moderation for the non-billionaire-controlled social web.</p>

<p>IFTAS.</p>

<p>Free Our Feeds does not mention the existence of IFTAS. (Initially, they didn’t even mention ActivityPub, adding a note about that protocol in their FAQ later).</p>

<p>So, while Free Our Feeds seeks money for their  unclear goals (as <a href="https://tante.cc/2025/01/13/but-does-it-free-our-feeds/">critics</a> <a href="https://rubenerd.com/free-our-feeds/">have argued</a>), another organization that has actually achieved tangible things – IFTAS – is folding for lack of funding.</p>

<h2 id="is-this-a-standards-war">Is This a Standards War?</h2>
<p>Free Our Feeds eventually included a note about ActivityPub in their FAQ:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>ActivityPub is a W3C standard that enables interoperability between platforms like Mastodon, Flipboard, Ghost, Threads, and others. [ATProto] and ActivityPub should not be either/or options.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That answer also includes a link to <a href="https://socialwebfoundation.org/2025/01/13/free-our-feeds-and-algorithmic-pluralism/">a blog post</a> by Mallory Knodel of the Social Web Foundation. That post explains,</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>[The Free Our Feeds] campaign is an opportunity to develop the capacity needed for the open social web protocols– ActivityPub along with Bluesky’s AT Protocol– to better interoperate, leveraging the entire open social ecosystem to create a working demonstration of algorithmic pluralism at scale.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The message is clear: It’s not either/or. It’s pluralism.</p>

<p>But is it?</p>

<p>The fact of the matter is that <strong>there are now two standards</strong> – ATProto and ActivityPub – making the <strong>same fundamental claims to being <em>the</em> open standard</strong> that allows for decentralized social media.</p>

<p>Another fact is that ATProto and ActivityPub are <strong>architecturally very, very different.</strong> The former is what <a href="https://dustycloud.org/blog/how-decentralized-is-bluesky/">Christine Lemmer-Webber calls</a> a “shared heap” structure, where an installation requires access to all the posts in the network, while the latter is server software that sends and fetches messages as the necessity arises. ATProto allows for “Personal Data Servers” – but these would rely on an infrastructure of indexes that likely will be prohibitively expensive. An ActivityPub server can run on a cheap server and still be a fully-fledged member of the fediverse.</p>

<p>Another fact is that <strong>both are overseen by very different bodies</strong> and <strong>both have come from very different processes.</strong> ActivityPub was developed at the W3C <a href="/2023/10/15/APnonStandard.html">largely independent of corporate interests</a>. The W3C remains the steward of ActivityPub. ATProto was born at Twitter and spun out into a separate, venture-capital funded corporation. While the Bluesky corporation <a href="https://docs.bsky.app/blog/protocol-roadmap">promised in 2023</a> ATProto development will be shifted to the IETF, this still has not happened, and ATProto development is closely tied to a corporation that no doubt faces pressure to be profitable.</p>

<p>While there have been projects seeking to connect the two protocols – such as Bridgy – another fact is that this <strong>bridging is incredibly clumsy.</strong> To make a Mastodon account visible on Bluesky, one has to follow “@bsky.brid.gy@bsky.brid.gy”, and then a <em>separate</em> account is what is followed by Bluesky users. It works the same in reverse. Even when it works, posts are quite differently handled on either side. And none of this really addresses the fundamental architectural differences between ATProto and ActivityPub. Bridgy is a technical achievement, for sure, but I do not think it can be called “interoperability.”</p>

<p>Thus, while Free Our Feeds has declared their interest in fostering interoperability and building resources that could benefit the decentralized social web, the facts are that <strong>there are major organizational, cultural, and technical distinctions between these protocols</strong> and <strong>there are only so many resources to go around.</strong></p>

<p>In other words, it’s possible we are watching a “standards war” happening in real time. It’s not as apparent because the stakes are not the same as, for example, different railroad gauges or different ways to deliver electricity.</p>

<p>But there are stakes. This is social media, where we have been taught that more is always better. Bluesky is attracting more people than the fediverse. This matters. Which standard would be recognized as the decentralized social media standard? Who will get the resources? Who will get developer energy, funding, academic research, and moderation support? Who will attract media coverage?</p>

<h2 id="iftas-as-casualty-in-a-standards-war">IFTAS as Casualty in a Standards War</h2>
<p>The case of IFTAS folding while Free Our Feeds emerges indicates that maybe AT Proto will win this potential standards war. If Free Our Feeds does raise the money for its (amorphous) goals, while IFTAS fails to get support for its actual services, that is pretty telling.</p>

<p>If Free Our Feeds merely concentrates on what they believe is best for Bluesky – as seems to be the case, given their interest in sorting algorithms, AI, and <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/who-owns-the-future-of-social-media-a-giant-leap-to-decentralize-core-components-of-blueskys-at-protocol-ecosystem-302387397.html">blockchains</a> – that is the most telling aspect of all.</p>

<p>Of course, it’s possible IFTAS has failed to raise funds for good reasons. Non-profits can and do fail. (Free our Feeds also might!)</p>

<p>But the failure of the broader tech, academic, and (frankly) celebrity sector to recognize and support an actually-existing trust and safety organization – one tied closely to ActivityPub – in favor of a relatively amorphous entity that is very tied to AT Proto is a troubling sign of how a potential standards war might turn out.</p>

<p>* Correction: I originally had this as the independent Fediverse Trust and Safety organization. The F stands for Federated, not fediverse.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ActivityPub" /><category term="ATProto" /><category term="IFTAS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While I was not surprised by the announcement, it was still sad to read the news that IFTAS is shutting down several of its services for lack of funding. It is hard for me not to see this as another aspect of a potential “standards war” between ActivityPub and ATProto.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The ASM Bibliography is Going Home</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/22/bib-is-moving.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ASM Bibliography is Going Home" /><published>2025-02-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/22/bib-is-moving</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/22/bib-is-moving.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a minor update: the ASM Bibliography is returning to its original home <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/bib.html">on the social media alternatives project</a> page.</p>

<p>It’s the same bibliography – I just don’t want to maintain two instances of it!</p>

<p>It’s kind of a homecoming for the bibliography. It is based on a <a href="https://www.zotero.org/groups/542752/social_media_alternatives_project_bibliography">Zotero Group</a> that I set up for the Social Media Alternatives Project back in the mid-2010s. (Contact me if you’re an academic and want to join that group.)</p>

<p>The bib has gone through a lot of changes lately – the <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/members.html">Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers</a> have been adding quite a bit to it. It’s really exciting to see the growth of the field!</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a minor update: the ASM Bibliography is returning to its original home on the social media alternatives project page.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You Can Post Your Way Out of Fascism if You Own the Means of Posting</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/15/organizing-fascism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You Can Post Your Way Out of Fascism if You Own the Means of Posting" /><published>2025-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/15/organizing-fascism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/15/organizing-fascism.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been mulling over Janus Rose’s recent <em>404 Media</em> article, <a href="https://www.404media.co/you-cant-post-your-way-out-of-fascism/">“You Can’t Post Your Way Out of Fascism.”</a>. In many ways, she’s not wrong. But once again people are ignoring an entirely other way of doing social media that can, in fact, fight fascism.</p>

<p>Rose’s article made the rounds in the social media feeds I follow. And for good reason. Many folks are deeply troubled – and frightened – of what’s happening in the USA. People who pay attention know that the difference between a democratic state and an authoritarian one is <em>indifference</em>, which is to say that if institutions are indifferent about stopping someone like Trump from abusing his power, he is de facto an authoritarian leader. And there’s <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/world/trump-courts-guardrails-analysis-1.7457725">a lot of indifference in the US government right now</a>.</p>

<p>So people want to find a way to stop Trumpism, and they’re eager for guidance – hence the sharing of Rose’s article.</p>

<p>What is to be done? Well, Rose argues that there is no antidote to Trumpian poison to be found in merely taking to social media and posting about his (or Elon Musk’s, or Pete Hesgeth’s, or any other Trumpist’s) bizarre or cruel statements. “If there’s one thing I’d hoped people had learned going into the next four years of Donald Trump as president,” she writes, “it’s that spending lots of time online posting about what people in power are saying and doing is not going to accomplish anything. If anything, it’s exactly what they want.”</p>

<p>Rose points to the work of political theorists and sociologists, arguing that being outraged and overwhelmed is the point. “Thinkers like Jean-Paul Sartre and Hannah Arendt warned us that the point of this deluge is not to persuade, but to overwhelm and paralyze our capacity to act.” She draws on the work of <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/log-off-why-posting-and-politics-almost-never-mix-katherine-cross/78a509d4d3703d91?ean=9781736716861&amp;next=t&amp;next=t">Katherine Cross</a> to argue that corporate social media is all too happy to provide an outlet for the rage. Cross “documents how tech platforms encourage us, through their design affordances, to post and seethe and doomscroll into the void, always reacting and never acting.”</p>

<p>Cross’s language is an apt description of corporate social media – X and Meta properties are now full-on algorithmic outrage engines, designed to keep us looking, scrolling, and posting. (And never forget why: they sell our attention to marketers. That’s their whole purpose.)</p>

<p>Instead, as Rose argues, people need to get organized – to do actual, on-the-ground activism, rather than merely posting about the outage du jour.</p>

<h2 id="slactivism-20">Slactivism 2.0?</h2>
<p>One might be tempted to dismiss Rose’s argument because it’s not new. It’s basically a repetition of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slacktivism">“slacktivism”</a> complaint popularized by Evgeny Morozov in the early 2010s. (Morozov’s own argument repeated arguments made in the 1990s, but I will stick with 2010s on).</p>

<p>Against the backdrop of breathless proclamations about “Facebook revolutions” and “Twitter democracy,” Morozov argued that what was really happening was that corporate social media activism allowed people to confuse clicking “like” on a political post with actually doing something about it. Rose herself repeats this argument (by way of citing Cross): “the greatest [sin] is convincing ourselves that posting is a form of political activism, when it is at best a coping mechanism—an individualist solution to problems that can only be solved by collective action.”</p>

<p>The slacktivism critique probably reached its high water mark with the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/09/world/africa/online-joseph-kony-and-a-ugandan-conflict-soar-to-topic-no-1.html"><em>Kony 2012</em> phenomenon</a>, a short Youtube video which promised viewers that they could bring an end to  Joseph Kony’s use of children as soldiers with “just a click.” Clicking, it was argued, is a far cry from on-the-ground, collective organizing to combat the use of children in warfighting in Uganda.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://us1-browse.startpage.com/av/anon-image?piurl=https%3A%2F%2Fi.pinimg.com%2F236x%2F18%2F4f%2F1e%2F184f1ef000b76e01e7364897acc7ab9a.jpg&amp;sp=1739636813Tad45153b3cc7ed4d39ba00847d5f0d1ff5fbabf86b300c0542af991a999fd134">memes mocking this notion</a> soon followed. The memes encapsulate the major critique of slacktivism: raising “awareness” of social ills does nothing to actually address them.</p>

<p>“Slacktivism” was thus contrasted with “real activism” – marches, protests, community organizing, raising and distributing resources, and the like.</p>

<p>So, we have a dichotomy here: either you’re posting and liking on social media, or you’re on the streets, organizing and fighting back. It’s a dichotomy that we’ve been hearing about since at least the 2010s.</p>

<p>Indeed, Rose’s argument also goes in this direction, updating it for 2025. She points to anti-Immigration and Customs Enforcement actions and efforts to provide shelter for the unhoused. She argues that these arose from real organizing, not just posting. “Some of these efforts were coordinated online over Discord and secure messaging apps, but all of them arose from existing networks of neighbors and community organizers, some of whom have been organizing for decades.” Such real organizing is what we need: “when it comes to addressing the problems we face, no amount of posting or passive info consumption is going to substitute the hard, unsexy work of organizing.”</p>

<h2 id="beyond-the-dichotomy">Beyond the Dichotomy</h2>

<p>There are two ways out of the dichotomy between doomscrolling/posting and getting organized. One way is to argue that it is a false dichtomy – that posting and organizing aren’t mutually exclusive. Critics of the “slacktivism” complaint <a href="https://beyond.ubc.ca/online-activism-isnt-just-slacktivism/">have done that work</a>, arguing that online activism enables marginalized people to start getting involved, and that arguments that online activism is worthless discourage people from doing anything at all.</p>

<p>I won’t repeat these arguments, though I certainly talk about them when I teach classes about social movements. Instead, here I will point to another way out, one that I’ve been studying since before the “slacktivism” complaint gained prominence in the early 2010s.</p>

<p>It won’t surprise you to learn that I argue for alternative social media where its users – or, as I prefer, <em>members</em> – are in control. These systems have been around since the early 2010s – indeed, they arose right around the time of Morozov’s slacktivism complaint. The latest iteration is ActivityPub-enabled federated social media.</p>

<p>Can folks doomscroll on the fediverse? Yes. Can folks post on the fediverse? Yes. Might they post about the latest outrage of Trump? Yes, definitely.</p>

<p>Does that mean they are failing to fight incipient fascism? No.</p>

<p>In fact, I argue that the act of running, moderating, and participating in federated social media is precisely the sort of organizing that Rose calls for. It’s just taking place in a media environment, rather than, say, in an NGO’s offices in a city.</p>

<p>Communities who make their own codes of conduct collectively establish how they want to relate to one another. They make decisions about content moderation. They make decisions about federating and defederating with other instances. They are governing themselves online.</p>

<p>This is another example of the “hard, unsexy work of organizing.” Moreover, to quote Rose further: “We need to collectively decide what kind of world we actually do want, and what we’re willing to do to achieve it.” Exactly. And part of that world is the communication infrastructure. Who should own it? Who should govern it? To what purpose should it be put – marketing messages and consumerism, or collective sensemaking?</p>

<p>With Silicon Valley executives and media moguls openly allying themselves with Donald Trump – and with Musk, owner of a major communication platform, actively involved in the Trump administration – we need media that operates outside of corporate control. We need non-capitalist, non-centralized media.</p>

<p>Indeed, we already have it! It’s been around for quite some time! And if you want unsexy hard work, set up your own server, recruit people to it, and moderate it.</p>

<h2 id="the-art-of-forgetting">The Art of Forgetting</h2>
<p>It’s odd that I have to write this, because once again I feel like an actual, existing alternative to corporate social media exists.</p>

<p>But what’s odder to me still is that Rose ropes Bluesky into the same orbit as Twitter/X or Facebook:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Many Twitter refugees made a good choice in migrating from Musk’s X to Bluesky, carving out a new online space that is inhospitable to bigoted debate bros and time-wasting trolls. But in their enemies’ absence, many of these Left-leaning posters have just reverted to dunking on each other, preferring the catharsis of sectarian conflict over the hard work of organizing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I thought Bluesky was supposed to be the alternative that allowed people more control? That puts algorithms in the hands of end users? That gives people choices? Instead, Rose is equating Bluesky with other corporate social media – it, like Meta or X, does not encourage “the hard work of organizing.”</p>

<p>I increasingly tend to agree with that equation. Bluesky PBC has taken venture capital funding. It will face pressure to monetize. And along with that, it seems less and less invested in developing actual ways to decentralize.</p>

<p>However, you might disagree. Let’s set that aside. For now, I will point out that the critique of social media as a space for mere posting, doomscrolling, and algorithmic manipulation simply does not apply to the fediverse. The fediverse <em>demands</em> the hard work of organizing.</p>

<p>But for Rose to write this article, the only way the argument works is to forget the existence of the fediverse.</p>

<p>In my time studying non-corporate social media, I’ve seen this forgetting again and again. Fortunately, I’ve also seen the activists who make, run, moderate and participate in these non-corporate alternatives keep going, in spite of being forgotten or ignored.</p>

<p>That gives me hope that we can post our way out of fascism… on <em>our</em> social media.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Alternative Social Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been mulling over Janus Rose’s recent 404 Media article, “You Can’t Post Your Way Out of Fascism.”. In many ways, she’s not wrong. But once again people are ignoring an entirely other way of doing social media that can, in fact, fight fascism.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing: the Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/01/asmNet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing: the Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers" /><published>2025-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/01/asmNet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/02/01/asmNet.html"><![CDATA[<p>For years, researching alternative social media has been a bit lonely. But not anymore!</p>

<p>Over the past few months, I’ve been recruiting people to join an email list for academics who study alternative social media, broadly conceived. Every week or so, I’d send an update about the state of ASM, and folks would share articles they’ve written.</p>

<p>It’s gone quite well, and now we’re going public with it!</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-network-of-alternative-social-media-researchers">The Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/">Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers</a> is a home page, blog, archive, and bibliography all centered on ASM research. We have a growing <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/members.html">members</a> page with short bios. As for the archive, I’ve kept my older project, the <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/archive/">S-MAP</a>, where grad students and I collected screenshots of many past and current alternative social media.</p>

<p>These are early days for the project – as you can see, I still have a bit of fine-tuning to do on the website. But I believe this project will lead to collaborations, panels, and even entire conferences exploring the world of ASM.</p>

<p>If you’re an academic doing research in this space, please check of the <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/">ASM network page</a> for more information on joining us.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="alternative social media" /><category term="asm update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For years, researching alternative social media has been a bit lonely. But not anymore!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Alternative Social Media in a Corporate Social Media World</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/01/18/makingAlts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Alternative Social Media in a Corporate Social Media World" /><published>2025-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/01/18/makingAlts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/01/18/makingAlts.html"><![CDATA[<p>In this week’s <a href="/tags/asm update.html">Alternative Social Media Update</a>, I want to share two things that happened this week and have a fundamental connection: they both indicate the challenges alternative social media developers face when they make ASM in a corporate social media world.</p>

<!-- more -->
<h2 id="item-one-algorithmic-choice">Item One: Algorithmic Choice</h2>

<p>Writing on the W3C <a href="https://www.w3.org/community/socialcg/">Social Web Incubator Community Group</a> email list, <a href="https://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-swicg/2025Jan/0016.html">Bob Wyman asks</a>, “How would algorithmic choice’ laws/regulations impact ActivityPub?” Wyman points to the Missouri Attorney General Bailey’s <a href="https://ago.mo.gov/attorney-general-bailey-promulgates-regulation-securing-algorithmic-freedom-for-social-media-users/">new regulation about “algorithmic freedom” for users of social media</a>. In that press release, the AG says,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Big Tech oligarchs have manipulated consumers’ social media feeds for their own purposes and exercised monopoly control over content moderation. To that end, I am invoking my authority under consumer protection law to ensure Missourians get to control the content they consume on social media.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While he notes this regulation will face implementation and legal challenges, Wyman nonetheless suggests that ActivityPub developers think seriously about new regulations that may affect them:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I think we should anticipate that the coming
to power of Trump and MAGA Republicans is likely to spawn many such
proposals in the coming years. Given this, I think it would be useful to at
least consider what impact such regulations would have on Social Media
systems that rely on ActivityPub and ActivityStreams.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Wyman’s message resonates with me, because I’ve already written about how regulations <a href="/2024/04/10/Online-Harms-Act.html">might affect the fediverse</a>.</p>

<p>In a world where the vast majority of people are only familiar with corporate social media, any new regulations are going to likely be written in ways that can have unintended consequences for alternative social media. The idea of “algorithmic choice” is likely applicable to corporate services such as Instagram or TikTok. It’s less clear how this idea would apply as a regulation of federated social media, which tends to eschew content sorting algorithms in favor of reverse-chronological ordering and boosting. <em>Requiring</em> small, federated instances to implement alternative ways to sort streams would place a major burden on them.</p>

<p>Moreover, if alternative social media continues to grow, corporate social media may lobby to have laws written in such a way that they <em>purposely</em> undermine small alternatives. After all, they have loads of money and power and lobbyists – as we’re seeing now with Meta’s attempts to ingratiate itself with Trump, as well as with Musk’s outright buying of Trump.</p>

<p>Finally, this Missouri AG regulation is clearly coming out of the right-wing “media is full of liberals” view. Consider this closing passage from the press release:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This is the first prong of a comprehensive offensive to protect free speech in 2025,” said Attorney General Bailey. “Now that we have a presidential administration coming into office that will not silence disfavored speech, we’re turning our focus to corporate censorship. Missouri will continue to lead the way in defense of our most fundamental freedoms.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If that AG thinks Meta is left-leaning (and thus “silencing disfavored speech”), keep him away from much of the fediverse! It certainly “silences” the “freedom” of trolls and bigots. This raises a third scenario: regulations that are written specifically by lawmakers to crush independent social media if their values don’t align with right-wing values (perhaps under the guise of protecting children or fighting terrorism).</p>

<h2 id="item-two-terms-of-servitude">Item Two: Terms of Servitude?</h2>
<p>Mark Zuckerberg is tripping over himself to bow down to Trump. The changes at Meta includes the end of fact-checking and <a href="https://www.404media.co/its-total-chaos-internally-at-meta-right-now-employees-protest-zuckerbergs-anti-lgbtq-changes/">explicitly allowing people to harass queer folks</a>.</p>

<p>As a result, once again, folks are looking around for alternatives to corporate social media and there it sits: <a href="https://loops.video/">Pixelfed</a> and <a href="https://loops.video/">Loops.Video</a>. Both are made by <a href="https://dansup.com/">Dan Supernault</a>. Pixelfed is an image-centric, ActivityPub-enabled service. That means that it is geared toward photographers who can share their pictures, but it also means that people on other fediverse systems, like Mastodon, can follow those photographers, see the pictures, and comment on them.</p>

<p>Loops is newer and under development – and it’s the one that prompted a controversy. Loops is meant to be a TikTok-like short video system that will also enable ActivityPub. While it’s in beta, it has been growing at a pretty rapid clip.</p>

<p>Such growth invites scrutiny. A blog post by Phil has taken a <a href="https://bajsicki.com/blog/loops-video-terms/">critical look at Loops.Video’s terms of service</a> and the analysis is troubling. Here’s a key bit of what Phil found: Loops.Video’s TOS includes the paragraph,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>By posting your Contributions to any part of the Services or making Contributions accessible to the Services by linking your account from the Services to any of your social networking accounts, you automatically grant, and you represent and warrant that you have the right to grant, to us an unrestricted, unlimited, irrevocable, perpetual, non-exclusive, transferable, royalty-free, fully-paid, worldwide right, and license to host, use, copy, reproduce, disclose, sell, resell, publish, broadcast, retitle, archive, store, cache, publicly perform, publicly display, reformat, translate, transmit, excerpt (in whole or in part), and distribute such Contributions (including, without limitation, your image and voice) for any purpose, commercial, advertising, or otherwise, and to prepare derivative works of, or incorporate into other works, such Contributions, and grant and authorize sublicenses of the foregoing. The use and distribution may occur in any media formats and through any media channels.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(Note that Phil’s post is absolutely accurate as of this writing – I checked <a href="https://loops.video/legal/terms-of-service">Loops’s TOS myself and saw this language</a>.)</p>

<p>If you’re like me and you regularly read terms of service agreements, I pity you, but also you and I have seen this language many, many times before: this is the language of surveillance capitalism. I <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/882779130">wrote about this exact issue back in 2014</a>. Like so many corporations before it, Loops.Video is claiming the right to use your content basically forever and for whatever purposes it sees fit – including selling your data to advertisers or training generative AI.</p>

<p>Is this a secret plot by Dan Supernault to bring surveillance capitalism to the predominantly non-capitalist fediverse? Maybe not. To his credit, when this was brought to Supernault’s attention, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@dansup/113848396412970536">he said he’d fix it right away</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There have been several concerns raised about [these terms of service], and I want you to know that we will be replacing them with a better, more clearer set of rules and policies.<sup><a href="#note1">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>

<p>It turns out he used <a href="https://termly.io/">Termly</a>, an online resource to write terms of service agreements. “Please don’t assume the worst,” Supernault wrote. “I’m trying my best but don’t have a team to help me with stuff like this.” Basically, Supernault is saying that, in the absence of a legal team, in the heat of trying to spin up a new service, he went with a boilerplate solution to legal agreements.</p>

<p>I anticipate Supernault will fix this – after all, take a look at <a href="https://pixelfed.social/site/terms">Pixelfed.social’s terms</a>. They are nothing like the Loops terms.</p>

<h2 id="making-asm-in-a-csm-world">Making ASM in a CSM World</h2>
<p>The clash between the values of alternative social media and corporate social media go beyond things like avoiding surveillance capitalism or providing community-based governance and moderation. Increasingly, they will also involve how to manage state-based regulations and legal regimes.</p>

<p>In the case of state regulation, like that of the Missouri AG in the USA, alternative social media developers will have to think about how new regulations will affect them – and they may need to preemptively address them. And I’m not saying they should address them in code, but by advocating for ASM in front of regulators.</p>

<p>In the case of terms of service, it would be good if organizations who support ASM would offer boilerplate terms that are not based on corporate logics and instead reflect fediverse values.</p>

<p>In both cases, making alternative social media in a corporate social media world means more work from communities: not just coding, not just self-governance, but also engaging with regulators and working with lawyers across jurisdictions. This work is already happening, of course, but I imagine more will need to be done.</p>

<h2 id="notes">Notes</h2>
<p id="note1">1) Note that in almost all cases, I reach out to people on the fediverse to get permission to quote them outside of the fedi. In some cases, I do not think the consent is necessary. An example case is when a project leader makes a public statement about that project. I think this post falls under that exception.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="Loops" /><category term="ActivityPub" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this week’s Alternative Social Media Update, I want to share two things that happened this week and have a fundamental connection: they both indicate the challenges alternative social media developers face when they make ASM in a corporate social media world.]]></summary></entry></feed>