<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-16T11:31:00-06:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Test post for Mastodon Comments</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/12/16/CommentsTest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Test post for Mastodon Comments" /><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/12/16/CommentsTest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/12/16/CommentsTest.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been struggling with having comments on this Jekyll-based static site for a while. For a bit, I used Staticman, but that died for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, it hit me: so many sites use Facebook comments. Why can’t I use Mastodon, the FOSS alternative social media system, to do something similar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.xmgz.eu/jekyll-mastodon-comment/&quot;&gt;this guide&lt;/a&gt; provided all the code I could need to do exactly that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is a test run. Feel free to comment on it using your Mastodon account. (I think other federated accounts might work, but not sure – if so, let me know in the comments!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a Mastodon account, don’t worry! You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://joinmastodon.org&quot;&gt;sign up for an instance&lt;/a&gt; and join the federated fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-1&quot;&gt;UPDATE #1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tested it a bit and have found a few things that give me pause:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It does not respect the distinction between Unlisted and Public privacy settings. Both will show up here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; respect DM – that is, DMs do not show up as comments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It does not respect Content Warnings. CWs don’t show up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that in mind, I think I may keep it (pending further testing) and include a warning in the “Comments” section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-2&quot;&gt;UPDATE #2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to another Mastodoner, I found that if anyone who uses Mastodon to comment on a blog post deletes said comment, then it will also no longer appear on the blog. I think that’s a cool feature, but I’m thinking that I have be &lt;em&gt;extremely clear&lt;/em&gt; about what happens when people comment on my blog. It’s going to be public – very public – not just in the federation, but also on my website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’m not 100% certain this is wise. I’d love to get more opinions from Mastodon users. Feel free to leave them in the comments – or, to be certain that your opinion is expressed privately, DM me (@robertwgehl@scholar.social).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">I’ve been struggling with having comments on this Jekyll-based static site for a while. For a bit, I used Staticman, but that died for some reason. Then, it hit me: so many sites use Facebook comments. Why can’t I use Mastodon, the FOSS alternative social media system, to do something similar? Fortunately, this guide provided all the code I could need to do exactly that! So this is a test run. Feel free to comment on it using your Mastodon account. (I think other federated accounts might work, but not sure – if so, let me know in the comments!) If you don’t have a Mastodon account, don’t worry! You can sign up for an instance and join the federated fun. UPDATE #1 I’ve tested it a bit and have found a few things that give me pause: It does not respect the distinction between Unlisted and Public privacy settings. Both will show up here. It does respect DM – that is, DMs do not show up as comments. It does not respect Content Warnings. CWs don’t show up. With all that in mind, I think I may keep it (pending further testing) and include a warning in the “Comments” section. UPDATE #2 Thanks to another Mastodoner, I found that if anyone who uses Mastodon to comment on a blog post deletes said comment, then it will also no longer appear on the blog. I think that’s a cool feature, but I’m thinking that I have be extremely clear about what happens when people comment on my blog. It’s going to be public – very public – not just in the federation, but also on my website. However, I’m not 100% certain this is wise. I’d love to get more opinions from Mastodon users. Feel free to leave them in the comments – or, to be certain that your opinion is expressed privately, DM me (@robertwgehl@scholar.social).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tuxies 2021</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/12/11/Tuxies2021.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tuxies 2021" /><published>2021-12-11T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-12-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/12/11/Tuxies2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/12/11/Tuxies2021.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://linuxunplugged.com/&quot;&gt;Linux Unplugged&lt;/a&gt; is at it again: it’s Tuxies time! I voted, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://tuxies.party&quot;&gt;you can, too&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike last year, this year they’re using a self-hosted Nextcloud form – brilliant! Like &lt;a href=&quot;2020/12/10/The-Tuxies-Academic-Style.html&quot;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve voted based on my experience as a FOSS Academic. My picks may not win – but they might just help you live the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tuxintux.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tux the Penguin Wearing a Tuxedo&quot; title=&quot;Tux the Penguin Wearing a Tuxedo&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-newcomerbecame-well-known&quot;&gt;Best Newcomer/Became Well Known&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to keep pounding a drum few of us will hear, but &lt;strong&gt;Zotero&lt;/strong&gt; needs to be known about. Zotero, which is a bibliographic management system, released a beta of a new PDF reader and annotator which has greatly improved how I do academic research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;text-editor&quot;&gt;Text Editor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nano.&lt;/strong&gt; It just gets things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;distro-of-the-year&quot;&gt;Distro of the Year&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manjaro.&lt;/strong&gt; I predict Fedora’s going to win because it was constantly discussed on Linux Unplugged and I suspect the listenership will go with it. But I switched my main work laptop from Debian-based distros to Manjaro this year and have been so impressed. I didn’t realize what a relief it is not to have to worry about doing a massive upgrade – just keep rolling along instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;server&quot;&gt;Server&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Ubuntu LTS servers for stability, so I probably have no business making this call. But I have been impressed by the organizational structure of &lt;strong&gt;AlmaLinux.&lt;/strong&gt; Every time I hear one of their representatives speak on podcasts, I can just hear their unwavering commitment to creating a community-owned enterprise Linux server distro. In fact, I think I need to study their structure a bit further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;desktop-environment&quot;&gt;Desktop Environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one won’t win, but I love &lt;strong&gt;MATE&lt;/strong&gt; and will defend it with crysknives. I’ve said it before, but when it comes to desktops, I’m a Linux Luddite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;largest-impact&quot;&gt;Largest impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect Pipewire will win, but I think &lt;strong&gt;Wireguard&lt;/strong&gt; has been brilliant. I’ve used it extensively to create a virtual private network of devices, including Android phones, all using an installation of Pi-Hole to block unwanted traffic. In fact, right now I’m serving Jekyll from one machine over the local network to another via my Wireguard VPN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big, big benefit I’ve seen is countering some bad practices from my ISP: if I listen to internet radio streams on my regular connection, they are dropped after a few minutes. Run them through Wireguard and the streams will flow for days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;self-hosted-service&quot;&gt;Self-hosted service&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pi-hole.&lt;/strong&gt; Ad-blocking, local DNS, child-proofing my kid’s computer, blocking Facebook from my network… it’s all possible with Pi-Hole. Couple this with Wireguard and I can block ads on any connection, anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Tuxies" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">Linux Unplugged is at it again: it’s Tuxies time! I voted, and you can, too. Unlike last year, this year they’re using a self-hosted Nextcloud form – brilliant! Like last year, I’ve voted based on my experience as a FOSS Academic. My picks may not win – but they might just help you live the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In Praise of Mastodon, Again</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/10/30/PraiseMastodonAgain.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Praise of Mastodon, Again" /><published>2021-10-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-10-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/10/30/PraiseMastodonAgain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/10/30/PraiseMastodonAgain.html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, in the wake of the attempted coup that happened right here, live, on TV, in these United States, I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/08/PraiseMastodon.html&quot;&gt;a post praising how Mastodon handled the alt-right and Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt;. As I saw it, Mastodon’s swift action against the alt-right (specifically, their quick repudiation of Gab) was a very different approach than the corporate platform approach of Facebook and Twitter. Yes, the latter removed Trump. But they did so at a pretty convenient moment: after the election was over and the ad dollars were spent. Moreover, while banning Trump was a long-overdue move, it was clearly inadequate. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2021/10/22/jan-6-capitol-riot-facebook/&quot;&gt;As investigative journalism is revealing&lt;/a&gt;, Facebook in particular did little to quell the planning of the January 6 insurrection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come again to praise Mastodon. This time, for quickly addressing the problem of Trump’s new platform, Truth, which appears to be a fork (or simply CTRL+F and replace) of Mastodon’s code. That in itself is not the issue – after all, Mastodon is FOSS, and people can therefore take it and use it. The issue is that Trump is claiming to &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.joinmastodon.org/2021/10/trumps-new-social-media-platform-found-using-mastodon-code/&quot;&gt;Mastodon’s response&lt;/a&gt; – as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfconservancy.org/blog/2021/oct/21/trump-group-agplv3/&quot;&gt;that of the Software Freedom Conservancy&lt;/a&gt; – is to give Trump 30 days to quit claiming ownership of the code or be in violation of the license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my mind, this is like a powerful force hitting a very stupid object. It seems obvious that Trump will have to relinquish his claims that the code is proprietary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then again, Trump is notorious for doing things and then daring people to lawyer up, dragging his feet by using the courts. It’s clearly what he’s hoping to do with the January 6 investigation, and I wouldn’t be surprised if he does the same with Mastodon and the SFC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those are Trump’s flaws. Again, I come to praise Mastodon, once again, for showing nerve and a steel spine where corporations with a great deal more revenue, lobbying power, and users didn’t do in the first place: call Trump out on his bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="Trump" /><summary type="html">Earlier this year, in the wake of the attempted coup that happened right here, live, on TV, in these United States, I wrote a post praising how Mastodon handled the alt-right and Donald Trump. As I saw it, Mastodon’s swift action against the alt-right (specifically, their quick repudiation of Gab) was a very different approach than the corporate platform approach of Facebook and Twitter. Yes, the latter removed Trump. But they did so at a pretty convenient moment: after the election was over and the ad dollars were spent. Moreover, while banning Trump was a long-overdue move, it was clearly inadequate. As investigative journalism is revealing, Facebook in particular did little to quell the planning of the January 6 insurrection. I come again to praise Mastodon. This time, for quickly addressing the problem of Trump’s new platform, Truth, which appears to be a fork (or simply CTRL+F and replace) of Mastodon’s code. That in itself is not the issue – after all, Mastodon is FOSS, and people can therefore take it and use it. The issue is that Trump is claiming to own the code. Derp. Mastodon’s response – as well as that of the Software Freedom Conservancy – is to give Trump 30 days to quit claiming ownership of the code or be in violation of the license. To my mind, this is like a powerful force hitting a very stupid object. It seems obvious that Trump will have to relinquish his claims that the code is proprietary. Then again, Trump is notorious for doing things and then daring people to lawyer up, dragging his feet by using the courts. It’s clearly what he’s hoping to do with the January 6 investigation, and I wouldn’t be surprised if he does the same with Mastodon and the SFC. But those are Trump’s flaws. Again, I come to praise Mastodon, once again, for showing nerve and a steel spine where corporations with a great deal more revenue, lobbying power, and users didn’t do in the first place: call Trump out on his bullshit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nextcloud Appointments!</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/09/25/Appointments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nextcloud Appointments!" /><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/09/25/Appointments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/09/25/Appointments.html">&lt;p&gt;I used an exclamation point intentionally, because the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/appointments&quot;&gt;Appointments app for Nextcloud&lt;/a&gt; is just that awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a professor, I keep office hours and encourage students to meet with me. And, I also need to advise graduate students at various institutions around the world. And this is not to mention meeting with other professors I’m collaborating with – again, from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, setting up meetings went a bit like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Them: Hey, can we meet? 
Me: Sure! When do you want to meet?
Them: I’m free Mondays and Fridays. 
Me: How about noon on Monday?
Them: Actually, I have an appointment them. What day of the week works for you?
Me: Wednesdays and Fridays.
Them: Great! What about 1 on Wednesday?
Me: Sure! 
Them: What timezone are you in?
Me: Central.
Them: Oh! Then 1 pm for you is 9 pm for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Etc, etc. Each of these being an email, of course, and usually with a delay of several hours between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they used to say in the commercials, “there’s got to be a better way!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nextcloud Appointments is that better way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appointments&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creates a public form where would-be attendees can pick an open spot.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Those spots are based on pre-selected weekly times (e.g., my office hours).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But! Appointments watches my other calendars for conflicts and blocks off those times from the public form.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And! Appointments also includes the option to embargo appointment spots in the next X hours (to prevent last-minute sign-ups).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This system has saved me a great deal of time. The back-and-forth of emails is no more. I share my public appointment link, people sign up, and they get contact info (for video chat or my office location). And Appointments works with timezones, so there’s no adjustment needed on either end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who fill out the form get an email, I get an email, and appointments adds the spot to my calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s brilliant. Sergey Mosin, the developer, gets 5 stars from me for helping with the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="FALD" /><summary type="html">I used an exclamation point intentionally, because the Appointments app for Nextcloud is just that awesome. As a professor, I keep office hours and encourage students to meet with me. And, I also need to advise graduate students at various institutions around the world. And this is not to mention meeting with other professors I’m collaborating with – again, from around the world. In the past, setting up meetings went a bit like this: Them: Hey, can we meet? Me: Sure! When do you want to meet? Them: I’m free Mondays and Fridays. Me: How about noon on Monday? Them: Actually, I have an appointment them. What day of the week works for you? Me: Wednesdays and Fridays. Them: Great! What about 1 on Wednesday? Me: Sure! Them: What timezone are you in? Me: Central. Them: Oh! Then 1 pm for you is 9 pm for me. Etc, etc. Each of these being an email, of course, and usually with a delay of several hours between them. As they used to say in the commercials, “there’s got to be a better way!” Nextcloud Appointments is that better way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">September update</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/09/10/Update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="September update" /><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/09/10/Update</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/09/10/Update.html">&lt;p&gt;I took a bit more time off, at least from this blog, but it’s late September and I really should be back in school. And I am. Classes just started up at LaTech, and with them my attention turns to reading and writing about FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I have done in the intervening past few weeks is publish another post to The Reboot, this time &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereboot.com/cracking-open-the-android-ios-grip-on-smartphones-and-the-mobile-internet/&quot;&gt;focusing on the state of FOSS phones&lt;/a&gt;. I had the pleasure of talking to Ioana Luncheon of Fairphone, Lukasz Erecinski of PINE64, and Félim Whiteley of Late Night Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also been digging into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethicalsource.dev/&quot;&gt;Ethical Source&lt;/a&gt; movement, which is producing a new version of the Hippocratic License for software projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I’ve been steadily working on a co-authored paper on Mastodon, the federated social networking site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a lot going on, and a lot more to come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I’m getting ever closer to revealing my Goal 2: Book Project on the blog. I want to blog out my progress openly. To do that, of course, I’ll have to clarify my project!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and other stuff on the to-do list includes figuring out a new commenting system, since Staticman is no longer working.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">I took a bit more time off, at least from this blog, but it’s late September and I really should be back in school. And I am. Classes just started up at LaTech, and with them my attention turns to reading and writing about FOSS. One thing I have done in the intervening past few weeks is publish another post to The Reboot, this time focusing on the state of FOSS phones. I had the pleasure of talking to Ioana Luncheon of Fairphone, Lukasz Erecinski of PINE64, and Félim Whiteley of Late Night Linux. I’ve also been digging into the Ethical Source movement, which is producing a new version of the Hippocratic License for software projects. And, I’ve been steadily working on a co-authored paper on Mastodon, the federated social networking site. So, a lot going on, and a lot more to come! In fact, I’m getting ever closer to revealing my Goal 2: Book Project on the blog. I want to blog out my progress openly. To do that, of course, I’ll have to clarify my project! Oh, and other stuff on the to-do list includes figuring out a new commenting system, since Staticman is no longer working.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Manjaro Mania!</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/07/18/Manjaro-Madness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manjaro Mania!" /><published>2021-07-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/07/18/Manjaro%20Madness</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/07/18/Manjaro-Madness.html">&lt;p&gt;I made a change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I droppped Ubuntu 18.04 for Manjaro (Mate, of course). And it’s going great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/manjaro.png&quot; alt=&quot;Manjaro Logo&quot; title=&quot;Manjaro&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manjaro feels a lot like Linux Mint back around 2010 – it’s detecting hardware (including hardware needing proprietary drivers) flawlessly. In fact, that was my biggest concern with the Dell computer I’m using. The day I got this computer it had Ubuntu 18.04 installed, which I was fine with. The first thing I did, however, broke the hardware support: I updated the computer. That’s it. &amp;lt;pre&amp;gt;sudo apt update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo apt upgrade -y&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt; killed the sound and, very likely, the special power management firmware this Dell required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working with Dell support, I got a particular Ubuntu image and got things running. However, I was always nervous that any upgrade would kill a lot of hardware. I even went so far as to stick with one kernel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I kept hearing about Manjaro – how they’re working on the PinePhone, how many people are running it, and how running an Arch-based distro means that there’s no need to do OS reinstallations. Given that Ubuntu 18.04 is showing its age, I tried running Manjaro off a USB drive on the laptop and… all good. So I took the plunge and installed Manjaro instead of Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Manjaro’s community version with MATE has gone pretty much seamlessly. I can still do the setup I prefer, with devilspie moving windows to workspaces, and all my favorite applications (Libreoffice, Zotero) are running great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, now I get to explore the world of pacman. I am really comfortable with apt, but pacman is just as easy to use, and I’m starting to see the appeal of having the latest versions of various software packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I’ve gone Manjaro Mental and put it on my son’s laptop and another computer, as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have Ubuntu boxes – mainly as servers – so I don’t think I will ever leave Ubuntu behind, but for now I’m diggin’ Manjaro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I still know: I cannot truly say “I use Arch btw…”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Manjaro" /><summary type="html">I made a change. I droppped Ubuntu 18.04 for Manjaro (Mate, of course). And it’s going great!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">(Almost) De-Googled Research</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/07/03/DeGoogleSearch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="(Almost) De-Googled Research" /><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/07/03/DeGoogleSearch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/07/03/DeGoogleSearch.html">&lt;p&gt;Big news on the search front! The Brave Browser is now &lt;a href=&quot;https://search.brave.com/&quot;&gt;offering a search engine&lt;/a&gt;. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://brave.com/brave-search-beta/&quot;&gt;their announcment&lt;/a&gt;, Brave Search promises “independent option for search which gives them unmatched privacy” and will use an independent index, rather than rely on Google or Microsoft. I’ve already started playing with Brave Search and am curious to see how it develops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, any time someone offers a search engine and their corporate parent isn’t named Alphabet, there’s a pretty predictable reaction: “Good on them for trying, but you just can’t beat Google.”  I’ve also heard academics say the same thing: “I can’t find anything without Google.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Search is, of course, a very common approach to conducting research, and it’s especially important to my work on Internet cultures. One key way to study the Internet is by searching it. And it seems as though that means all my work ought to flow through Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t really thought much about this situation until just recently. Along with Sean Lawson, I co-authored a book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/social-engineering&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Engineering: How Crowdmasters, Phreaks, Hackers, and Trolls Created a New Form of Manipulative Communication&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It will come out from MIT Press in a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is the result of four years of research on hacker social engineering practices as well as early 20th century propaganda and public relations (a field that also referred to its activity as “social engineering”). After finishing this latest book, I realized I’m a living testament to the fact that yes, you can de-Google your search and still conduct research. Because that’s what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/antiGoogle.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google logo with a line through it&quot; title=&quot;Google logo with a line through it&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how I conducted mostly de-Googled searches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;startpage&quot;&gt;Startpage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bulk of my research – especially my research on the history of hacker social engineers – relied on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.startpage.com&quot;&gt;Startpage&lt;/a&gt; searches, especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.startpage.com/en/advanced-search.html&quot;&gt;the advanced search features&lt;/a&gt;. I used those find obscure documents and websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I can already hear many of you: “Startpage uses Google’s index!” Indeed, it does. One way to think of it is using Google through a proxy. But that’s not entirely the case. First of all, Startpage uses its own algorithms to sort Google’s index, so it differs in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more importantly, Startpage does not customize search results based on my previous searches. I find that to be &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; important, because as a scholar focusing on the Internet cultures, I don’t want my previous search biases affecting what I find. I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to find unusual stuff that surprises me, not the most optimized result for me. I’m not looking for a donut shop near me that has the type of donuts I prefer; I’m looking for obscure text files, PDFs, and websites – things I haven’t found before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;archiveorg&quot;&gt;Archive.org&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; is… I can’t think of good superlatives. Awesome? Invaluable? The coolest thing ever? In any case, all Internet Studies work should engage with the IA at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet Archive has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.protocol.com/internet-archive-preserving-future&quot;&gt;massive database&lt;/a&gt; – roughly 90 petabytes. Despite its size, the IA also offers its own search engine, mostly returning text-based results. Those results usually get me in the vicinity of what I’m looking for – often it’s a matter of searching within PDFs, which the IA also allows for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;worldcatorg&quot;&gt;Worldcat.org&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org&quot;&gt;Worldcat&lt;/a&gt; is a metasearch for holdings in libraries around the world. I often use it to get very good metadata on books for &lt;a href=&quot;https://zotero.org&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;. Google Books and Amazon metadata are usually awful, missing fields like publisher, publisher city, and sometimes the author’s name. Worldcat, however, has been consistently good for metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond that, Worldcat’s metasearch of libraries reveals a wealth of historical insight. Knowing the rhythm of book publications – for example, Walter Lippmann’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/public-opinion/oclc/1252782253/editions?start_edition=261&amp;amp;sd=desc&amp;amp;referer=di&amp;amp;se=yr&amp;amp;editionsView=true&amp;amp;fq=&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Public Opinion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; appeared in 1922, and Edward Bernays’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/crystallizing-public-opinion/oclc/226657356&amp;amp;referer=brief_results&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crystalizing Public Opinion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; appeared in 1923 – can tell me a lot about the “dialog” happening among authors. Plus, Worldcat also returns results for scholarly articles and other media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unfortunately-google-scholar&quot;&gt;Unfortunately: Google Scholar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said “mostly de-Googled,” and by that I did not mean the fact that Startpage uses Google’s index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, by that I mean that there’s no substitute for Google Scholar, and over the course of writing &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering,&lt;/em&gt; I relied on Google Scholar very heavily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always watching for alternatives to Google Scholar, but they consistently come up short. I often use a vanity search for my own work to test a given database – mainly because I know what I’ve published over the years. Google Scholar finds my publications right away. &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.microsoft.com&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s academic search&lt;/a&gt; seems to miss quite a bit, though it’s better than it used to be. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scinapse.io&quot;&gt;Scinapse&lt;/a&gt; – who argues they’re “better than Google Scholar” – also fails to find many of my papers. I’m not sure what &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.refseek.com&quot;&gt;Refseek&lt;/a&gt; is trying to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one I had high hopes for is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.base-search.net&quot;&gt;Bielefield Academic Search Engine&lt;/a&gt; (BASE), mainly because it is run by a university library (Bielefeld University Library). But the results there – for my admittedly vain search for my own work – is also underwhelming. I believe I can “claim” my profile and add papers manually, but who has time for that? After years of building profiles in Academia.edu, ResearchGate, or SSRN, I’m done with all that. I could spend my life building profiles of myself instead of, you know, &lt;em&gt;doing research.&lt;/em&gt; Instead, I just put my papers &lt;a href=&quot;https://robertwgehl.org/text/pubs/&quot;&gt;on my own website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upshot to Google Scholar is, for better or worse, it finds my papers automatically. And because of that, I’m pretty confident that I can find other people’s papers in Google Scholar – which is, of course, what I actually use it for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-searching&quot;&gt;Keep Searching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there you have it. There is search beyond Google. It can be done. At the very least, thanks to Startpage, you don’t have to use Google proper – and this is not even to mention DuckDuckGo or, of course, Brave Search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Google Scholar still seems indispensible, but I can even imagine doing a project without using Google Scholar, relying on a mix of Worldcat.org and maybe Microsoft Academic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have I missed anything? Any of you done research without having it flow through Google? Let me know in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Google" /><category term="Startpage" /><category term="DuckDuckGo" /><category term="Brave" /><summary type="html">Big news on the search front! The Brave Browser is now offering a search engine. According to their announcment, Brave Search promises “independent option for search which gives them unmatched privacy” and will use an independent index, rather than rely on Google or Microsoft. I’ve already started playing with Brave Search and am curious to see how it develops. However, any time someone offers a search engine and their corporate parent isn’t named Alphabet, there’s a pretty predictable reaction: “Good on them for trying, but you just can’t beat Google.” I’ve also heard academics say the same thing: “I can’t find anything without Google.” Search is, of course, a very common approach to conducting research, and it’s especially important to my work on Internet cultures. One key way to study the Internet is by searching it. And it seems as though that means all my work ought to flow through Google. I hadn’t really thought much about this situation until just recently. Along with Sean Lawson, I co-authored a book, Social Engineering: How Crowdmasters, Phreaks, Hackers, and Trolls Created a New Form of Manipulative Communication. It will come out from MIT Press in a few months. The book is the result of four years of research on hacker social engineering practices as well as early 20th century propaganda and public relations (a field that also referred to its activity as “social engineering”). After finishing this latest book, I realized I’m a living testament to the fact that yes, you can de-Google your search and still conduct research. Because that’s what I did.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Vacation and F-Droid</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/06/24/Vacation-and-FDroid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Vacation and F-Droid" /><published>2021-06-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-06-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/06/24/Vacation%20and%20FDroid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/06/24/Vacation-and-FDroid.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve not posted for a while. And that’s ok. Why? Because we all need a break. A vacation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You. You there. You should take a break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did. It’s ok. The work will be there later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gentooBeach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Gentoo penguin frolicking on a beach somewhere&quot; title=&quot;A Gentoo penguin frolicking on a beach somewhere&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While traveling with family and seeing my friends, I once again relied heavily on a device I begrudgingly have: a mobile phone, in this case a Google Android device. While I work really hard to avoid apps or limit their permissions, I just &lt;em&gt;don’t like&lt;/em&gt; having Google anything in my pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while I have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pine64.org/pinephone/&quot;&gt;PinePhone&lt;/a&gt; Braveheart edition, it’s just not ready to be my main phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in the interim, I’m doing something I should have done a while ago: trying out &lt;a href=&quot;https://f-droid.org/en/packages/org.fdroid.fdroid/&quot;&gt;F-Droid&lt;/a&gt;, the FOSS collection of Android apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired in part by an interview I had with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/felimwhiteley&quot;&gt;Félim Whiteley&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://latenightlinux.com/&quot;&gt;Late Night Linux&lt;/a&gt; podcast. Whiteley is a well-known de-Googler. The interview will be used as a part of the research for a forthcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereboot.com&quot;&gt;Reboot&lt;/a&gt; article I’m working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I guess the vacation wasn’t all vacation, because I found myself mucking about with FOSS, once again. This time on my phone. But, hey, that’s the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream for you. I can’t turn it off easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More posts soon!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="F Droid" /><summary type="html">I’ve not posted for a while. And that’s ok. Why? Because we all need a break. A vacation. You. You there. You should take a break. I did. It’s ok. The work will be there later. While traveling with family and seeing my friends, I once again relied heavily on a device I begrudgingly have: a mobile phone, in this case a Google Android device. While I work really hard to avoid apps or limit their permissions, I just don’t like having Google anything in my pocket. And while I have a PinePhone Braveheart edition, it’s just not ready to be my main phone. So, in the interim, I’m doing something I should have done a while ago: trying out F-Droid, the FOSS collection of Android apps. I was inspired in part by an interview I had with Félim Whiteley of the Late Night Linux podcast. Whiteley is a well-known de-Googler. The interview will be used as a part of the research for a forthcoming Reboot article I’m working on. So I guess the vacation wasn’t all vacation, because I found myself mucking about with FOSS, once again. This time on my phone. But, hey, that’s the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream for you. I can’t turn it off easily. More posts soon!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FALD Updates</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/05/14/FALDupdate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FALD Updates" /><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/05/14/FALDupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/05/14/FALDupdate.html">&lt;p&gt;A few quick updates on the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nextcloud-ftw&quot;&gt;Nextcloud FTW&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while back, &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/02/07/CloudAcademic.html&quot;&gt;I asked people on Mastodon about FOSS tools for academics&lt;/a&gt;. A clear winner was Nextcloud. Since then, I’ve gone pretty much all-in on Nextcloud, using it to sync my ODT files (those are like DOCX, but better) across my machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ve gotten so much more our of it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/spreed&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/a&gt; app has worked flawlessly for one-on-one video chats with friends and colleagues. I think it’s easier to use than Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s a downright magical add-on called &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/appointments&quot;&gt;Appointments&lt;/a&gt;. I am &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/6CWrR1Neoj0?t=19&quot;&gt;never, ever, ever, ever&lt;/a&gt; going back to emailing back and forth, back and forth with anyone who wants to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;“How’s your Monday?” “I’m free after 1.” “How about 1.30.” “Oh, wait, I can’t make Monday, after all. How’s your Tuesday?”&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, with Appointments I share a public link, whomever wants to meet fills in a form, and the meeting is on my calendar, and they get instructions on how to meet (a chat link, office address, etc). In addition, Appointments watches my calendar, so people will not double-book. And, I can set a delay (say, 8 hours from &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;) where people can’t schedule, so no one can schedule a last-minute meeting. It’s worked really, really well with student office hours. And none of it relies on the Googles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zotero-beta-progress&quot;&gt;Zotero Beta Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also talked to people on Mastodon about ways in which academics like me – that is, ones who don’t really code all that much – can contribute to FOSS. The consensus was: bug reporting. So I &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/02/ZoteroComments.html&quot;&gt;joined the Zotero 6 Beta&lt;/a&gt;, did some testing, and reported bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a strange, happy feeling today because Zotero fixed the issues I reported. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/02/ZoteroComments.html&quot;&gt;note-taking lag I reported&lt;/a&gt; is now gone. Notes are as smooth as before the beta, but with more features, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This moment of bug-reporting joy has inspired me to report more bugs to other projects. And in turn, I feel a little bit more connected to the software I’m using to live the Lifestyle Dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hunt-for-card-sorting-software&quot;&gt;The hunt for card sorting software…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did have a recent FOSS failure, however: I could not find card sorting software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Card sorting is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/card-sorting.html&quot;&gt;a technique used in web information architecture and usability&lt;/a&gt; work. When I taught basic web design, card sorts were an integral part of the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cart sorting asks you to write down every idea or bit of information associated with the website on 3x5 cards. The idea is to not censor one’s self – just write them down, one idea per card. Then, you can take the cards and sort them – these 5 cards relate to this central idea, those 6 relate to another, and so on. Eventually, the cards reveal the “information architecture” of a site, and this leads to creating top-level navigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students seemed to get a lot out of web design card sorts. And I started to see them as quite useful for planning book projects. I used the technique during the early days of writing my soon-to-be-released book on social engineering (co-authored with Sean Lawson, and due out from MIT Press). Card sorting, it seems to me, is quite similar to the “maps” that Adele Clarke talks about in her book &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/books/situational-analysis-grounded-theory-after-the-interpretive-turn/9781452260907&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Situational Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s the obvious downside to 3x5 cards: they’re not searchable. Sorting them is easy enough, and I can take a picture of a sort – and other people could sort them, too – but I’m not sure how useful those sorts are in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I was on the hunt for FOSS tools to do card sorts and… nothing. The closest thing I could find are notebook tools or mind-maps, but both are not flexible enough for this task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, back to the stack o’ cards for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-why-hunt-for-card-sorting-software&quot;&gt;…But why hunt for card sorting software?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is… Goal 2. One of my goals for this blog is to write a book about FOSS. But I can’t write about all the FOSS. That’s too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have settled on a project to explore. I want to use it as a central “character.” I will reveal which one it is when I think the moment is right, which is… after I do a card sort!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Nextcloud" /><category term="Zotero" /><category term="FALD" /><category term="goal 1" /><category term="goal 2" /><summary type="html">A few quick updates on the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream front.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Messin’ with Wireguard</title><link href="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/04/29/Wireguard.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Messin’ with Wireguard" /><published>2021-04-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/04/29/Wireguard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://10.0.0.5:4000/2021/04/29/Wireguard.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been messin’ about with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wireguard.com/&quot;&gt;Wireguard&lt;/a&gt; and – after some hiccups – I have a small network of peers connected. I now have a couple laptops, a desktop, a phone, and a Raspberry Pi all networked, with the connection remaining persistent even as the mobile devices move across wi-fi networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wireguard.svg&quot; alt=&quot;The Wireguard logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My proudest achievement is connecting this network to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/&quot;&gt;Pi-hole&lt;/a&gt; installation on a Digital Ocean VPS. Now all those Internet ads cannot reach me, not matter where on the network I am. I should probably allow ads, since I am a media studies scholar and &lt;a href=&quot;https://xroads.virginia.edu/~DRBR2/rwilliams.pdf&quot;&gt;ads are staple object of media studies&lt;/a&gt;. But then again, I’m addicted to things like &lt;a href=&quot;https://marketingland.com/pop-up-ads-why-everyone-hates-them-and-why-theyll-never-die-273343&quot;&gt;actually being able to read websites&lt;/a&gt;, having them &lt;a href=&quot;https://thetechieguy.com/ad-blocker-impact-internet-speed/&quot;&gt;load quickly&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://brianchristner.io/how-a-single-raspberry-pi-made-my-home-network-faster/&quot;&gt;not being tracked&lt;/a&gt;, so… yeah, I’ll pass on the ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a Wireguard-based network, I can SSH into any of my computers. It’s rare that I have to do that, but sometimes I forget to sync a file – say, a lecture, or a PDF of an article. No worries there – just log into a remote computer and grab it. I’m starting to think about setting up my own personal media streaming system, as well. Because, why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wireguard is billed as faster and easier to work with than OVPN, and in my view, it’s living up to the billing. 
Setting things up initially took a long while, with my mistakes including not setting up rules in my firewalls (I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/ufw-essentials-common-firewall-rules-and-commands&quot;&gt;UFW&lt;/a&gt;). Once I figured out how to allow connections from the network I was building, it began to work quite well. And it is fast – the network speed is nearly as fast as without the VPN in place. (In fact, I’m pretty sure my ISP, Suddenlink, is dropping packets from internet radio streams – but with Wireguard, those packets aren’t dropping).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One tip I can offer: I discovered a need for a “PersistentKeepalive” on that Pi-hole server. This appears to be a bit of a no-no with Wireguard, which is built on the idea that “silence is golden” – i.e., the less packets flying aorund the better. But the Pi-hole peer kept dropping off the network, and thus my DNS lookups wouldn’t happen. By adding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;PersistentKeepalive = 25
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to the Pi-hole [Peer] section of the client config file, the connection stays active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of you are itchin’ to try some Wireguard, I have found the tutorial at &lt;a href=&quot;https://serversideup.net/courses/gain-flexibility-and-increase-privacy-with-wireguard-vpn/&quot;&gt;ServerSide Up&lt;/a&gt; to be really helpful. That, and my old friend “trying stuff until it works”…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/try.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A parody of O'Reilly tech books. This cover says &amp;quot;Trying Stuff Until It Works&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EDIT: I got KDE Connect working! You just have to &lt;a href=&quot;https://userbase.kde.org/KDEConnect#Running_KDE_Connect_over_OpenVPN&quot;&gt;add devices by IP address&lt;/a&gt;! That is &lt;em&gt;so cool.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Wireguard" /><category term="FALD" /><summary type="html">I’ve been messin’ about with Wireguard and – after some hiccups – I have a small network of peers connected. I now have a couple laptops, a desktop, a phone, and a Raspberry Pi all networked, with the connection remaining persistent even as the mobile devices move across wi-fi networks.</summary></entry></feed>