<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-03T13:40:18-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">(Almost) De-Googled Research</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/07/03/DeGoogleSearch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="(Almost) De-Googled Research" /><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/07/03/DeGoogleSearch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/07/03/DeGoogleSearch.html">&lt;p&gt;Big news on the search front! The Brave Browser is now &lt;a href=&quot;https://search.brave.com/&quot;&gt;offering a search engine&lt;/a&gt;. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://brave.com/brave-search-beta/&quot;&gt;their announcment&lt;/a&gt;, Brave Search promises “independent option for search which gives them unmatched privacy” and will use an independent index, rather than rely on Google or Microsoft. I’ve already started playing with Brave Search and am curious to see how it develops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, any time someone offers a search engine and their corporate parent isn’t named Alphbet, there’s a pretty predictable reaction: “Good on them for trying, but you just can’t beat Google.”  I’ve also heard academics say the same thing: “I can’t find anything without Google.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Search is, of course, a very common approach to conducting research, and it’s especially important to my work on Internet cultures. One key way to study the Internet is by searching it. And it seems as though that means all my work ought to flow through Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t really thought much about this situation until just recently. Along with Sean Lawson, I co-authored a book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/social-engineering&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Engineering: How Crowdmasters, Phreaks, Hackers, and Trolls Created a New Form of Manipulative Communication&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It will come out from MIT Press in a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is the result of four years of research on hacker social engineering practices as well as early 20th century propaganda and public relations (a field that also referred to its activity as “social engineering”). After finishing this latest book, I realized I’m a living testament to the fact that yes, you can de-Google your search and still conduct research. Because that’s what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/antiGoogle.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google logo with a line through it&quot; title=&quot;Google logo with a line through it&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how I conducted mostly de-Googled searches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;startpage&quot;&gt;Startpage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bulk of my research – especially my research on the history of hacker social engineers – relied on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.startpage.com&quot;&gt;Startpage&lt;/a&gt; searches, especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.startpage.com/en/advanced-search.html&quot;&gt;the advanced search features&lt;/a&gt;. I used those find obscure documents and websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I can already hear many of you: “Startpage uses Google’s index!” Indeed, it does. One way to think of it is using Google through a proxy. But that’s not entirely the case. First of all, Startpage uses its own algorithms to sort Google’s index, so it differs in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more importantly, Startpage does not customize search results based on my previous searches. I find that to be &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; important, because as a scholar focusing on the Internet cultures, I don’t want my previous search biases affecting what I find. I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to find unusual stuff that surprises me, not the most optimized result for me. I’m not looking for a donut shop near me that has the type of donuts I prefer; I’m looking for obscure text files, PDFs, and websites – things I haven’t found before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;archiveorg&quot;&gt;Archive.org&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; is… I can’t think of good superlatives. Awesome? Invaluable? The coolest thing ever? In any case, all Internet Studies work should engage with the IA at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet Archive has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.protocol.com/internet-archive-preserving-future&quot;&gt;massive database&lt;/a&gt; – roughly 90 petabytes. Despite its size, the IA also offers its own search engine, mostly returning text-based results. Those results usually get me in the vicinity of what I’m looking for – often it’s a matter of searching within PDFs, which the IA also allows for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;worldcatorg&quot;&gt;Worldcat.org&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org&quot;&gt;Worldcat&lt;/a&gt; is a metasearch for holdings in libraries around the world. I often use it to get very good metadata on books for &lt;a href=&quot;https://zotero.org&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;. Google Books and Amazon metadata are usually awful, missing fields like publisher, publisher city, and sometimes the author’s name. Worldcat, however, has been consistently good for metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond that, Worldcat’s metasearch of libraries reveals a wealth of historical insight. Knowing the rhythm of book publications – for example, Walter Lippmann’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/public-opinion/oclc/1252782253/editions?start_edition=261&amp;amp;sd=desc&amp;amp;referer=di&amp;amp;se=yr&amp;amp;editionsView=true&amp;amp;fq=&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Public Opinion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; appeared in 1922, and Edward Bernays’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/title/crystallizing-public-opinion/oclc/226657356&amp;amp;referer=brief_results&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crystalizing Public Opinion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; appeared in 1923 – can tell me a lot about the “dialog” happening among authors. Plus, Worldcat also returns results for scholarly articles and other media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unfortunately-google-scholar&quot;&gt;Unfortunately: Google Scholar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said “mostly de-Googled,” and by that I did not mean the fact that Startpage uses Google’s index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, by that I mean that there’s no substitute for Google Scholar, and over the course of writing &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering,&lt;/em&gt; I relied on Google Scholar very heavily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always watching for alternatives to Google Scholar, but they consistently come up short. I often use a vanity search for my own work to test a given database – mainly because I know what I’ve published over the years. Google Scholar finds my publications right away. &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.microsoft.com&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s academic search&lt;/a&gt; seems to miss quite a bit, though it’s better than it used to be. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scinapse.io&quot;&gt;Scinapse&lt;/a&gt; – who argues they’re “better than Google Scholar” – also fails to find many of my papers. I’m not sure what &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.refseek.com&quot;&gt;Refseek&lt;/a&gt; is trying to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one I had high hopes for is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.base-search.net&quot;&gt;Bielefield Academic Search Engine&lt;/a&gt; (BASE), mainly because it is run by a university library (Bielefeld University Library). But the results there – for my admittedly vain search for my own work – is also underwhelming. I believe I can “claim” my profile and add papers manually, but who has time for that? After years of building profiles in Academia.edu, ResearchGate, or SSRN, I’m done with all that. I could spend my life building profiles of myself instead of, you know, &lt;em&gt;doing research.&lt;/em&gt; Instead, I just put my papers &lt;a href=&quot;https://robertwgehl.org/text/pubs/&quot;&gt;on my own website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upshot to Google Scholar is, for better or worse, it finds my papers automatically. And because of that, I’m pretty confident that I can find other people’s papers in Google Scholar – which is, of course, what I actually use it for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-searching&quot;&gt;Keep Searching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there you have it. There is search beyond Google. It can be done. At the very least, thanks to Startpage, you don’t have to use Google proper – and this is not even to mention DuckDuckGo or, of course, Brave Search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Google Scholar still seems indispensible, but I can even imagine doing a project without using Google Scholar, relying on a mix of Worldcat.org and maybe Microsoft Academic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have I missed anything? Any of you done research without having it flow through Google? Let me know in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Google" /><category term="Startpage" /><category term="DuckDuckGo" /><category term="Brave" /><summary type="html">Big news on the search front! The Brave Browser is now offering a search engine. According to their announcment, Brave Search promises “independent option for search which gives them unmatched privacy” and will use an independent index, rather than rely on Google or Microsoft. I’ve already started playing with Brave Search and am curious to see how it develops. However, any time someone offers a search engine and their corporate parent isn’t named Alphbet, there’s a pretty predictable reaction: “Good on them for trying, but you just can’t beat Google.” I’ve also heard academics say the same thing: “I can’t find anything without Google.” Search is, of course, a very common approach to conducting research, and it’s especially important to my work on Internet cultures. One key way to study the Internet is by searching it. And it seems as though that means all my work ought to flow through Google. I hadn’t really thought much about this situation until just recently. Along with Sean Lawson, I co-authored a book, Social Engineering: How Crowdmasters, Phreaks, Hackers, and Trolls Created a New Form of Manipulative Communication. It will come out from MIT Press in a few months. The book is the result of four years of research on hacker social engineering practices as well as early 20th century propaganda and public relations (a field that also referred to its activity as “social engineering”). After finishing this latest book, I realized I’m a living testament to the fact that yes, you can de-Google your search and still conduct research. Because that’s what I did.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Vacation and F-Droid</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/06/24/Vacation-and-FDroid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Vacation and F-Droid" /><published>2021-06-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-06-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/06/24/Vacation%20and%20FDroid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/06/24/Vacation-and-FDroid.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve not posted for a while. And that’s ok. Why? Because we all need a break. A vacation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You. You there. You should take a break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did. It’s ok. The work will be there later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gentooBeach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Gentoo penguin frolicking on a beach somewhere&quot; title=&quot;A Gentoo penguin frolicking on a beach somewhere&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While traveling with family and seeing my friends, I once again relied heavily on a device I begrudgingly have: a mobile phone, in this case a Google Android device. While I work really hard to avoid apps or limit their permissions, I just &lt;em&gt;don’t like&lt;/em&gt; having Google anything in my pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while I have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pine64.org/pinephone/&quot;&gt;PinePhone&lt;/a&gt; Braveheart edition, it’s just not ready to be my main phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in the interim, I’m doing something I should have done a while ago: trying out &lt;a href=&quot;https://f-droid.org/en/packages/org.fdroid.fdroid/&quot;&gt;F-Droid&lt;/a&gt;, the FOSS collection of Android apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired in part by an interview I had with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/felimwhiteley&quot;&gt;Félim Whiteley&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://latenightlinux.com/&quot;&gt;Late Night Linux&lt;/a&gt; podcast. Whiteley is a well-known de-Googler. The interview will be used as a part of the research for a forthcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereboot.com&quot;&gt;Reboot&lt;/a&gt; article I’m working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I guess the vacation wasn’t all vacation, because I found myself mucking about with FOSS, once again. This time on my phone. But, hey, that’s the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream for you. I can’t turn it off easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More posts soon!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="F Droid" /><summary type="html">I’ve not posted for a while. And that’s ok. Why? Because we all need a break. A vacation. You. You there. You should take a break. I did. It’s ok. The work will be there later. While traveling with family and seeing my friends, I once again relied heavily on a device I begrudgingly have: a mobile phone, in this case a Google Android device. While I work really hard to avoid apps or limit their permissions, I just don’t like having Google anything in my pocket. And while I have a PinePhone Braveheart edition, it’s just not ready to be my main phone. So, in the interim, I’m doing something I should have done a while ago: trying out F-Droid, the FOSS collection of Android apps. I was inspired in part by an interview I had with Félim Whiteley of the Late Night Linux podcast. Whiteley is a well-known de-Googler. The interview will be used as a part of the research for a forthcoming Reboot article I’m working on. So I guess the vacation wasn’t all vacation, because I found myself mucking about with FOSS, once again. This time on my phone. But, hey, that’s the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream for you. I can’t turn it off easily. More posts soon!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FALD Updates</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/05/14/FALDupdate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FALD Updates" /><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/05/14/FALDupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/05/14/FALDupdate.html">&lt;p&gt;A few quick updates on the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nextcloud-ftw&quot;&gt;Nextcloud FTW&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while back, &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/02/07/CloudAcademic.html&quot;&gt;I asked people on Mastodon about FOSS tools for academics&lt;/a&gt;. A clear winner was Nextcloud. Since then, I’ve gone pretty much all-in on Nextcloud, using it to sync my ODT files (those are like DOCX, but better) across my machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’ve gotten so much more our of it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/spreed&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/a&gt; app has worked flawlessly for one-on-one video chats with friends and colleagues. I think it’s easier to use than Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s a downright magical add-on called &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/appointments&quot;&gt;Appointments&lt;/a&gt;. I am &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/6CWrR1Neoj0?t=19&quot;&gt;never, ever, ever, ever&lt;/a&gt; going back to emailing back and forth, back and forth with anyone who wants to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;“How’s your Monday?” “I’m free after 1.” “How about 1.30.” “Oh, wait, I can’t make Monday, after all. How’s your Tuesday?”&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, with Appointments I share a public link, whomever wants to meet fills in a form, and the meeting is on my calendar, and they get instructions on how to meet (a chat link, office address, etc). In addition, Appointments watches my calendar, so people will not double-book. And, I can set a delay (say, 8 hours from &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;) where people can’t schedule, so no one can schedule a last-minute meeting. It’s worked really, really well with student office hours. And none of it relies on the Googles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zotero-beta-progress&quot;&gt;Zotero Beta Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also talked to people on Mastodon about ways in which academics like me – that is, ones who don’t really code all that much – can contribute to FOSS. The consensus was: bug reporting. So I &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/02/ZoteroComments.html&quot;&gt;joined the Zotero 6 Beta&lt;/a&gt;, did some testing, and reported bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a strange, happy feeling today because Zotero fixed the issues I reported. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/02/ZoteroComments.html&quot;&gt;note-taking lag I reported&lt;/a&gt; is now gone. Notes are as smooth as before the beta, but with more features, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This moment of bug-reporting joy has inspired me to report more bugs to other projects. And in turn, I feel a little bit more connected to the software I’m using to live the Lifestyle Dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hunt-for-card-sorting-software&quot;&gt;The hunt for card sorting software…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did have a recent FOSS failure, however: I could not find card sorting software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Card sorting is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/card-sorting.html&quot;&gt;a technique used in web information architecture and usability&lt;/a&gt; work. When I taught basic web design, card sorts were an integral part of the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cart sorting asks you to write down every idea or bit of information associated with the website on 3x5 cards. The idea is to not censor one’s self – just write them down, one idea per card. Then, you can take the cards and sort them – these 5 cards relate to this central idea, those 6 relate to another, and so on. Eventually, the cards reveal the “information architecture” of a site, and this leads to creating top-level navigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students seemed to get a lot out of web design card sorts. And I started to see them as quite useful for planning book projects. I used the technique during the early days of writing my soon-to-be-released book on social engineering (co-authored with Sean Lawson, and due out from MIT Press). Card sorting, it seems to me, is quite similar to the “maps” that Adele Clarke talks about in her book &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/books/situational-analysis-grounded-theory-after-the-interpretive-turn/9781452260907&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Situational Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s the obvious downside to 3x5 cards: they’re not searchable. Sorting them is easy enough, and I can take a picture of a sort – and other people could sort them, too – but I’m not sure how useful those sorts are in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I was on the hunt for FOSS tools to do card sorts and… nothing. The closest thing I could find are notebook tools or mind-maps, but both are not flexible enough for this task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, back to the stack o’ cards for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-why-hunt-for-card-sorting-software&quot;&gt;…But why hunt for card sorting software?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is… Goal 2. One of my goals for this blog is to write a book about FOSS. But I can’t write about all the FOSS. That’s too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have settled on a project to explore. I want to use it as a central “character.” I will reveal which one it is when I think the moment is right, which is… after I do a card sort!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Nextcloud" /><category term="Zotero" /><category term="FALD" /><category term="goal 1" /><category term="goal 2" /><summary type="html">A few quick updates on the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream front.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Messin’ with Wireguard</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/29/Wireguard.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Messin’ with Wireguard" /><published>2021-04-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/29/Wireguard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/29/Wireguard.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been messin’ about with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wireguard.com/&quot;&gt;Wireguard&lt;/a&gt; and – after some hiccups – I have a small network of peers connected. I now have a couple laptops, a desktop, a phone, and a Raspberry Pi all networked, with the connection remaining persistent even as the mobile devices move across wi-fi networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wireguard.svg&quot; alt=&quot;The Wireguard logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My proudest achievement is connecting this network to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/&quot;&gt;Pi-hole&lt;/a&gt; installation on a Digital Ocean VPS. Now all those Internet ads cannot reach me, not matter where on the network I am. I should probably allow ads, since I am a media studies scholar and &lt;a href=&quot;https://xroads.virginia.edu/~DRBR2/rwilliams.pdf&quot;&gt;ads are staple object of media studies&lt;/a&gt;. But then again, I’m addicted to things like &lt;a href=&quot;https://marketingland.com/pop-up-ads-why-everyone-hates-them-and-why-theyll-never-die-273343&quot;&gt;actually being able to read websites&lt;/a&gt;, having them &lt;a href=&quot;https://thetechieguy.com/ad-blocker-impact-internet-speed/&quot;&gt;load quickly&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://brianchristner.io/how-a-single-raspberry-pi-made-my-home-network-faster/&quot;&gt;not being tracked&lt;/a&gt;, so… yeah, I’ll pass on the ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a Wireguard-based network, I can SSH into any of my computers. It’s rare that I have to do that, but sometimes I forget to sync a file – say, a lecture, or a PDF of an article. No worries there – just log into a remote computer and grab it. I’m starting to think about setting up my own personal media streaming system, as well. Because, why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wireguard is billed as faster and easier to work with than OVPN, and in my view, it’s living up to the billing. 
Setting things up initially took a long while, with my mistakes including not setting up rules in my firewalls (I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/ufw-essentials-common-firewall-rules-and-commands&quot;&gt;UFW&lt;/a&gt;). Once I figured out how to allow connections from the network I was building, it began to work quite well. And it is fast – the network speed is nearly as fast as without the VPN in place. (In fact, I’m pretty sure my ISP, Suddenlink, is dropping packets from internet radio streams – but with Wireguard, those packets aren’t dropping).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One tip I can offer: I discovered a need for a “PersistentKeepalive” on that Pi-hole server. This appears to be a bit of a no-no with Wireguard, which is built on the idea that “silence is golden” – i.e., the less packets flying aorund the better. But the Pi-hole peer kept dropping off the network, and thus my DNS lookups wouldn’t happen. By adding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;PersistentKeepalive = 25
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to the Pi-hole [Peer] section of the client config file, the connection stays active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of you are itchin’ to try some Wireguard, I have found the tutorial at &lt;a href=&quot;https://serversideup.net/courses/gain-flexibility-and-increase-privacy-with-wireguard-vpn/&quot;&gt;ServerSide Up&lt;/a&gt; to be really helpful. That, and my old friend “trying stuff until it works”…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/try.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A parody of O'Reilly tech books. This cover says &amp;quot;Trying Stuff Until It Works&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EDIT: I got KDE Connect working! You just have to &lt;a href=&quot;https://userbase.kde.org/KDEConnect#Running_KDE_Connect_over_OpenVPN&quot;&gt;add devices by IP address&lt;/a&gt;! That is &lt;em&gt;so cool.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Wireguard" /><category term="FALD" /><summary type="html">I’ve been messin’ about with Wireguard and – after some hiccups – I have a small network of peers connected. I now have a couple laptops, a desktop, a phone, and a Raspberry Pi all networked, with the connection remaining persistent even as the mobile devices move across wi-fi networks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sudo Install Dark Mode</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/23/DarkMode.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sudo Install Dark Mode" /><published>2021-04-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/23/DarkMode</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/23/DarkMode.html">&lt;p&gt;Just a short post to note I have succumbed to the dark side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This whole pandemic has increased the amount of screen time we all endure, and I’ve increasingly recognized that dark modes feel better on my eyes. I started using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/darkreader/&quot;&gt;Dark Reader&lt;/a&gt; extension in Firefox to invert colors, and I set Mate to a dark theme on all my devices. After a few weeks of this, I realized that I liked the look of FOSS Academic when it was rendered using Dark Reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, using the magic of &lt;a href=&quot;https://sass-lang.com/&quot;&gt;SASS&lt;/a&gt; – I am loving SASS! – I changed a couple variables and BOOM! We’re doing FOSS after dark like were &lt;a href=&quot;https://latenightlinux.com/&quot;&gt;Joe, Félim, Graham, and Will&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see any issues with the styling, let me know in the comments. I still have to style the comments – I’ll get to it someday – but in the meantime, enjoy the dark.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="SASS" /><summary type="html">Just a short post to note I have succumbed to the dark side. This whole pandemic has increased the amount of screen time we all endure, and I’ve increasingly recognized that dark modes feel better on my eyes. I started using the Dark Reader extension in Firefox to invert colors, and I set Mate to a dark theme on all my devices. After a few weeks of this, I realized that I liked the look of FOSS Academic when it was rendered using Dark Reader. So, using the magic of SASS – I am loving SASS! – I changed a couple variables and BOOM! We’re doing FOSS after dark like were Joe, Félim, Graham, and Will. If you see any issues with the styling, let me know in the comments. I still have to style the comments – I’ll get to it someday – but in the meantime, enjoy the dark.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review of Zotero’s New PDF Annotation Features</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/02/ZoteroComments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review of Zotero’s New PDF Annotation Features" /><published>2021-04-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/02/ZoteroComments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/04/02/ZoteroComments.html">&lt;p&gt;Zotero recently announced two major new features: an internal PDF reader and tab-based navigation. These are scheduled to be a part of the Zotero 6 release later this year, but when I heard about them, &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/03/19/cuttingZotero.html&quot;&gt;I installed the Zotero 5 developer version&lt;/a&gt; to give them a whirl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zotero.png&quot; alt=&quot;Zotero's Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My quick take on the new features? They are now a key part of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-simple-pleasure-of-a-tab&quot;&gt;The Simple Pleasure of a Tab&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, opening a PDF in Zotero now opens its own native PDF reader with new annotation capabililties. I’ll get to that. But first, I did not realize how happy one tab could make me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PDF now opens in a new tab, where I can read it and take notes. What’s so cool about that is that I can easily go back to the main library and look at another source. I didn’t realize how often I did that, but it makes sense: the PDF I’m reading might make reference to another source, so I might want to go back to my library to see if I have it and cross-reference ideas. Or maybe I don’t have it – I can pop into Firefox and get it easily enough. All the while, the PDF tab is waiting there, patiently, for me to return to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can even open a second PDF in another tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zoterotab.png&quot; alt=&quot;Zotero's new tab interface&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Zotero's new tab interface&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feature is great, and it makes me want more: could I eventually open search folders in a new tab? Group libraries? If so – managing my library will get so much easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taking-notes&quot;&gt;Taking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for taking notes, the new PDF system offers a subtle, yet, invaluable capability: when I highlight text in the PDF, a button appears, allowing me to paste that highlighted section in a note. &lt;em&gt;And the pasted material doesn’t have carriage returns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years now, I would copy and paste PDF text into a Zotero note and have to go through and delete carriage returns. It could take so long that often I would just re-type the text rather than copy and paste it. This new setup will save me a great deal of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s more – the pasted material has a citation at the end, allowing me an option to “Go To Page.” Clicking on that citation does what it says – it jumps to the page of the PDF. In addition, I tested this feature without a PDF open: clicking on it opens the PDF associated with the note in a new tab and jumps to the page. That’s a fantastic feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zoteronote.png&quot; alt=&quot;Automatically generated citation in a Zotero note&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;An automatically generated citation in a Zotero note. Clicking on the citation allows you to go to that page in the PDF.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that would really make this feature sing is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I open a note and see a PDF citation, but the PDF in question is not open;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I click on the citation and click on”Go To Page”;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The PDF &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the corresponding note open in a new page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the new note feature, the PDF annotation system has PDF highlighting and sticky note capabilities. Both the highlights and sticky notes can easily be added to a separate note, as well. The sticky notes can be tagged. There’s a lot of new possibilities for library navigation now thanks to tagging sticky notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, it looks like my location in a PDF was synced across devices. When I opened a PDF I was reading on a laptop at home on a second computer at work, I was dropped in exactly where I left off reading on the laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, these new features are so rich, I feel as though I’m barely scratching the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bugs&quot;&gt;Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being beta software, I understand that there will be bugs. And there are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, the note window is pretty laggy. It often gets unresponsive while I’m typing. That can be frustrating – it reminds me of the early days when Zotero broke out of being a Firefox-only add-on and went “Standalone.” Zotero’s “snappiness” improved over time, and I imagine the same will happen here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, adding a chunk of text from the PDF to the note creates a new paragraph, rather than placing the text snippet on the current paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the cursor seems to get lost when navigating the note with the keypad, especially when the cursor traverses the citation field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features-lost&quot;&gt;Features Lost&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s unfortunately a feature lost in notes: the new note system does not allow for HTML editing, nor does it currently have the old highlighting. Looking at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.zotero.org/discussion/88064/available-in-preview-zotero-pdf-reader-and-new-note-editor&quot;&gt;comments in the Zotero forum&lt;/a&gt;, HTML editing is not coming back, since the notes won’t use HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I put in a feature request, asking for a return of the highlighting option, and it sounds like the Zotero crew will implement that feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overall-take&quot;&gt;Overall Take&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the lagginess in note-taking, for anyone interested in these features but in the middle of important projects, I do recommend waiting until the Zotero 6 release. I’m in between projects, so lagginess in note-taking is not a big concern for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if history is any guide, the good people at Zotero will optimize these features for speed, and then this will be the biggest shift in how we interact with Zotero since it went “Standalone.” I’m already using these changes and benefiting from them, and I’m quite certain other academics will, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Zotero" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">Zotero recently announced two major new features: an internal PDF reader and tab-based navigation. These are scheduled to be a part of the Zotero 6 release later this year, but when I heard about them, I installed the Zotero 5 developer version to give them a whirl. My quick take on the new features? They are now a key part of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RM Mess</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/28/RMMess.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RM Mess" /><published>2021-03-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/28/RMMess</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/28/RMMess.html">&lt;p&gt;I guess I have strange timing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just got done reading Sam Williams’s 2002 book &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/books/free-as-in-freedom-paperback-richard-stallman-s-crusade-for-free-software/9781449324643&quot;&gt;Free As In Freedom: Richard Stallman’s Crusade for Free Software&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; I started reading it about March 15 or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I thought of Stallman as largely in the background of the world of FOSS, since of course he resigned from the Free Software Foundation back in 2019. I knew that he was called out for some comments about Marvin Minsky and the Jeffrey Epstein case – comments that were, at best, tone-deaf and, at worst, apologies for the sexual predation of children. I also knew of increasing numbers of women who reported Stallman’s behavior made them uncomfortable and even unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/williams.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Cover of Williams's book Free as in Freedom, a biography of Richard Stallman&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Cover of Williams's book Free as in Freedom, a biography of Richard Stallman&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since I’m putting together Goal 2 – a book-length research project about FOSS – I figured that I need to engage with Stallman in some form, even if he was fading into the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Williams’s book caught my eye. As I read, I came across curious moments that may have appeared differently in 2002 than they do to this reader in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intention was to read the book and post a bit about it here, as I did with &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/12/06/Dreaming-In-Code.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dreaming In Code&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as part of my larger research project into FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it turns out that I also finished the book in time for RM Mess 2.0. So this is changing from a book review into a post that connect Williams’s now two-decades old biography with a current event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content warnings: this post discusses sexual assault, child exploitation, and harassment. You might want to skip it on those grounds. Moreover, if you’re tired of discussions of Stallman, you also might want to skip this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;curious-moment-1-on-freedom-for-children&quot;&gt;Curious Moment #1: On “freedom” for children&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Williams writes about Stallman’s childhood, including his refusal to obey his mother. RMS would, for example, refuse to come to dinner and opt to read a book instead. As RMS recalls,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If I wanted to read, and my mother told me to go to the kitchen and eat or go to sleep, I wasn’t going to listen. I saw no reason why I couldn’t read. No reason why she should be able to tell me what to do, period. Essentially, what I had read about, ideas such as democracy and individual freedom, I applied to myself. I didn’t see any reason to exclude children from these principles” (page 27).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams goes on to note RMS refused to write term papers for his English classes, because freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RMS is, shall we say, notoriously consistent. His most notorious comment to date is likely the Marvin Minsky case, where he argues that Minsky’s sex with one of the children Epstein was grooming does not rise to the level of sexual assault:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We can imagine many scenarios, but the most plausible scenario is that she presented herself to him as entirely willing. Assuming she was being coerced by Epstein, he would have had every reason to tell her to conceal that from most of his associates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve concluded from various examples of accusation inflation that it is absolutely wrong to use the term “sexual assault” in an accusation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://selamjie.medium.com/remove-richard-stallman-fec6ec210794&quot;&gt;Selam G’s original Medium blog post&lt;/a&gt; presents the full RMS email and dissects its language much better than I will here. I simply want to flag a thread of logic used by RMS: freedom, apparently, includes the freedom of children to want sex with adults. Minsky’s fault, here, was not doing enough investigative work to find out if the victim was “truly” willing or serving in sexual servitude (as part of Epstein’s “harem,” to use RMS’s term). RMS is consistent with his previous position – children should be free to read what they wish. Children should be seen as willing sex partners. It’s not assault if the child is willing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISCLAIMER&lt;/strong&gt;: Before I go any further I need to clarify. &lt;strong&gt;I do not condone the sexual exploitation of children.&lt;/strong&gt; Moreover, being who I am (a middle-aged, straight, white man with a stable career), I struggle to understand the experiences of others, and my comments here cannot be considered a last word by any means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows, then, is my own analysis of the logic of RMS and how his consistent position on children’s “freedom” is a position that ultimately supports the privilege of exploiting children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you may know I wrote a book about the Dark Web. Anyone who engages with the Dark Web has to deal with the stomach-turningly wretched specter of child expoitation. I studiously and carefully avoided child exploitation media during my research on the Dark Web, but I did engage in participant observation on Dark Web social media, and the topic often came up for debate. While there, I came across many people who would condemn child exploitation, but some who would apologize for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logic the child exploitation defenders used is exactly that of RMS: children should have rights!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This position is nothing more than an argument for guilt-free sexual objectification and exploitation of children. Basically, the apologists for Dark Web child exploitation argued that children should have the right to consent to sex with adults. Maybe children should have others rights, too, these people argued, but in the end it was always about reconceptualizing children as willing participants in adults’ sexual pleasure. That was basically the end goal of the argument for the freedom of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RMS’s trajectory here – the 2002 interview with Williams, comments in an email thread about Epstein and Minsky – replicate this telos almost exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is a major gap between RMS’s precocious childhood refusal to write term papers or eat his supper and his defense of Minsky. It is a gap that exposes so many problems with RMS’s “freedom.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partly, it’s a gap that includes a spectrum of freedom for children. Perhaps RMS has made calls for the rights of children beyond being their ability to refuse dinner or consent to sex with adults. Maybe he’s argued for voting rights, for example. But what has been documented, however, are his other, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rms-open-letter.github.io/appendix&quot;&gt;similar comments invoking of “willingness” and “consent”&lt;/a&gt; of children for sex. This echoes the logic found among the stunted political philosophies of Dark Web child exploitation advocates: “child rights” only means “adult rights to sexualize children.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the gap also includes the range of human experiences beyond those of a privileged man who went to private schools and was destined for Harvard. It’s perhaps easy for a man to conclude, based on his relatively privileged position, that his freedom as a boy to not go to bed should be analogous to the “freedom” of a young girl to go to bed with a much older adult. But that’s a leap in logic that completely ignores the whole host of human experiences – including class, race, gender, sexual identity – that complicates RMS’s radically reductive syllogism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could, for example, a young Black woman make an argument that she shouldn’t do her term papers? Can she still get into Harvard, as RMS did, despite not doing her school work? Can she live – sleep, eat, and presumably bathe – in safety in a computer lab at MIT, as RMS did?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should she make the same conclusions about freedom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Condemning RMS for the Minsky comments was absolutely correct, and I see no reason to relent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;curious-moments-2-affection-for-women-in-tech&quot;&gt;Curious Moment(s) #2: Affection for women in tech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than a single moment, this is more of a thread throughout Williams’s book, something impossible to miss post-2019. At one point, during lunch, Williams brings up something he’s observed RMS do with women he meets: he kisses their hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Yes, I do do that,” Stallman says. “I’ve found it’s a way of offering some affection that a lot of women will enjoy. It’s a chance to give some affection and to be appreciated for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, at another meal with RMS, RMS’s girlfriend, and Williams’s wife, Williams notes RMS engaging in more flirtation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although more flirtatious than I remembered – a flirtatiousness spoiled somewhat by the number of times Stallman’s eyes fixated on my wife’s chest – Stallman retained the same general level of prickliness (page 198).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, this comment about chest-fixation is excised from &lt;a href=&quot;https://sagitter.fedorapeople.org/faif-2.0.pdf&quot;&gt;Version 2.0 of the book&lt;/a&gt; – a version RMS himself edited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Minsky comments are presented as the proximate cause of RMS’s ouster, reports of RMS’s behavior towards women have contributed, as well. Selam G’s original post &lt;a href=&quot;https://selamjie.medium.com/remove-richard-stallman-appendix-a-a7e41e784f88&quot;&gt;led to women coming forward to explain the ways in which RMS made them uncomfortable or even unsafe at MIT&lt;/a&gt;. These women join women who made similar observations about their experiences at MIT – &lt;a href=&quot;https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~lazowska/mit/Images/Chapter2.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;back in 1983&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These women are citing their experiences at MIT or working in the tech sector. I myself work at a tech school. This week, I will teach a class on professional identity, and to prime the conversation, the class is reading Deneen Hatmaker’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1468-0432.2012.00589.x&quot;&gt;article on the problems women face in engineering&lt;/a&gt;. That article is a decade old. Its themes are the same as the MIT report from 4 decades ago. Despite the age of the article, or the revelations from that 1983 report, my students &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt; are saying the same thing about contemporary engineering and tech fields: they experience or have witnessed the lack of acceptance – and outright harassment – of women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The call for someone like RMS to step aside is justified precisely because his presence is clearly hindering the professional, intellectual, and personal development of so many people – including people who could be otherwise, you know, making free software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;curious-moment-3-rage&quot;&gt;Curious Moment #3: Rage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other curious moment isn’t so curious. It’s pure Stallman. Chapter 12 of Williams’s book, “A Brief Journey Through Hacker Hell,” documents RMS’s growing rage during a drive. RMS is driving a car (with Williams along for the ride) and a friend is in a car ahead of him, leading him through a town in Hawaii to a dinner appointment. Stallman is enraged because the other driver is taking a street instead of a highway. His rage grows, and grows, until, as Williams reports, he’s flailing against the steering wheel and screaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t really have to say much more than this – the #1 cited reason why people don’t like Stallman is his, as Williams puts it charitably, “prickliness.” Others might characterize it as belligerence and anger. The targets of his rage include enemies of freedom, but also fellow travelers and erstwhile friends – &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jskq3-lpQnE&quot;&gt;even people who invite him to speak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are moments when principles matter, and of course with things like licenses, words matter. I am too young to have witnessed the “Free Software” versus “Open Source” debates, but I do understand the distinction, and I understand calls for terms like “&lt;a href=&quot;https://communalsoftware.codeberg.page/&quot;&gt;Communal Software&lt;/a&gt;” as a means to clarify what software should be used for. I understand the politics of names and labels and theoretical concepts quite well, and how the free labor of people can not only provide valuable resources to those who wouldn’t afford them – like the FOSS I came to as a grad student – but also &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.facebook.com/&quot;&gt;provide a “competitive advantage” to massive corporations making our current digital dystopia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, raging at allies for making mistakes or saying something “wrong” is not building a movement. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://p1k3.com/2019/10/20/&quot;&gt;this post argues&lt;/a&gt;, the problems we face are bigger than interjecting a word and a slash into the conversation: “Free software isn’t whatever RMS says it is. Free software is what we make of it: We who want to be free, we who want others to be free.” So we need to move past RMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the call for RMS to step aside helps grow the movement, not hobble it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rm-mess-redux&quot;&gt;RM Mess, Redux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, I started reading Williams’s book &lt;em&gt;Free As In Freedom&lt;/em&gt; around March 15, 2021, a time when RMS was not involved in the FSF. I finished it on March 21. I planned on writing down notes and moving on to other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I woke up on the 22nd to &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.itsfoss.com/richard-stallman-is-back-at-fsf/&quot;&gt;the news that RMS is back&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now waking up every morning to news that people aren’t letting this slide. To date, I’ve seen condemnations of RMS’s return to the Free Software Foundation from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/03/statement-re-election-richard-stallman-fsf-board&quot;&gt;The Electronic Frontier Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mozilla/status/1374513444838199304?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;The Mozilla Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Tor Project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redhat.com/en/blog/red-hat-statement-about-richard-stallmans-return-free-software-foundation-board&quot;&gt;Red Hat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and more (having trouble keeping up).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably, these organizations (and, I imagine, this blog post) will be condemned as the fevered reactions of froth-mouthed “cancel mobs.” Indeed, Abhishek of It’s FOSS is using &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.itsfoss.com/richard-stallman-is-back-at-fsf/&quot;&gt;that language&lt;/a&gt;, as are commenters on Slashdot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wonder: how much evidence does anyone need before they are willing to accept that RMS is toxic and FOSS ought to move on? The evidence was there in Williams’s book two decades ago. The evidence was in the MIT CS report four decades ago. The evidence is piling up in front of you now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free as in freedom may require being freed of the “founder” of Freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-williamss-book&quot;&gt;On Williams’s Book&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lost in all this is any assessment of Williams’s book itself. It’s hard to judge &lt;em&gt;Free As In Freedom&lt;/em&gt; now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get the sense, reading it, that Williams was treading lightly, but in the end – especially in his epilogue – he started to get weary of his subject. I’m reading this from a strange perspective, but I can’t help but feel that Williams was trying to warn us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Stallman" /><category term="Free Software Foundation" /><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="FOSS Library" /><summary type="html">I guess I have strange timing. I just got done reading Sam Williams’s 2002 book Free As In Freedom: Richard Stallman’s Crusade for Free Software. I started reading it about March 15 or so. At the time, I thought of Stallman as largely in the background of the world of FOSS, since of course he resigned from the Free Software Foundation back in 2019. I knew that he was called out for some comments about Marvin Minsky and the Jeffrey Epstein case – comments that were, at best, tone-deaf and, at worst, apologies for the sexual predation of children. I also knew of increasing numbers of women who reported Stallman’s behavior made them uncomfortable and even unsafe. The Cover of Williams's book Free as in Freedom, a biography of Richard Stallman But since I’m putting together Goal 2 – a book-length research project about FOSS – I figured that I need to engage with Stallman in some form, even if he was fading into the background. So Williams’s book caught my eye. As I read, I came across curious moments that may have appeared differently in 2002 than they do to this reader in 2021. My intention was to read the book and post a bit about it here, as I did with Dreaming In Code as part of my larger research project into FOSS. But it turns out that I also finished the book in time for RM Mess 2.0. So this is changing from a book review into a post that connect Williams’s now two-decades old biography with a current event. Content warnings: this post discusses sexual assault, child exploitation, and harassment. You might want to skip it on those grounds. Moreover, if you’re tired of discussions of Stallman, you also might want to skip this post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cutting-Edge Zotero</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/19/cuttingZotero.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cutting-Edge Zotero" /><published>2021-03-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/19/cuttingZotero</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/19/cuttingZotero.html">&lt;p&gt;There’s exciting news on the Zotero front!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zotero just announced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/support/pdf_reader_preview&quot;&gt;preview of their new tab system, complete with a built-in PDF reader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone living the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream, this is huge news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zotero.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Zotero Logo&quot; title=&quot;The Zotero Logo&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Zotero logo is in the public domain.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They plan on releasing these features to the public in Version 6, but anyone itching to try it can use the development version of Zotero. This post will discuss how to install Zotero’s beta in Ubuntu Mate 18.04, though the approach should be similar for other Linux distros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;NB: Note, I would have found this sooner or later, but credit to Sean Lawson for alerting me!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-shut-zotero-down-and-back-it-up&quot;&gt;Step 1: Shut Zotero Down and Back It Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, make sure you’re not running Zotero. You can still have your browser open, however – the Zotero plugin will not affect this step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After shutting down, navigate to your Zotero profile folder. You should see a zotero.sqlite file. Because switching to the Zotero Beta could cause irreversible changes to this database, it’s best to back it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zoterosqlite.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the Zotero folder and zotero.sqlite file&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Zotero folder and zotero.sqlite file in Caja, Mate's file browser&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also backed up my installation of Zotero’s program files. Out of habit, I put them in a folder called “zoteroStandalone” in /.local/share. I simply created an archive of that folder and then deleted its contents. This is going to be my target for the Beta version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-get-the-beta&quot;&gt;Step 2: Get the Beta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then downloaded the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/support/dev_builds&quot;&gt;beta version of Zotero&lt;/a&gt; from their Dev Builds page. It’s in a compressed archive. I unpacked the archive in my now-empty /.local/share/zoteroStandalone folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zoterostandalonebackup.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of my .local/share folder with zoteroStandalone's directory in it&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;I store Zotero's executable files in /.local/share/zoteroStandalone&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, since I’ve been using Zotero for a while, I could then just launch Zotero from Mate’s Brisk menu and it was up and running. But, in case any of you want to know how to add Zotero to your menu, see the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-step-add-to-the-brisk-menu&quot;&gt;Optional Step: Add to the Brisk Menu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add Zotero to Mate’s Brisk menu, right-click on your menu and choose “Edit Menus.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to add Zotero to the “Office” subcategory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/briskmenu.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Mate's Brisk menu editor&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Brisk Menu editing starts with selecting where you want to add your menu items.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, select “Add Item.” You will see a menu like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/addingmenuitem.png&quot; alt=&quot;Adding an individual item to the Brisk menu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I stored Zotero in my /.local/share folder, the command path is /home/robert/.local/share/zoteroStandalone/zotero. To add an icon, I click on that springy Mario Brothers-looking icon and navigate to /home/robert/.local/share/zoteroStandalone/chrome/icons/default/default256.png.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I can launch Zotero from the menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve done all this and installed the Zotero beta, perhaps you’re as curious as I am about the new tabbed interface and PDF reader. To get those features, you have to opt-in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/betaoptin.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Zotero's general preferences menu&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Here is where you turn on magic things.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do that, go to Edit -&amp;gt; Preferences and use the General Tab. There’s an option about halfway down the menu to opt in. After a restart, Zotero will have the new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just did this process minutes ago, so expect a follow-up post on using the new features soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, if you’re looking for Zotero tricks and tips, &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/12/01/Zotero-Tips-and-Tricks.html&quot;&gt;check out this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Zotero" /><category term="FALD" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">There’s exciting news on the Zotero front! Zotero just announced a preview of their new tab system, complete with a built-in PDF reader. For anyone living the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream, this is huge news. The Zotero logo is in the public domain. They plan on releasing these features to the public in Version 6, but anyone itching to try it can use the development version of Zotero. This post will discuss how to install Zotero’s beta in Ubuntu Mate 18.04, though the approach should be similar for other Linux distros. NB: Note, I would have found this sooner or later, but credit to Sean Lawson for alerting me!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GDPR Compliance</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/11/GDPR.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GDPR Compliance" /><published>2021-03-11T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-03-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/11/GDPR</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/11/GDPR.html">&lt;p&gt;A quick note to any readers in GDPR regulated areas: I’m in the USA, and I don’t really do business in Europe. I don’t really do business anywhere, to be honest. Anyway, I also really respect privacy concerns. So, in the interest of transparency, I want to note that I use a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com&quot;&gt;Statcounter&lt;/a&gt; script to help track traffic to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the Javascript in the page source for the blog, and I’ve also &lt;a href=&quot;https://statcounter.com/p5832197/summary/?account_id=1462290&amp;amp;login_id=3&amp;amp;code=6a0a1540cdf3119c0be6e16464d0d1fe&amp;amp;guest_login=1&quot;&gt;made the stats public&lt;/a&gt; (marvel at my traffic!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;If you block Javascript, I not only don’t mind, nothing should change for you. The site will function just fine with Javascript blocked.&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit on March 20: Oops! I forgot about Javascript from Heroku, enabling &lt;a href=&quot;https://staticman.net/&quot;&gt;Staticman comments&lt;/a&gt;. I was reminded of this when I got a comment from a reader. If you block Javascript, you may have trouble commenting on posts. Those of you using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/noscript/&quot;&gt;Noscript extension for Firefox&lt;/a&gt; (an extension I really love, by the way), you can give temporary permission to a script from fossacademic.herokuapp.com if you want to comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My call is still out: if you have a better way to get basic traffic data for a Github.io-hosted static Jekyll blog, let me know in the comments or via Mastodon (@robertwgehl@scholar.social).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><summary type="html">A quick note to any readers in GDPR regulated areas: I’m in the USA, and I don’t really do business in Europe. I don’t really do business anywhere, to be honest. Anyway, I also really respect privacy concerns. So, in the interest of transparency, I want to note that I use a Statcounter script to help track traffic to this blog. You can see the Javascript in the page source for the blog, and I’ve also made the stats public (marvel at my traffic!). If you block Javascript, I not only don’t mind, nothing should change for you. The site will function just fine with Javascript blocked. Edit on March 20: Oops! I forgot about Javascript from Heroku, enabling Staticman comments. I was reminded of this when I got a comment from a reader. If you block Javascript, you may have trouble commenting on posts. Those of you using the Noscript extension for Firefox (an extension I really love, by the way), you can give temporary permission to a script from fossacademic.herokuapp.com if you want to comment. My call is still out: if you have a better way to get basic traffic data for a Github.io-hosted static Jekyll blog, let me know in the comments or via Mastodon (@robertwgehl@scholar.social).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PDF Hell</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/10/PDFhell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PDF Hell" /><published>2021-03-10T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-03-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/10/PDFhell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/03/10/PDFhell.html">&lt;p&gt;Why in the year 2021 is it hard to edit PDFs in Linux?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/acdchell.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;An image of a PDF of the musical notation to AC/DC's Highway to Hell.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;This is an image of a PDF of sheet music for AC/DC's &quot;Highway to Hell.&quot; Please enjoy the music, but don't ask me to edit the PDF.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don’t tell me to use Okular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don’t tell me to use LaTex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m barely keeping things together using Atril and pdfunite in the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I popped over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://itsfoss.com/pdf-editors-linux/&quot;&gt;It’s FOSS&lt;/a&gt; to see their list of top applications. When your list starts with LibreOffice Draw… I don’t know what to say. It gets worse from there, going to a bunch of commercial, proprietary solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now work for an organization that makes heavy use of PDF forms. I lament the lost hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Printing and scanning seems like the most efficient thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, feel free to tell me to switch to Windows.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><summary type="html">Why in the year 2021 is it hard to edit PDFs in Linux? This is an image of a PDF of sheet music for AC/DC's &quot;Highway to Hell.&quot; Please enjoy the music, but don't ask me to edit the PDF. Please don’t tell me to use Okular. Please don’t tell me to use LaTex. I’m barely keeping things together using Atril and pdfunite in the command line. I popped over to It’s FOSS to see their list of top applications. When your list starts with LibreOffice Draw… I don’t know what to say. It gets worse from there, going to a bunch of commercial, proprietary solutions. I now work for an organization that makes heavy use of PDF forms. I lament the lost hours. Printing and scanning seems like the most efficient thing to do. At this point, feel free to tell me to switch to Windows.</summary></entry></feed>