<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-03-15T14:18:02-04:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">AoIR Social’s Code of Conduct</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/03/15/AOIRsocialCOC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AoIR Social’s Code of Conduct" /><published>2023-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2023/03/15/AOIRsocialCOC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/03/15/AOIRsocialCOC.html">&lt;p&gt;So, as I noted in the &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/03/03/AOIR-social.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, AoIR.social is &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social&quot;&gt;live&lt;/a&gt;! It’s in beta testing, so to speak, as we bring on board moderators to learn the system before rolling out to the Association of Internet Researchers membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And moderators can’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1plPyJdXKIY&quot;&gt;mount up&lt;/a&gt; and moderate without a Code of Conduct. Along with Sarah Roberts and Aram Sinnreich, we drafted a COC based on the successful one found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.social&quot;&gt;scholar.social&lt;/a&gt;. We posted it to AoIR.social this week, and the moderators are weighing in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is meant to document this process, not just for posterity, but also for the Fediverse writ large. Below, I’ll post the full AoIR.social COC and document the feedback the moderators are giving it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-coc-so-far&quot;&gt;The COC, So Far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Click the little arrow to see the AoIR.social Code of Conduct, March 2023&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; Code of Conduct&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;NB: This is a DRAFT Code of Conduct, based in part on the Code of Conduct from scholar.social. As of March 2023, it is being reviewed by volunteer moderators.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an instance for current members of the Association of Internet Researchers. Real names and credentials are only recommended if you plan to use your account on this instance for networking purposes; they are absolutely not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Encouraged uses of AoIR.Social&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brag about your publications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share references and resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network with other AoIR members&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put it on the last slide of your conference presentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recruit participants for academic surveys—formal, IRB-approved ones or even informal ones (just make sure to use content warnings so that others can consent and don&apos;t get too obnoxious about it; see below for more about research on AoIR.social&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Satire and activism are welcome here, but they must make a good-faith effort to punch up. (&quot;Punching up&quot;: making jokes or criticism at the expense of those with more power, higher status or greater privilege.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are an AoIR member in good standing, and you are willing to engage with others respectfully, and you will respect our community&apos;s efforts to make this a safe space for queer, BIPOC, and other structurally disadvantaged people, you are absolutely welcome here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your AoIR membership has lapsed for longer than 2 years, you will be contacted about renewing your membership. If you choose not to renew, you will have 60 days to download your data. You may move your data to another Mastodon instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Introduce yourself!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After signing up, post a message to the Local Timeline telling us who you are, what your academic interests are, and helping us to get to know you better. We have set the administrative account to automatically boost public posts tagged with #introductions. (But if you abuse this by using it for anything else, we will close your account without warning.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Content Warnings (CW&apos;s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please add CW&apos;s (content warnings) that are accurate and descriptive enough to enable reader consent to the following types of posts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt;strong language,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   selfies,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   current events (includes: US or non-US, local, national, international, and should be applied regardless of whether sources are academic or non-partisan), high-conflict or otherwise exhausting issues of popular debate (e.g. climate change, GMO&apos;s, privacy issues, elections, etc.),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   mentions of death or violence,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   photographs or illustrations of insects, genitals, wounds (even if they come from a scientific source)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   references or links to Facebook/Twitter/other big tech companies,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   spoilers of popular and recent TV shows or other media, ASCII art (this one is important to ensure that someone using a screen reader doesn&apos;t have to listen to an attempt to read out a bunch of obscure symbols)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   stresses particular to academia such as grades, exams, thesis progress, academic job market prospects, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   anything else where another user might want to decide for themselves whether or when they want to interact with your post.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a setting in your preferences to open all posts with Content Warnings automatically, if you don&apos;t want to click through each one.
Image descriptions (alt-text)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an expectation of this instance that you add accurate descriptions to all images and video that you post to aid in accessibility. (A description like &quot;image.jpg&quot; that does not aid in accessibility would not meet this expectation.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you post an image of a screenshot of text, it is an expectation of this instance that you transcribe the text in the image description. Here’s a guide on how and why to supply alt-text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Unwelcome conduct on AoIR.Social&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following will result in: a warning from the admin or having offending posts deleted, possibly without prior notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt; Providing unsolicited advice to strangers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Inappropriate un-CW&apos;d posts on the Local Timeline (see above for CW policies)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Posts with un-described images or video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Shortened links, e.g. bit.ly, t.ly, tinyurl.com, goo.gl, ift.tt, lnkd.in, is.gd or t.co (These are considered malicious because link-shorteners track users without their consent and obscure the destination address, which also prevents users from being able to decide whether they want to visit the link beforehand)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Advertisement or apologia for cryptocurrencies, NFT&apos;s, or multi-level marketing schemes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Unrequested solicitations to join religious, political, or other ideologically-defined organizations&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exceptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DOI links (e.g. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.k959) are allowed but the post must accurately describe the title/author/journal to allow the reader to decide for themselves whether they would like to follow the link. (In cases of very long titles, you may truncate it, and in cases of long author lists, &quot;First-Author et al&quot; will do.) Posts with DOI links where the target of the link is not described, or not described sufficiently, may be deleted without warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Things that will get your account closed, possibly without warning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;li&gt;   Racism, sexism, homophobia, transphobia, casteism, able-ism, etc. (will result in a permanent ban, you may not receive a prior warning)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Serious dishonesty that is hurtful to others (e.g. falsely representing oneself as a member of a minority; services offering to write academic papers to help students cheat; vaccine denialism; predatory conferences or journals; overt pseudoscience such as flat-earther-ism etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Anything that could be described as &quot;spam&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Impersonating other people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Harassment of any kind, including condemnations of individuals or institutions based on location, nationality, class, caste, religion, ethnicity, age, gender, or sexual identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   No bots and no &quot;institutional&quot; accounts operated by non-members please; AoIR.social is for people. The obvious exception is that the AoIR organization itself will post official communications here. Any official communications will be marked as such.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Accounts that automatically repeat a Twitter account, RSS feed, etc. must post to AoIR.social as Unlisted, not Public&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Regarding attempts to abuse these anti-abuse tools and policies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not attempt to weaponize our Community Standards or anti-abuse tools/policies against marginalized groups such as people of colour, women or queer people. Users of AoIR.social are expected to have the literacy to understand that &quot;reverse discrimination&quot; is not real, and so attempts to re-centre discussions of marginalized people around the feelings of the privileged will be taken as manipulative behaviour undertaken deliberately in bad-faith. (E.g. white people should not demand that people of colour put CW&apos;s on every discussion of race). Furthermore, the abuse of content moderation tools for targeted efforts to silence, smear, or otherwise harass any individual account holder, for any reason, will not be tolerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Use of AoIR.Social for research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers who wish to study AoIR.social or our users by collecting data using the API or through any other means that does not involve an &quot;opt-in&quot; from individual users are required to submit their protocol, analysis plan and all relevant ethics approval documentation from their institutional review board or departmental internal review documentation by email to the AoIR Fediverse admin account. You may also be required to submit code you plan to execute so that it can be tested to ensure it does not degrade the quality of service to other users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not apply to, e.g. surveys circulated on AoIR.social that individual users can consent to participating in. This does apply to database scraping software, or any means of recording user activity where our users might be surprised that they were included afterward, because they were not given a chance to consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AoIR is well known for being the leading organization developing ethical online research. Ethical research on this instance (and much of the fediverse) should be sensitive to the privacy expectations of its members. Many people came to the fediverse in order to avoid being included in unethical social media research, and so we place a higher value on conducting research on human subjects with informed consent than most other social media, in order to maintain high ethical standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the admin&apos;s discretion, you may be asked to submit your research protocol, and the institution that is providing ethical review, even in the case that it is an opt-in survey. Failure to disclose your research plan may result in closure of your account, or having your network banned from our service.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-feedback-so-far&quot;&gt;The Feedback, So Far&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;NB: I will provide attribution when I have the permission of the author. I’ll also add more as I observe it.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mission statement: we should include a bit more about what this server is about. Why have we set it up? What is it for?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Similarly, another member noted that we should be clearer that socializing – in addition to being professional – is encouraged (indeed, that the very personal/professional divide in the academy needs to be troubled)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explanation for each section: for example, a bit more explaining why we ask for CWs. This would be good for new Mastodon members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moderation commitments: how many moderators do we have? What’s the typical turnaround for responding to issues?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bit more clarity about what we mean about no crypto-shilling, especially when we have scholars who &lt;em&gt;study&lt;/em&gt; cryptcurrencies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bit of clarity about sexual expression, e.g., discussions of sex work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- That&apos;s it, so far, but I expect our moderators to add more. The current COC is a draft, and even after it&apos;s gone through this round of revision, I would consider it a living document. --&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Association of Internet Researchers" /><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="goal 1" /><summary type="html">So, as I noted in the last post, AoIR.social is live! It’s in beta testing, so to speak, as we bring on board moderators to learn the system before rolling out to the Association of Internet Researchers membership. And moderators can’t mount up and moderate without a Code of Conduct. Along with Sarah Roberts and Aram Sinnreich, we drafted a COC based on the successful one found at scholar.social. We posted it to AoIR.social this week, and the moderators are weighing in. This post is meant to document this process, not just for posterity, but also for the Fediverse writ large. Below, I’ll post the full AoIR.social COC and document the feedback the moderators are giving it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AOIR.social!</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/03/03/AOIR-social.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AOIR.social!" /><published>2023-03-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2023/03/03/AOIR%20social</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/03/03/AOIR-social.html">&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/12/11/AOIR-social.html&quot;&gt;wrote about the possibility of the Association on Internet Researchers running their own Mastodon instance&lt;/a&gt;. I discussed the major concerns the organization had about running such an instance, and the direction the project is heading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/aoir.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Association of Internet Researchers Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to announce that AOIR.social is going to happen. In fact, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social&quot;&gt;it’s live right now&lt;/a&gt;, but we’re not actively signing up AOIR members just yet. First, we’re going to let our volunteer moderators join to learn the tooling (and the tooting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have to do some work on preemptively blocking instances that don’t share our values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and we have to finalize our Code of Conduct (both for the Mastodon instance and for the organization as a whole).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to investigate signing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://joinmastodon.org/covenant&quot;&gt;Mastodon Server Covenant&lt;/a&gt;. (I want this to be a respectable part of the fediverse, after all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s probably more that I’m not thinking about, but in any case… it’s happening, people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, lots to do! Stay tuned, AOIRfriends!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Association of Internet Researchers" /><category term="Mastodon" /><summary type="html">A few months ago, I wrote about the possibility of the Association on Internet Researchers running their own Mastodon instance. I discussed the major concerns the organization had about running such an instance, and the direction the project is heading. I’m excited to announce that AOIR.social is going to happen. In fact, it’s live right now, but we’re not actively signing up AOIR members just yet. First, we’re going to let our volunteer moderators join to learn the tooling (and the tooting). And I have to do some work on preemptively blocking instances that don’t share our values. Oh, and we have to finalize our Code of Conduct (both for the Mastodon instance and for the organization as a whole). And I want to investigate signing the Mastodon Server Covenant. (I want this to be a respectable part of the fediverse, after all). There’s probably more that I’m not thinking about, but in any case… it’s happening, people! So, lots to do! Stay tuned, AOIRfriends!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bumps, Slumps and the Killer Hype Cycle</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bumps, Slumps and the Killer Hype Cycle" /><published>2023-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump.html">&lt;p&gt;Ok, you all probably remember last fall, when the Muskening happened. When Mastodon saw a massive influx of new members. When Mastodon admins were struggling to keep up with the influx but ultimately showed that the network can, in fact, scale up. It was, in my view, the biggest stress on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/&quot;&gt;ActivityPub&lt;/a&gt; protocol – and ActivityPub kicked ass. Millions of people signed up for Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the titular Mastodon “bump.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’ve published academic articles on Mastodon, during that Eternal Muskvember, I was approached by a lot of journalists (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/twitter-users-mastodon-meltdown/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rnz.co.nz/national/programmes/ninetonoon/audio/2018866818/twitter-users-seek-alternative-to-musk-run-platform&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketplace.org/shows/make-me-smart/unpacking-mastodon/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for example) to talk about Mastodon, answering questions ranging from “what is it?” to “will it replace Twitter?” It was an exciting and sometimes exasperating time. I basically told myself, “Self, this sort of media attention is rare. Enjoy it, but know that it won’t last.” And indeed, a few weeks later, the story died down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also told myself to expect the inevitable follow-up. That’s what I’m writing about here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many readers of this blog are likely aware, after the new year, Mastodon’s active user base dropped off. As with every wave of social media movement from platform to platform, some percentage of people just don’t stick with the new site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s the titular Mastodon “slump.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, I got an interview request from WIRED’s Amanda Hoover, who was working on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/the-mastodon-bump-is-now-a-slump/amp&quot;&gt;a story&lt;/a&gt; about how Mastodon’s drop in active users signaled that it had failed in its mission to replace Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, before I go any further I will say Hoover’s reporting on Mastodon has been excellent. She asks great questions, and she does more than just interview Eugen Rochko – she talks to instance admins, lawyers, and academics like myself. And, in fact, the article I’m going to critique is quite good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am going to use her latest WIRED article to illustrate an all-too-common trope in reporting on alternative social media: it’s what I call “The Killer Hype Cycle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-killer-hype-cycle&quot;&gt;The Killer Hype Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here’s the Killer Hype Cycle, as a couple colleagues and I describe it in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/objects/hc:29856/datastreams/CONTENT/content&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Media and Society&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Killer Hype Cycles are often seen in tech reporting on alternatives to mainstream social media platforms, such as Facebook and Twitter. The Cycle goes like this: first, a journalist notices a fledgling alternative social media system. Looking for a click-worthy angle, the journalist declares it the next ‘Facebook Killer’ or ‘Twitter
Killer,’ arguing that within months, the corporate social media giant will be ‘killed’ because its users will leave en masse for the new alternative. Later, when someone notices that Facebook or Twitter is still active despite the presence of the ‘Killer,’ another journalist (or even the original journalist) will declare the alternative a ‘failure’ or simply ‘dead,’ mainly because it did not attract hundreds of millions of new users in a matter of weeks. The cycle appears to end—that is, until another alternative is noticed by a tech reporter, and the cycle is repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;em&gt;New Media and Society&lt;/em&gt; article provides citations, but here I’ll quickly cover some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2010, when diaspora* was getting attention, journalists declared it to be a “Facebook killer,” and soon after, declared it to be a failure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2014, ello was dubbed a Facebook killer, and then weeks later it was called a failure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And in 2017, the same happened to… Mastodon, which was dubbed a “Twitter Killer” only to be written off for dead that same year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see the same thing over the past few months with Mastodon coverage. In the fall, journalists asked me if Mastodon will replace Twitter. My typical reply was something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve seen massive discontent over corporate social media many times (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2014/06/everything-we-know-about-facebooks-secret-mood-manipulation-experiment/373648/&quot;&gt;Emotional Contagion&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/news/series/cambridge-analytica-files&quot;&gt;Cambridge Analytica&lt;/a&gt;) and somehow people keep using Facebook and Twitter et al. So, probably not, although if Twitter went away, I’d be fine with it. Regardless, what Mastodon and its kin offer is an alternative to corporate social media for those of us concerned about surveillance, disinformation, and harassment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, no matter what I said, the very emphasis on “will it replace Twitter?” is not too far off of “will it kill Twitter?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to last week, and WIRED’s Hoover asked me if I was concerned about the dropoff in Mastodon active users. I didn’t write down my exact reply, but I said something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No, because these waves come and go, and while some percentage of new users might stop using Mastodon, Mastodon’s overall membership has gone up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also stressed the fact that the real lesson of the Fall of 2022 was that ActivityPub succeeded in scaling up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/the-mastodon-bump-is-now-a-slump/&quot;&gt;resulting article&lt;/a&gt; is actually quite good. I commend Hoover for the article because it covered things like emerging questions about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2022/12/user-generated-content-and-fediverse-legal-primer&quot;&gt;legal liability&lt;/a&gt; and the fact that the network did scale and because she interviewed a Mastodon admin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it does however imply that Mastodon is somehow failing because of the “slump.” It implies that Mastodon is dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know this because just a day after it came out, &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; reporter called to ask about Mastodon’s impending demise – and that reporter cited Hoover’s WIRED article.
That second reporter was working on a story about… new and emerging alternatives to corporate social media. And they were starting with the premise that Mastodon failed and it was time to find something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, that reporter was looking for the next Killer Hype Cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-do-about-this-trope&quot;&gt;What to do about this trope?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d recommend to tech journalists covering alternative social media to push past the “Killer” trope and consider each alternative on its own terms, rather than strictly in opposition to a corporate counterpart. Yes, some comparison is inevitable – after all, we understand “alternative” in relation to a “mainstream.” But these are not 1:1 replacements – they have their own logics and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, part of the appeal of the alternatives is the refusal of the growth logics of corporate social media. Mastodon admins, for example, don’t really want to run instances on the scale of Twitter. They want small instances that are more easily moderated at a human scale. Because of this, growth of Mastodon as a whole depends on the establishment of many new instances, which takes time and effort. As I say over and over, it’s not a matter of signing up at a central site, like Twitter.com. This is purposeful building of democratic social media, and growth is not always the best thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reporting in this space needs to focus on these nuances and eliminate the oversimplification “growth always equals good.” That’s hard to do when we’re conditioned by 20 years of corporate, venture capital, Silicon Valley thinking, but there is a world beyond the Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the rest of us in Mastodon and across the fediverse, I probably don’t need to say this, but I will, anyway: don’t be fazed. Keep on doing what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La lucha sigue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">Ok, you all probably remember last fall, when the Muskening happened. When Mastodon saw a massive influx of new members. When Mastodon admins were struggling to keep up with the influx but ultimately showed that the network can, in fact, scale up. It was, in my view, the biggest stress on the ActivityPub protocol – and ActivityPub kicked ass. Millions of people signed up for Mastodon. That’s the titular Mastodon “bump.” Since I’ve published academic articles on Mastodon, during that Eternal Muskvember, I was approached by a lot of journalists (here, here, and here, for example) to talk about Mastodon, answering questions ranging from “what is it?” to “will it replace Twitter?” It was an exciting and sometimes exasperating time. I basically told myself, “Self, this sort of media attention is rare. Enjoy it, but know that it won’t last.” And indeed, a few weeks later, the story died down. I also told myself to expect the inevitable follow-up. That’s what I’m writing about here. As many readers of this blog are likely aware, after the new year, Mastodon’s active user base dropped off. As with every wave of social media movement from platform to platform, some percentage of people just don’t stick with the new site. There’s the titular Mastodon “slump.” Last week, I got an interview request from WIRED’s Amanda Hoover, who was working on a story about how Mastodon’s drop in active users signaled that it had failed in its mission to replace Twitter. Now, before I go any further I will say Hoover’s reporting on Mastodon has been excellent. She asks great questions, and she does more than just interview Eugen Rochko – she talks to instance admins, lawyers, and academics like myself. And, in fact, the article I’m going to critique is quite good. But I am going to use her latest WIRED article to illustrate an all-too-common trope in reporting on alternative social media: it’s what I call “The Killer Hype Cycle.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reading the Minutes of the Social Web Working Group, part 1</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/01/20/ActivityPub1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reading the Minutes of the Social Web Working Group, part 1" /><published>2023-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2023/01/20/ActivityPub1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/01/20/ActivityPub1.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NB: This is the first in a series of posts where I will share my notes on my readings of the minutes of the Social Web Working Group. Future posts to come.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As readers of the blog know by now, Goal 2 of the blog is &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/01/06/Goal2.html&quot;&gt;to document my writing of my next book&lt;/a&gt;, which I’m tentatively titling &lt;em&gt;Move Slowly and Build Bridges: Mastodon and the Struggle for Ethical Alternative Social Media&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end, I have been studying the workings of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/Social/WG&quot;&gt;Social Web Working Group&lt;/a&gt; (SocialWG), a W3C standards group which ran from 2014 through 2017 and ultimately produced, among other things, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/&quot;&gt;ActivityPub&lt;/a&gt;, the protocol that underpins much of the fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I figure I cannot tell any stories about Mastodon without understanding the production of ActivityPub. Looking through the SocialWG meetings, it’s quite clear that Mastodon and ActivityPub’s histories are deeply intertwined. Mastodon adopted ActivityPub it prior to AP being a Candidate Recommendation (the penultimate stage in the W3C recommendation process). Mastodon is also a key reason why the Social Web Working Group got a 6 month extension for their work in 2017 – see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2017-06-27-minutes&quot;&gt;this meeting&lt;/a&gt;. They even set up a Mastodon instance (w3c.social) to show W3C members that software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will discuss the early period of the SocialWG (circa 2014 through 2015). I’ll follow up later with more posts and notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, I need to offer a couple caveats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I didn’t participate in the group. Instead, I’m basing much of this off the meeting minutes, as well as blog posts by SocialWG members, and to a lesser extent on informal discussions and formal interviews with some of the members. It’s possible – likely, even – that I will get details wrong, not simply because I wasn’t there, but also because this poor English major was not trained in computer science. The notes here are things that caught my eye. If you have corrections or critiques of my interpretation, please do share in the comments! And, as I talk to more people, I might change my interpretations, as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, my focus is predominantly going to be on ActivityPub. However, the SocialWG produced quite a few other standards. That said, in focusing on the group’s history, I should cover a lot of ground, even with my emphasis on ActivityPub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, the meeting minutes are not verbatim transcripts (which makes sense – meeting minutes almost never are). They were taken by volunteers from among the SocialWG, who were trying to transcribe phone conversations while an IRC chat was going. So, any quotes I include here should not be taken as verbatim statements. In addition, given the sheer number of times I read statements such as “who’s speaking now?” and “I can hear weird noises” – these were largely telephone conferences, after all – I would take any attributions here with a major grain of salt, as well. Take, for example, the following exchange from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-02-17-minutes&quot;&gt;this meeting&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;harry: so a cheapo understanding of heirarchy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… am confused when I read the spec&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;scribe: was that harry or dret ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;sorry if I set the wrong one&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;dret: me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice in this example statements are attributed to harry when they were actually said by dret. So, I will tend to cite statements and ideas with minimal attribution unless I am 99% certain the statement can be attributed to the person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part--getting-started-getting-organized-2014-to-end-of-2015&quot;&gt;Part : Getting Started, Getting Organized (2014 to end of 2015)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-charter&quot;&gt;The Charter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase of a Working Group at the W3C is a Charter, and the Social Web Working Group is no exception. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2013/socialweb/social-wg-charter.html&quot;&gt;Their charter&lt;/a&gt; stated&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Social Web Working Group will create &lt;strong&gt;Recommendation Track&lt;/strong&gt; deliverables that standardize a common JSON-based syntax for social data, a client-side API, and a Web protocol for federating social information such as status updates.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, there are three goals (although one was actually optional, more on that in a bit):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A social syntax (what would ultimately become &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-core/&quot;&gt;Activity Streams 2.0&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A client API&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A federation protocol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the Charter connected the SocialWG to another group, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2013/socialweb/social-ig-charter.html&quot;&gt;Social Interest Group&lt;/a&gt;. As we’ll see in posts to come, the Social Interest Group played a key role by creating “user stories” that capture online social activities. Those stories would help structure the specifications the SocialWG would ultimately produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;organizational-issues&quot;&gt;Organizational Issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Charter, the Group began meeting, and the early meetings are marked by seemingly mundane and yet important issues, such as how teleconferencing works, how to take and post minutes, and when and where to meet in person. Those early meetings were about setting workflows and meeting schedules, including how the Draft and Recommendation process works at the W3C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These meetings also established/emphasized rules about who is allowed to participate in a Working Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-caught-my-eye&quot;&gt;What Caught My Eye&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so the first thing that I found fascinating was a desire for and fear of established social media corporations (specifically, Twitter, Google, Facebook). The SocialWG stated again and again that they wanted Facebook or Twitter to participate – here is but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-09-29-minutes&quot;&gt;one example&lt;/a&gt; of such a discussion –  but there is also a strong fear of the work being appropriated or buried. Two things are often mentioned as cautionary tales: Schema.org and the Open Web Foundation. Obviously, the desire for and fear of corporate social media involvement relates to who can or should participate. And the lack of involvement from those corporations is really important for this history, I would think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also interesting to note that federation was bracketed off at this point. This is consistent with the Charter, which contemplated that Federation would be an optional deliverable: “Note that the Working Group may not develop the Federation Protocol into a Recommendation and it may become a Working Group Note.” Given that, from my perspective, the most important product of this group was the ActivityPub federation protocol, it’s remarkable that it almost didn’t get done because it was seen as optional. More on that in posts to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that caught my eye is that implementation and real-world examples were emphasized right away. The W3C specification process requires at least two implementations of every feature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Arnaud: Would like to remind people that as a part of the W3C spec track, there will be a point at which we have a call for implementations, at which point we need 2 implementations of &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; feature to move forward &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2014-09-30-minutes&quot;&gt;(2014-09-30 meeting)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be very important in terms of the eventual ActivityPub and Mastodon. The first time we see much emphasis on implementation would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-10-06-minutes&quot;&gt;when ActivityStreams 2.0 is set to move to Candidate Recommendation&lt;/a&gt; in late 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fascinating aspect is that roughly a year into its existence, the SocialWG members would have a pretty heated debate about how to communicate. I tagged this in Zotero as “org comm,” short for “organizational communication,” or how an organization is constituted through its communicative practices. So, even though much time was spent early on in 2014 on how the group would get things done, communication conflicts emerged later on, with discussions about overloads in terms of channels and even flare-ups about who gets to speak when.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final note, but an important one. There are three distinct “camps” in the SocialWG:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An academic-focused group centered on SoLiD and semantic markup;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People with previous federation experience, such as Pump.io folks,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and IndieWeb, a group of folks who put the webpage at the center of everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll say more about these groups and their competing visions in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="ActivityPub" /><summary type="html">NB: This is the first in a series of posts where I will share my notes on my readings of the minutes of the Social Web Working Group. Future posts to come. As readers of the blog know by now, Goal 2 of the blog is to document my writing of my next book, which I’m tentatively titling Move Slowly and Build Bridges: Mastodon and the Struggle for Ethical Alternative Social Media. To that end, I have been studying the workings of the Social Web Working Group (SocialWG), a W3C standards group which ran from 2014 through 2017 and ultimately produced, among other things, ActivityPub, the protocol that underpins much of the fediverse. I figure I cannot tell any stories about Mastodon without understanding the production of ActivityPub. Looking through the SocialWG meetings, it’s quite clear that Mastodon and ActivityPub’s histories are deeply intertwined. Mastodon adopted ActivityPub it prior to AP being a Candidate Recommendation (the penultimate stage in the W3C recommendation process). Mastodon is also a key reason why the Social Web Working Group got a 6 month extension for their work in 2017 – see this meeting. They even set up a Mastodon instance (w3c.social) to show W3C members that software. This post will discuss the early period of the SocialWG (circa 2014 through 2015). I’ll follow up later with more posts and notes. Importantly, I need to offer a couple caveats. First, I didn’t participate in the group. Instead, I’m basing much of this off the meeting minutes, as well as blog posts by SocialWG members, and to a lesser extent on informal discussions and formal interviews with some of the members. It’s possible – likely, even – that I will get details wrong, not simply because I wasn’t there, but also because this poor English major was not trained in computer science. The notes here are things that caught my eye. If you have corrections or critiques of my interpretation, please do share in the comments! And, as I talk to more people, I might change my interpretations, as well. Second, my focus is predominantly going to be on ActivityPub. However, the SocialWG produced quite a few other standards. That said, in focusing on the group’s history, I should cover a lot of ground, even with my emphasis on ActivityPub. Third, the meeting minutes are not verbatim transcripts (which makes sense – meeting minutes almost never are). They were taken by volunteers from among the SocialWG, who were trying to transcribe phone conversations while an IRC chat was going. So, any quotes I include here should not be taken as verbatim statements. In addition, given the sheer number of times I read statements such as “who’s speaking now?” and “I can hear weird noises” – these were largely telephone conferences, after all – I would take any attributions here with a major grain of salt, as well. Take, for example, the following exchange from this meeting: harry: so a cheapo understanding of heirarchy … am confused when I read the spec scribe: was that harry or dret ? sorry if I set the wrong one dret: me Notice in this example statements are attributed to harry when they were actually said by dret. So, I will tend to cite statements and ideas with minimal attribution unless I am 99% certain the statement can be attributed to the person. Let’s dive in!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Academic Year in Review 2022</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/01/03/FOSSacademicYIR-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Academic Year in Review 2022" /><published>2023-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2023/01/03/FOSSacademicYIR%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2023/01/03/FOSSacademicYIR-copy.html">&lt;p&gt;I don’t often do “Year in Review” posts, but… this past year has been something else. I’ve started a new job in a new country, I published another book, and my area of research (alternative social media) got a lot of media attention. In addition, I’ve formulated a new book project – and in doing so, I almost regret the name of this blog! But don’t worry: the &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/11/27/introduction.html&quot;&gt;FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream&lt;/a&gt; is still alive, even if it is a bit more self-reflexive about what FOSS means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll do this post in roughly chronological order. Buckle up: it’s a long post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-new-book-social-engineering&quot;&gt;A New Book: Social Engineering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 2022 started out as ‘21 ended: I was the F. Jay Taylor Endowed Research Chair of Communication at Louisiana Tech. And at the start of 2022, I was eagerly awaiting the physical appearance of my third book. Co-authored with my good friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seanlawson.net/&quot;&gt;Sean Lawson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262543453/&quot;&gt;Social Engineering: How Crowdmasters, Phreaks, Hackers, and Trolls Created a New Form of Manipulative Communication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; tackles disinformation in the digital age. Sean and I drew on two histories of disinformation to tell the tale. First, there’s early 20th century propaganda (think of the work of Doris Fleischman, Edward Bernays, and Ivy Lee). Second, there’s mid-century phone and computer hacking (think of Suzy Thunder and Kevin Mitnick). We argue that today’s manipulation (think Russian election interference or deceptive marketing) is a mix of old-school propaganda and newer, interpersonal hacking. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2022/03/26/NewBookOldBook.html&quot;&gt;Here’s a longer summary if you’re interested&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about that book, though. You’re probably wondering, “What software did you use to write it?” As I’ve written about here on the blog, Sean and I used a lot of FOSS to put this work together, including &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/10/05/deepdivezotero.html&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; and Nextcloud. I was able to do much of my work at LaTech using Linux and LibreOffice, among other tools. So the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream was in full effect for the composition of &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering.&lt;/em&gt; And! MIT Press also &lt;a href=&quot;https://direct.mit.edu/books/oa-monograph/5281/Social-EngineeringHow-Crowdmasters-Phreaks-Hackers&quot;&gt;generously made the book Open Access&lt;/a&gt;, so open source is a theme here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the book is doing well. Sean and I presented it to various audiences, including Town Hall Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-next-book-move-slowly-and-build-bridges&quot;&gt;The Next Book: &lt;em&gt;Move Slowly and Build Bridges&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have found myself doing when one book is wrapping up, I start looking around for the next project. And as &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/em&gt; was nearing completion, I realized I already had a project: alternative social media. After all, I started this very blog with the vague idea of writing a book about FOSS. And many alternative social media projects are FOSS projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such FOSS alternative in particular I had been watching for a few years: Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been studying alternative social media for many years – in fact, my dissertation and &lt;a href=&quot;https://tupress.temple.edu/books/reverse-engineering-social-media&quot;&gt;first book&lt;/a&gt; concluded with a call for alternatives, and I’ve been publishing about them ever since. At this point, early in 2022, it felt like a lonely area of study (although read on for more about this!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I started conceptualizing a book about Mastodon. And the more I looked at Mastodon, the more I learned how FOSS is much, much more complex than I had even realized. For example, how do we understand the fact that Mastodon was built predominantly by queer and trans folks, but that it was appropriated by white supremacists (in the form of Gab.com)? In other words, how do we understand the “freedom” in FOSS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lightning bolt struck me when I came across the work of &lt;a href=&quot;https://where.coraline.codes/&quot;&gt;Coraline Ada Ehmke&lt;/a&gt;. I started studying her work on “&lt;a href=&quot;https://ethicalsource.dev/&quot;&gt;Ethical Source Software&lt;/a&gt;,” which is essentially FOSS for collective good. Rather than the absolute freedom of Freedom 0 – including the freedom to use software for destructive or unjust purposes – Ethical Source is about licensing software for use by anyone, but only for just purposes. It’s a radical project – radical in the best sense, in that it is getting to the root of problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the privilege of interviewing Ehmke to learn more. And all of it makes me wish I titled this blog something other than “fossacademic.tech”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also had the privilege of representing the Organization for Ethical Source at a Mastodon/Hometown workshop in Rotterdam in May of 2022. Conducted by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://varia.zone/en/&quot;&gt;Varia Collective&lt;/a&gt; (the good folks behind &lt;a href=&quot;https://post.lurk.org/about&quot;&gt;post.lurk.org&lt;/a&gt;), I participated in a masterclass in digital community building and moderation. I also talked to folks about the contradictions of FOSS – not only the issues of Freedom 0, but also issues around the devaluing of non-technical contributions and environmental impacts of digital media. I wrote a report for the OES on whether or not that organization should start its own Mastodon instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this has influenced my work on Mastodon. I worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://cla.purdue.edu/directory/profiles/diana-zulli.html&quot;&gt;Diana Zulli&lt;/a&gt;, a political communication scholar at Purdue, to think about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400&quot;&gt;non-centralized platform governance&lt;/a&gt;, ethics, and content moderation on Mastodon. The resulting paper is called “The Digital Covenant” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400&quot;&gt;published version&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:49433/&quot;&gt;open access version&lt;/a&gt;). This work helped me think through &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of the questions people like Ehmke are raising, but certainly not all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I started &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html&quot;&gt;interviewing Mastodon folks&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about its history, from its pre-cursors to ActivityPub to Playvicious to the prenent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What all this showed me is that things are even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; complicated! But also that there is a book in all this. It should be a fascinating book – I’ve tentatively titled it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Move Slowly and Build Bridges: Mastodon and the Struggle for Ethical Social Media.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And do not despair, fediverse friends: I will talk about the rest of the fediverse, too. I just need a main ‘character’ to do it, and Mastodon is it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-new-job-in-a-new-country&quot;&gt;A New Job in a New Country&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if starting a new book project wasn’t enough, I started a new job in a new country. In September, I moved North to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorku.ca/&quot;&gt;York University&lt;/a&gt; in Toronto! I am so excited to be in Toronto, in Canada, and at York. Why? First, Toronto is not far from where I grew up in Michigan, and of course it’s an exciting city. Second, I’ve wanted to get to Canada for years now, especially since doing a Fulbright in Calgary. Third, I’ve admired York University – the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorku.ca/laps/comn/&quot;&gt;Department of Communication and Media Studies&lt;/a&gt; in particular – for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enough of that,” I hear you say. “Can you live the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream at York?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is: yes, but it’s a bit harder than other places I’ve been. It’s a Microsoft shop, with Outlook and Teams running amok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’m writing this post on a Linux box I was able to purchase through York with my startup funds. And I’ve been able to route emails and calendars from Outlook to Thunderbird. I can of course edit documents with LibreOffice – the compatibility with Word is solid. I just have to use Teams (and Zoom) on occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can live with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-research-gets-noticed&quot;&gt;My Research Gets Noticed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so all of that takes me through the early part of the year (the &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/em&gt; book, starting a new book on Mastodon) and the middle bit (moving to York). What I would have liked is a quiet end to the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rumblings of a noisy end to 2022 started back in April, when a fellow named Musk offered to buy Twitter. That started a minor wave of folks who either started new Mastodon/fediverse accounts or revived dormant ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that wasn’t the big wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late October, 2022: Musk completes the purchase. And the waves start coming. And they kept coming after Musk made weird choice after weird choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I have published work on Mastodon and other alternative social media, I had the privilege of talking to a lot of reporters at this time. I was interviewed about Musk, Twitter, and Mastodon by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/listen/live-radio/1-102-radio-noon-quebec/clip/15956335-why-care-happens-twitter&quot;&gt;CBC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketplace.org/shows/make-me-smart/unpacking-mastodon/&quot;&gt;Kai Ryssdal (of NPR Marketplace fame) and Kimberly Adams&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/twitter-users-mastodon-meltdown/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;WIRED&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rnz.co.nz/national/programmes/ninetonoon/audio/2018866818/twitter-users-seek-alternative-to-musk-run-platform&quot;&gt;Radio New Zealand&lt;/a&gt;, among other outlets. It was a wild time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also went to the annual Association of Internet Researchers conference in Dublin the midst of all this. As you can imagine, the hot topic was what to do if Twitter burns to the ground. &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/12/11/AOIR-social.html&quot;&gt;AOIR is now talking about starting its own Mastodon/Hometown instance&lt;/a&gt;. And several of the AOIR scholars who work on alternative social media are starting to plan projects together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this cements my idea that my next book should be about Mastodon. Indeed, it’s made me rethink that project – I don’t want to write it for academics. I want to write it for all the people who are deeply troubled by the fact that corporate social media can be dominated by billionaires, that we have no control over it, and that these systems are designed to exploit our sociality for profit. What the Musk wave taught me is that there are literally &lt;em&gt;millions&lt;/em&gt; of such people out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I no longer feel lonely in studying alternatives like Mastodon. In fact, I have the great privilege of connecting to people around the world who are thinking deeply about what social media means for our lives. Some of them have been on non-centralized, FOSS, democratically-run social media for years. Some are only now experimenting with these systems. But the conversation is now rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in an effort to reach a broader audience, I’m now writing &lt;em&gt;Move Slowly and Build Bridges&lt;/em&gt; in a more accessible format. I will continue to blog about it here, and I will &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/opinion/contributors/2022/12/18/elon-musks-stance-on-free-speech-doesnt-include-competition-to-twitter.html&quot;&gt;write op-eds&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/citizens-social-media-can-provide-an-antidote-to-propaganda-and-disinformation-192491&quot;&gt;other accessible publications&lt;/a&gt; about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also looking for a book agent for my next project. (Perhaps that’s you? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.robertwgehl.org/&quot;&gt;Please contact me!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2023 is going to be an exciting year, I think!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">I don’t often do “Year in Review” posts, but… this past year has been something else. I’ve started a new job in a new country, I published another book, and my area of research (alternative social media) got a lot of media attention. In addition, I’ve formulated a new book project – and in doing so, I almost regret the name of this blog! But don’t worry: the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream is still alive, even if it is a bit more self-reflexive about what FOSS means. I’ll do this post in roughly chronological order. Buckle up: it’s a long post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Very Playvicious Christmas</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/24/Playvicous-Christmas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Very Playvicious Christmas" /><published>2022-12-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/24/Playvicous-Christmas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/24/Playvicous-Christmas.html">&lt;p&gt;This Christmas season, we all received a gift: Ro is blogging about Playvicious.social. He currently has four posts with more on the way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://roiskinda.cool/2022/11/recuerda-pv-chapter-1-the-start-part-1.html&quot;&gt;The Start, Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://roiskinda.cool/2022/12/recuerda-pv-chapter-2-the-start-part-2.html&quot;&gt;The Start, Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://roiskinda.cool/2022/12/recuerda-pv-chapter-3-the-name.html&quot;&gt;The Name&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://roiskinda.cool/2022/12/recuerda-pv-chapter-4-away-we-go.html&quot;&gt;Away We Go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came across Ro’s work while Playvicious was running sometime in 2018, and I made a note of it – and then forgot. I got distracted by a major project: my co-authored book on disinformation, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262543453/&quot;&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/a&gt;. I put off my Mastodon/fediverse studies in order to understand social media and propaganda, especially in relation to US presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I don’t regret diving into disinformation, I do regret not witnessing Playvicious’s run. It was an early, if not the first, Black-run instance on the fediverse. It was a source of joy for a lot of people. As Ro puts it, the idea of “play vicious” is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The energetic, unfiltered, sometimes uncomfortable, but the relentlessly progressive pursuit of understanding ourselves through creativity. It defined us as a group of thinking and feeling people who wanted to burn away all unnecessary details and get to the essence of why we loved what we loved and exist in that space for however long we could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that energy attracted some hate. As Ro will no doubt relate, Playvicious.social faced harassment and racism. Ro shut it down after watching as his moderators were traumatized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I missed its run online. And I really regret that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Ro (and others – I think more folks are starting to talk about PV) is giving all of us a great gift: an inside view of this most important Mastodon instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story Ro is telling is intensely personal. It’s also deeply important for the big questions of the fediverse, such as content moderation, how instances should relate to one another, and how societal injustices are replicated again and again online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Mastodon grows, a big stain has been not only the end of Playvicious.social, but also the experience of Black Mastodon members more generally. When people left Twitter after Musk’s takeover, it included the community known as Black Twitter. But Black Twitter ran into casual racism on the fediverse, and currently people are struggling to create #BlackMastodon. (I recommend following that hashtag and boosting posts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, while PV.social is gone, Ro is not done. He’s building new software to this day, he hosts a microblog (a Misskey instance), and he’s contributing moderation tools to the fediverse – even in spite of all he and his colleagues went through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to Ro (and other PV folks) because I believe I cannot write my current book (Goal 2!) about Mastodon without talking about Playvicious.social. But it’s also not my story to tell. It’s Ro’s and other folks’ story. My job is to talk about it in the contexts that I can dig up through research and &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html&quot;&gt;interviews&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to support Ro’s work, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/Are0h&quot;&gt;head to his Patreon&lt;/a&gt;. And keep watching &lt;a href=&quot;https://roiskinda.cool&quot;&gt;roiskinda.cool&lt;/a&gt; for more about PV!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Mastodon" /><summary type="html">This Christmas season, we all received a gift: Ro is blogging about Playvicious.social. He currently has four posts with more on the way: The Start, Part 1 The Start, Part 2 The Name Away We Go I came across Ro’s work while Playvicious was running sometime in 2018, and I made a note of it – and then forgot. I got distracted by a major project: my co-authored book on disinformation, Social Engineering. I put off my Mastodon/fediverse studies in order to understand social media and propaganda, especially in relation to US presidential elections. While I don’t regret diving into disinformation, I do regret not witnessing Playvicious’s run. It was an early, if not the first, Black-run instance on the fediverse. It was a source of joy for a lot of people. As Ro puts it, the idea of “play vicious” is The energetic, unfiltered, sometimes uncomfortable, but the relentlessly progressive pursuit of understanding ourselves through creativity. It defined us as a group of thinking and feeling people who wanted to burn away all unnecessary details and get to the essence of why we loved what we loved and exist in that space for however long we could. But that energy attracted some hate. As Ro will no doubt relate, Playvicious.social faced harassment and racism. Ro shut it down after watching as his moderators were traumatized. I missed its run online. And I really regret that. But Ro (and others – I think more folks are starting to talk about PV) is giving all of us a great gift: an inside view of this most important Mastodon instance. The story Ro is telling is intensely personal. It’s also deeply important for the big questions of the fediverse, such as content moderation, how instances should relate to one another, and how societal injustices are replicated again and again online. As Mastodon grows, a big stain has been not only the end of Playvicious.social, but also the experience of Black Mastodon members more generally. When people left Twitter after Musk’s takeover, it included the community known as Black Twitter. But Black Twitter ran into casual racism on the fediverse, and currently people are struggling to create #BlackMastodon. (I recommend following that hashtag and boosting posts). Fortunately, while PV.social is gone, Ro is not done. He’s building new software to this day, he hosts a microblog (a Misskey instance), and he’s contributing moderation tools to the fediverse – even in spite of all he and his colleagues went through. I’m grateful to Ro (and other PV folks) because I believe I cannot write my current book (Goal 2!) about Mastodon without talking about Playvicious.social. But it’s also not my story to tell. It’s Ro’s and other folks’ story. My job is to talk about it in the contexts that I can dig up through research and interviews. If you want to support Ro’s work, head to his Patreon. And keep watching roiskinda.cool for more about PV!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two New Publications</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/19/Two-new-pubs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two New Publications" /><published>2022-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/19/Two-new-pubs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/19/Two-new-pubs.html">&lt;p&gt;Just a quick note: I have a new journal article, co-authored with Diana Zulli: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400&quot;&gt;The Digital Covenant: Non-centralized Platform Governance on the Mastodon Social Network&lt;/a&gt;.” The abstract is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The majority of scholarship on platform governance focuses on for-profit, corporate social media with highly centralized network structures. Instead, we show how non-centralized platform governance functions in the Mastodon social network. Through an analysis of survey data, Github and Discourse developer discussions, Mastodon Codes of Conduct, and participant observations, we argue Mastodon’s platform governance is an exemplar of the covenant, a key concept from federalist political theory. We contrast Mastodon’s covenantal federalism platform governance with the contractual form used by corporate social media. We also use covenantal federalist theory to explain how Mastodon’s users, administrators, and developers justify revoking or denying membership in the federation. In doing so, this study sheds new light on the innovations in platform governance that go beyond the corporate/alt-right platform dichotomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/objects/hc:49434/datastreams/CONTENT/content&quot;&gt;available as a pre-print on H-Commons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/opinion/contributors/2022/12/18/elon-musks-stance-on-free-speech-doesnt-include-competition-to-twitter.html&quot;&gt;published an op-ed in the &lt;em&gt;Toronto Star&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; this morning. The op-ed discusses the fact that Twitter is blocking links to Mastodon instances, including my own, Scholar.social. However, Twitter is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; blocking links to Gab, the alt-right social network that hosts self-identified Nazis. It seems Musk is concerned about competition from well-moderated, tiny Mastodon instances, but not so much from the alt-right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the hours since I published the op-ed, things have gotten even more intense, with Twitter starting &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.twitter.com/en/rules-and-policies/social-platforms-policy&quot;&gt;a policy that bans any promotion of alternative social media&lt;/a&gt; (and some big corporate ones, too). The glaring exception? Gab.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Mastodon" /><summary type="html">Just a quick note: I have a new journal article, co-authored with Diana Zulli: “The Digital Covenant: Non-centralized Platform Governance on the Mastodon Social Network.” The abstract is: The majority of scholarship on platform governance focuses on for-profit, corporate social media with highly centralized network structures. Instead, we show how non-centralized platform governance functions in the Mastodon social network. Through an analysis of survey data, Github and Discourse developer discussions, Mastodon Codes of Conduct, and participant observations, we argue Mastodon’s platform governance is an exemplar of the covenant, a key concept from federalist political theory. We contrast Mastodon’s covenantal federalism platform governance with the contractual form used by corporate social media. We also use covenantal federalist theory to explain how Mastodon’s users, administrators, and developers justify revoking or denying membership in the federation. In doing so, this study sheds new light on the innovations in platform governance that go beyond the corporate/alt-right platform dichotomy. The paper is also available as a pre-print on H-Commons. And I also published an op-ed in the Toronto Star this morning. The op-ed discusses the fact that Twitter is blocking links to Mastodon instances, including my own, Scholar.social. However, Twitter is not blocking links to Gab, the alt-right social network that hosts self-identified Nazis. It seems Musk is concerned about competition from well-moderated, tiny Mastodon instances, but not so much from the alt-right. In the hours since I published the op-ed, things have gotten even more intense, with Twitter starting a policy that bans any promotion of alternative social media (and some big corporate ones, too). The glaring exception? Gab.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AOIR.social?</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/11/AOIR-social.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AOIR.social?" /><published>2022-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/11/AOIR%20social</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/11/AOIR-social.html">&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk has crazy timing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He completed his purchase of Twitter &lt;em&gt;right before&lt;/em&gt; the annual meeting of the Association of Internet Researchers, held in Dublin in November of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coincidence? I think not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Musk takeover of Twitter prompted a conversation at AOIR’s meeting in Dublin in early November: should AOIR start a Mastodon (specifically, a Hometown) instance? As someone who has been advocating for alternative social media for years, I was all about this. Internet researchers have been among the first to recognize the perils of corporate social media. But of course, AOIR members often deeply engage online, which means using those systems for their pleasures and professional opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the old commercial says, there’s got to be a better way: a way to do social media but to do it on our terms. If the Musk takeover is the catalyst that pushes AOIR to adopt the fediverse, then as disturbing as things have gotten, at least there will be a positive outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spurred on by Aram Sinnreich, we started having informal discussions at AOIR’s 2022 meeting about starting up our own social media. What would it entail? How would we do it? The informal discussion involved some of my favorite AOIR folks: Nik John, Adrienne Massanari, Nick Couldry, Pat Aufderheide, and Esther Hammelburg (if I left anyone out, please let me know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conversation went well but we all knew there was a lot of work ahead. Last week, I met with the AOIR Executive Committee to continue the work. They’ve agreed to my posting about this process to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is meant to do two things. First, it documents how an academic association deliberates over whether and how to establish a presence on the fediverse. That ought to be useful for other organizations considering doing the same. I know there are quite a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, my hope is that by sharing AOIR’s deliberations, the rest of the fediverse can have some insight into our decision to proceed (should it come to that). Given that AOIR members engage in Internet Research, there may be trepidation about AOIR joining the fediverse – would AOIR come to the fedi to study it? To turn its users into objects of research?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put another way, will AOIR be a good organizational citizen of the fediverse? Will it host a well-moderated instance? Will it respect fediverse cultures and norms? Please read on, fedifriends. I hope that it’s clear AOIR is going to do it right – otherwise, AOIR is not going to do it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tough-questions&quot;&gt;Tough Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meeting with AOIR Executive Committee went, in my view, extremely well, because they asked me the hardest questions. And for anyone starting a fediverse instance, I recommend asking similar questions. The questions included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do we spin up our own cloud server, a la Digital Ocean, or do we seek out managed hosting?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do we plan for our total membership to be involved (this year, 1000 people) or for a fraction of them?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do we block instances up front, or do we do so after bad actors appear?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should we proceed if we can’t attract a pool of moderators?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do we deal with minor infractions of a code of conduct?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do we teach our members the ways of the fediverse – including the context-specific aspects of privacy and safety, especially in relation to research?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would AOIR members get out of this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is: the conversation ended up answering these questions in the right way. The Executive Committee is on the right track, in my view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, we shouldn’t just spin up a DO droplet. We need managed hosting, because we do not have the expertise nor time to manage the backend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our anticipated growth from a few dozen interested early adoptors to potentially our full 1000-person membership also suggests working with managed hosting, since managed hosts have the expertise to scale up resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes to blocking instances from the outset. Rather than reacting to fascist BS after it happens, block the fascists first. This is the advice I’m hearing from the experienced admins out there, and it sounds like AOIR is going to do it, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, we should not proceed if we can’t recruit moderators. First of all, having no moderators would send the wrong signal to the rest of the fediverse, namely that we are not serious about this. Second, if we can’t recruit moderators from our membership, then perhaps the membership isn’t showing enough interest in AOIR having an instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of moderation, minor infractions should not be a basis to boot people. Discussion is the best course. (For me, this is the promise of the fediverse: moderation at a human scale. It’s not easy, but at least we’re not under the illusion that AI can moderate, or that one moderator to 100K members is a good ratio). This is social media, after all, and it’s a new system. People will make minor mistakes. We need to be ready to help them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related to the above, yes, we need to onboard our members. The fediverse isn’t Twitter. Moreover, AOIR is the group that produced Internet Research Ethics guides. And our ethics guides clearly state that Internet research needs to be very sensitive to context. The context of the fediverse, in my view, is that consent is ultra-important. That means lots of discussions with the membership about new research methods that take into account consent of the fediverse members. In my view, this will be the true struggle of an AOIR instance, and the way in which we address it will make it or break it. Because if we fail to respect the consent culture of the fediverse, our instance &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be isolated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, what would AOIR members get out of it? I mean, if you ask me, life beyond corporate social media is totally worth it. But the EC also suggests that this would allow for more communication among the membership – more opportunities for grad students and early researchers to connect with the senior researchers at AOIR. More opportunities to collaborate. More opportunities to share our work and celebrate it. And more cat pictures. Definitely more cat pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-to-come&quot;&gt;More to come&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conversation isn’t over, and that means more tough questions. But it’s a good sign that it’s the Executive Committee asking them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will post more as things develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;edit-for-credit&quot;&gt;Edit for Credit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t mention in the original post that Sarah T. Roberts, Aram, and I drafted a Code of Conduct for the Executive Committee ahead of the meeting. I want to acknowledge Sarah and Aram’s work on that document, too. I imagine we can share a draft of the COC with the fediverse, but for now we’re working on it in-house.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Association of Internet Researchers" /><category term="Hometown" /><summary type="html">Elon Musk has crazy timing. He completed his purchase of Twitter right before the annual meeting of the Association of Internet Researchers, held in Dublin in November of this year. Coincidence? I think not. The Musk takeover of Twitter prompted a conversation at AOIR’s meeting in Dublin in early November: should AOIR start a Mastodon (specifically, a Hometown) instance? As someone who has been advocating for alternative social media for years, I was all about this. Internet researchers have been among the first to recognize the perils of corporate social media. But of course, AOIR members often deeply engage online, which means using those systems for their pleasures and professional opportunities. As the old commercial says, there’s got to be a better way: a way to do social media but to do it on our terms. If the Musk takeover is the catalyst that pushes AOIR to adopt the fediverse, then as disturbing as things have gotten, at least there will be a positive outcome. Spurred on by Aram Sinnreich, we started having informal discussions at AOIR’s 2022 meeting about starting up our own social media. What would it entail? How would we do it? The informal discussion involved some of my favorite AOIR folks: Nik John, Adrienne Massanari, Nick Couldry, Pat Aufderheide, and Esther Hammelburg (if I left anyone out, please let me know). The conversation went well but we all knew there was a lot of work ahead. Last week, I met with the AOIR Executive Committee to continue the work. They’ve agreed to my posting about this process to this blog. This post is meant to do two things. First, it documents how an academic association deliberates over whether and how to establish a presence on the fediverse. That ought to be useful for other organizations considering doing the same. I know there are quite a few. Second, my hope is that by sharing AOIR’s deliberations, the rest of the fediverse can have some insight into our decision to proceed (should it come to that). Given that AOIR members engage in Internet Research, there may be trepidation about AOIR joining the fediverse – would AOIR come to the fedi to study it? To turn its users into objects of research? Put another way, will AOIR be a good organizational citizen of the fediverse? Will it host a well-moderated instance? Will it respect fediverse cultures and norms? Please read on, fedifriends. I hope that it’s clear AOIR is going to do it right – otherwise, AOIR is not going to do it at all.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds, Content Moderation webinar</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/09/FOSSFinds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds, Content Moderation webinar" /><published>2022-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/09/FOSSFinds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/12/09/FOSSFinds.html">&lt;p&gt;A short FOSS Finds this time, but it contains something worth watching out for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I attended a &lt;a href=&quot;https://meedan.com/event/webinar-trust-and-safety-on-the-fediverse&quot;&gt;web seminar&lt;/a&gt; run by Darius Kazemi (creator of the Hometown fork of Mastodon), Kat Lo, a community moderator, and Aaron Huslage, a computer security professional. It was about Trust and Safety on the fediverse. The event was sponsored by Darius’s employer, Meedan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the webinar (or a version of it) will be available in video form. I will watch for it and post an update here when I see a link. For now, if you’re interested in content moderation, I’d strongly recommend watching out for a video version of the webinar – especially because of the Q and A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The webinar itself was quite a good overview of moderation on the fediverse, talking about blocking, muting and the like, so if you need to know more about that, it’s worth a watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But during the Q and A, I heard the most interesting stuff. Darius and others talked about a lot of emerging projects that might be worth investigating. For example, co-op moderation collectives, which would offer their moderation know-how to new fediverse instances. I don’t have specifics here, but this sounds fascinating! Also, Darius talked about forthcoming legal guides to running instances. Again, no specifics yet, but something to watch for. Or, reach out to &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinysubversions.com/&quot;&gt;Darius&lt;/a&gt; – he seems really interested in helping others with these issues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="alternative social media" /><category term="content moderation" /><summary type="html">A short FOSS Finds this time, but it contains something worth watching out for. This week I attended a web seminar run by Darius Kazemi (creator of the Hometown fork of Mastodon), Kat Lo, a community moderator, and Aaron Huslage, a computer security professional. It was about Trust and Safety on the fediverse. The event was sponsored by Darius’s employer, Meedan. I believe the webinar (or a version of it) will be available in video form. I will watch for it and post an update here when I see a link. For now, if you’re interested in content moderation, I’d strongly recommend watching out for a video version of the webinar – especially because of the Q and A. The webinar itself was quite a good overview of moderation on the fediverse, talking about blocking, muting and the like, so if you need to know more about that, it’s worth a watch. But during the Q and A, I heard the most interesting stuff. Darius and others talked about a lot of emerging projects that might be worth investigating. For example, co-op moderation collectives, which would offer their moderation know-how to new fediverse instances. I don’t have specifics here, but this sounds fascinating! Also, Darius talked about forthcoming legal guides to running instances. Again, no specifics yet, but something to watch for. Or, reach out to Darius – he seems really interested in helping others with these issues.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Twitter Isn’t That Important</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/11/19/Surge.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Twitter Isn’t That Important" /><published>2022-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2022/11/19/Surge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2022/11/19/Surge.html">&lt;p&gt;Elon, what are you doing? I don’t know. None of us knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it appears you’re tearing Twitter apart. And this is driving people to Mastodon. I will talk about Mastodon at some other point – I am, of course, writing a book about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I want to talk about the fall of Twitter and what I think it means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TL;DR version is: I don’t think Twitter was all that important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I keep hearing: what are we losing if Twitter goes away? This is asked in many different ways — are we losing a town square? Are we losing insight into how people socialize? Are we losing an archive of human history? Perhaps the clearest explanation of what Twitter may have meant comes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/what-the-world-would-lose-with-the-demise-of-twitter-valuable-eyewitness-accounts-and-raw-data-on-human-behavior-as-well-as-a-habitat-for-trolls-194601&quot;&gt;Anjana Susaria’s Conversation article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, academics and journalists are mourning Twitter. But I would suggest that this moment is a good one to reconsider some very basic assumptions about that site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if instead of thinking of Twitter as a “town square,” maybe what’s really happening is &lt;em&gt;we are losing the conceit that a relatively small facet of human life has been conflated with a “town square” because the elites who use that system have declared it to be a town square?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if instead of a record of all human activity, &lt;em&gt;we are losing easy-to-gather datasets to make overly simple claims about sociality?&lt;/em&gt; And &lt;em&gt;what if all we are losing an archive that, were it to persist, would warp our conception of this period of history?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to downplay the importance of Twitter to your life – if it was important to you, that’s fine. Many people find community online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I am questioning is Twitter’s overall social utility. For every claim about the Arab Spring or Black Lives Matter (e.g., “how could social protest possibly happen without Twitter?!?”), let’s talk about governments using Twitter to monitor and dominate populations. For every claim about revealing previously unseen facets of social behavior, let’s talk about how Twitter reduces us to a small set of social verbs – so small, in fact, that socialbots can successfully mimic our behavior in the site. For all the claims about “the archive,” let’s not forget that this system was designed to get us to declare our likes and desires, generate data about those things, and sell us back to ourselves qua commodities. Some archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, anyone who knows my work for the past decade will probably not be surprised that I am dismissive of doom-and-gloom over Twitter’s loss. I’ve been calling for people to leave sites like Twitter for over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if it survives – and it may just – let’s take this moment to stop elevating it to a status that it really doesn’t deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-script-on-donald-trump&quot;&gt;Post-Script: On Donald Trump&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I write this, the news just broke that Musk will let the insurrectionist Donald Trump back onto the site. Again, here is exactly what I’m talking about: because media elites have relied on Twitter, it is only right and proper that Trump is brought back so we can have access to his contributions to the “town square.” Frankly, this is utterly insane. He. Tried. To. Become. The. Dictator. Of. The. World’s. Biggest. Military. Power. The idea that we have to debate issues with him and his ilk in a corporate website is bankrupt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-post-script-im-out&quot;&gt;Post-Post-Script: I’m out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just deactivated my Twitter account.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="alternative social media" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">Elon, what are you doing? I don’t know. None of us knows. But it appears you’re tearing Twitter apart. And this is driving people to Mastodon. I will talk about Mastodon at some other point – I am, of course, writing a book about it. Here, I want to talk about the fall of Twitter and what I think it means. The TL;DR version is: I don’t think Twitter was all that important.</summary></entry></feed>