<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-09-08T17:23:20-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">ASM update, Bibliography Edition</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/09/08/ASMupdateBib.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM update, Bibliography Edition" /><published>2023-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/09/08/ASMupdateBib</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/09/08/ASMupdateBib.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a minor update, but I hope it’s useful to anyone interested in doing alternative social media research. I’ve long hosted a Zotero group, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/groups/542752/social_media_alternatives_project_bibliography&quot;&gt;Social Media Alternatives Project&lt;/a&gt;, which has a library. As much as I love Zotero, though, I’ve not had much luck with groups for fostering public discussion. Their libraries are a bit too tucked away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since many people are requesting resources about ASM, and that Zotero library may not be the easiest thing to find, I’m going to regularly port that library to a &lt;a href=&quot;../bib.html&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/a&gt; page on this blog. I’ve got to do some cleaning up, but there’s some good stuff in there. As Steve Brule might say: check it out!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html">This is a minor update, but I hope it’s useful to anyone interested in doing alternative social media research. I’ve long hosted a Zotero group, the Social Media Alternatives Project, which has a library. As much as I love Zotero, though, I’ve not had much luck with groups for fostering public discussion. Their libraries are a bit too tucked away. Since many people are requesting resources about ASM, and that Zotero library may not be the easiest thing to find, I’m going to regularly port that library to a Bibliography page on this blog. I’ve got to do some cleaning up, but there’s some good stuff in there. As Steve Brule might say: check it out!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Move Slowly and Build Bridges to be published by Oxford University Press</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Move Slowly and Build Bridges to be published by Oxford University Press" /><published>2023-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/08/17/OxfordUP</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html">&lt;p&gt;I am very excited to announce that my next book, &lt;em&gt;Move Slowly and Building Bridges: Mastodon, the Fediverse, and the Struggle for Democratic Social Media&lt;/em&gt; will be published by Oxford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, I sent a proposal (a short synopsis of the book, audience considerations, and two sample chapters) to Oxford. They moved &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;. They recruited two peer reviewers who turned around reviews very quickly, and then Oxford’s editorial board reviewed the project. I just received a contract based on these reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word I got from Oxford is that they are excited about the project – and about the fediverse. That’s really good news, because the normal advice an author would get is to promote one’s work on corporate social media. But I think that any book about the fediverse has to be talked about on the fediverse. Maybe this project can help other academic authors break away from Twitter/X and Facebook/Meta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, fediverse, watch for &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social/@rwg&quot;&gt;posts about this book from me on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;. I’m also committing to sharing details about the book here on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-im-writing-about&quot;&gt;What I’m writing about&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about the book, I’d first point you to &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/01/06/Goal2.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, which is the earliest description of this project. Things have evolved somewhat since that post, but for now, that post from early 2022 gives you some insight into what I’m writing about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have a series of posts I’m writing about the creation of ActivityPub – you can see &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/20/ActivityPub1.html&quot;&gt;part 1 here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/05/09/ActivityPub2.html&quot;&gt;part 2 here&lt;/a&gt;. Watch for more of these, since one chapter will focus on the creation of ActivityPub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, watch out for &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/tags/asm%20update.html&quot;&gt;“Alternative Social Media Updates”&lt;/a&gt; – those posts discuss news items that are relevant to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also have some co-authored journal articles on &lt;a href=&quot;https://robertwgehl.org/text/pubs/Zulli%20et%20al.%20-%202020%20-%20Rethinking%20the%20%e2%80%9csocial%e2%80%9d%20in%20%e2%80%9csocial%20media%e2%80%9d%20Insight.pdf&quot;&gt;rethinking social media&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400&quot;&gt;codes of conduct&lt;/a&gt; that also give you some insight into the project. I do have a chapter focusing on codes of conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also plan on writing about specific chapters openly on this blog. Watch for such posts in the coming months. As an example of what that will look like, &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump.html&quot;&gt;this post on the “killer hype cycle”&lt;/a&gt; is now part of chapter 1 of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-im-writing-it&quot;&gt;How I’m writing it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have written about how I’m doing the research. I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html&quot;&gt;talked about my use of interviews here&lt;/a&gt; – that process is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/26/Subscribe.html&quot;&gt;wrote about my approach to using subscriptions&lt;/a&gt; as a way to support artists and creative folks on the fediverse – that is still ongoing, and will be relevant to a chapter on creativity on the fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have my &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/tags/goal%201.html&quot;&gt;“Goal 1” series of posts&lt;/a&gt; about using FOSS tools to write – I will continue to write about using Zotero, Zettlr, Nextcloud and other tools to write this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the next 12 months will be hectic, but I’m very gratified to have a publisher lined up for this book. This work has been a focus of mine for many years. I’ve met some incredible, smart, insightful people on the fediverse – I hope this book, and this process, will be up to their standards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">I am very excited to announce that my next book, Move Slowly and Building Bridges: Mastodon, the Fediverse, and the Struggle for Democratic Social Media will be published by Oxford University Press. Earlier this year, I sent a proposal (a short synopsis of the book, audience considerations, and two sample chapters) to Oxford. They moved fast. They recruited two peer reviewers who turned around reviews very quickly, and then Oxford’s editorial board reviewed the project. I just received a contract based on these reviews. The word I got from Oxford is that they are excited about the project – and about the fediverse. That’s really good news, because the normal advice an author would get is to promote one’s work on corporate social media. But I think that any book about the fediverse has to be talked about on the fediverse. Maybe this project can help other academic authors break away from Twitter/X and Facebook/Meta. So, fediverse, watch for posts about this book from me on Mastodon. I’m also committing to sharing details about the book here on this blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM update, August 12 2023</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/08/12/ASMupdateFSEP.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM update, August 12 2023" /><published>2023-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/08/12/ASMupdateFSEP</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/08/12/ASMupdateFSEP.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while, thanks to drama with rent and apartments (welcome to Toronto, Robert), but I’m back with another Alternative Social Media update!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-challenges-in-moderation-and-new-responses&quot;&gt;New challenges in moderation and new responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Content warning: abuse mention&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine most readers of this blog saw news about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cyber.fsi.stanford.edu/io/news/addressing-child-exploitation-federated-social-media&quot;&gt;Stanford Internet Observatory report&lt;/a&gt; on child sexual abuse material (CSAM) on the fediverse. I know I did. I’m currently the admin of &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social/&quot;&gt;AoIR.social&lt;/a&gt;, and the report came out while I was in the middle of moving apartments – and in the middle of relying on dodgy mobile hotspot internet. Regardless of the bad connection and stress of unpacking, the report’s publication prompted me to immediately do an audit of AoIR.social’s instance blocklist to see if we were facing any risk of having CSAM hit our server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am quite confident AoIR.social is in good shape. Why? Because on day one of AoIR.social (months before the Stanford report), I imported blocklists. First, I grabbed &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeberg.org/oliphant/blocklists&quot;&gt;Oliphant’s Tier 0 Blocklist&lt;/a&gt;, and later &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebad.space/&quot;&gt;Ro’s The Bad Space&lt;/a&gt; list. Both of those are based on community consensus about who are the bad actors on the fediverse, and by importing the lists into AoIR.social’s moderation panel, bad actors – including the ones implicitly identified in Stanford report – were already blocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while the Stanford report was scary as hell, the community has been aware of bad instances for a while now. The community is sharing knowledge about the bad servers and is blocking them. As one admin put it to me, any fedi admin with any consciousness about moderation has been blocking the bad instances for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since the report came out, I’ve interviewed Oliphant, Ro, and other respected fediverse admins and they are advocating for easier use of blocklists to prevent the fediverse from being swamped with bad servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, a great response to moderation challenges is coming in the form of Ro’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://nivenly.org/docs/papers/fsep/&quot;&gt;Fediverse Safety Enhancement Project&lt;/a&gt;. This project is about automated, consensus-based subscription blocklists. The proposed interface looks a lot like one of my favorite tools, The &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/&quot;&gt;Pi-Hole ad-blocking system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;huge.&lt;/em&gt; There are so many interesting things to figure out, from the technical to social. Special attention should be paid to how such lists will be governed. The good news is there are folks working on that exact issue, including Ro and Oliphant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint, hint, fellow ASM academics: this is a good topic to study! I know Ro and people like him would welcome academic knowledge about how to improve this new form of moderation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, if you’re interested in supporting Ro’s project, I recommend giving (you gotta give!) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gofundme.com/f/a-new-way-to-social-media&quot;&gt;to his GoFundMe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aoir-workshop-is-a-go&quot;&gt;AOIR Workshop is a Go&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, Jessa Lingel, Ashwin Nagappa, and I are hosting an &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.org/aoir2023/preconfworkshops/&quot;&gt;Association of Internet Researchers Preconference focusing on alternative social media&lt;/a&gt;. This will take place in Philadelphia on October 18. From what we’ve seen, we’re just short of full capacity. If you’re going to AOIR, there may be still time to sign up if you haven’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still planning details but our focus will be on research project creation and ethics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Moderation" /><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html">It’s been a while, thanks to drama with rent and apartments (welcome to Toronto, Robert), but I’m back with another Alternative Social Media update!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seeking Grad Students and Postdocs</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/07/02/GradStudentsPostDocs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seeking Grad Students and Postdocs" /><published>2023-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/07/02/GradStudentsPostDocs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/07/02/GradStudentsPostDocs.html">&lt;p&gt;This is just a short note to announce that, thanks to some generous funding at York University, I am recruiting graduate students (MA and PhD) as well as post-docs. I’d like to work with folks on alternative social media, in particular. Methodologically, I tend to use qualitative approaches, such as digital ethnography, software studies, and grounded theory/situational analysis. I am a critical scholar, as well, so I prefer working with people who are actively examining power relations in technical systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grad students, York has two programs I’m affiliated with: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorku.ca/gradstudies/sts/&quot;&gt;Science and Technology Studies&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorku.ca/gradstudies/cmct/&quot;&gt;Communication and Culture&lt;/a&gt;, a communication and media studies focused program. My understanding is that STS in particular is eager for students, so if you have any background in STS, I would recommend that route. Either way, please do contact me via email (I have a protonmail account, robertwgehl) or &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social/@rwg&quot;&gt;find me on the fediverse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-docs, York U has received a very generous grant called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorku.ca/research/connected-minds/opportunities/&quot;&gt;Connected Minds&lt;/a&gt; which includes many funding opportunities. Contact me if you have some interest there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.robertwgehl.org/text/gehl_vita.pdf&quot;&gt;Here’s a PDF of my CV&lt;/a&gt; if you want to get a sense of my work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="alternative social media" /><summary type="html">This is just a short note to announce that, thanks to some generous funding at York University, I am recruiting graduate students (MA and PhD) as well as post-docs. I’d like to work with folks on alternative social media, in particular. Methodologically, I tend to use qualitative approaches, such as digital ethnography, software studies, and grounded theory/situational analysis. I am a critical scholar, as well, so I prefer working with people who are actively examining power relations in technical systems. Grad students, York has two programs I’m affiliated with: Science and Technology Studies and Communication and Culture, a communication and media studies focused program. My understanding is that STS in particular is eager for students, so if you have any background in STS, I would recommend that route. Either way, please do contact me via email (I have a protonmail account, robertwgehl) or find me on the fediverse. Post-docs, York U has received a very generous grant called Connected Minds which includes many funding opportunities. Contact me if you have some interest there. Here’s a PDF of my CV if you want to get a sense of my work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Update, June 25 2023</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/06/25/ASMupdate-Warwick.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update, June 25 2023" /><published>2023-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/06/25/ASMupdate-Warwick</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/06/25/ASMupdate-Warwick.html">&lt;p&gt;This update focuses on the University of Warwick &lt;a href=&quot;https://events.teams.microsoft.com/event/4d682da3-3b4e-4909-9239-743d86cc7dcc@09bacfbd-47ef-4465-9265-3546f2eaf6bc&quot;&gt;Mastodon Research Symposium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nate Tkacz, Carlos Cámara-Menoyo, and Fangzhou Zhang put on a wonderful, and intensive, two days focused on Mastodon and the broader fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly of value, I thought, was the second day, which was unfortunately not streamed. We gathered together to talk about research ethics and methods. I posted some notes about what we said on the fediverse, using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social/tags/mastosymposium&quot;&gt;#MastoSymposium hashtag&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, one of the most important conversations we need to have – and openly have – is about research ethics &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the fediverse. I talked about this at length &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextcloud.robertwgehl.org/index.php/s/G34Y5X2PoNBq5Xp&quot;&gt;in my plenary presentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the point was hammered home for me on day 2 by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://systerserver.net/&quot;&gt;SysterServer&lt;/a&gt; collective, a group that hosts some instances and who attended the workshop. They aren’t academics, so they aren’t concerned with filling up CVs. But they have needs. Ethical research &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; them could help address their needs. Our research ought to resonate with the fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s next? I believe we can continue this conversation at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.org/aoir2023/preconfworkshops/#building&quot;&gt;AOIR preconference&lt;/a&gt; that several of us are hosting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, let’s keep talking research ethics on the fediverse – a conversation that has been happening for years – see &lt;a href=&quot;https://apintandaparma.club/katlh/research-ethics-and-the-fediverse&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogghoran.se/2020/01/27/on-scraping-mastodon/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sunclipse.org/wp-content/downloads/2020/01/open-letter.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for just three examples.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="FOSS finds" /><summary type="html">This update focuses on the University of Warwick Mastodon Research Symposium.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Update, June 16 2023</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/06/16/ASMupdate1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update, June 16 2023" /><published>2023-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/06/16/ASMupdate1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/06/16/ASMupdate1.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NB: I’ve started an alternative social media email list, and I regularly email the list with news from the world of ASM. Since many ASM are free and open source software, it occurred to me that I should mirror those emails here on the blog. These might be the next iteration of “FOSS finds,” a series I ran in previous posts. If you are an ASM researcher and want to subscribe to the email list, contact me and I can add you. Or, just watch this space for (roughly) fortnightly updates.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an update on the world of ASM – at least as I see it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reddit-meltdown&quot;&gt;Reddit meltdown&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never was a Redditor, but even so, it’s hard not to notice what’s going on over there: what can only be called a labor strike on the part of subreddit moderators, done in protest to changes in the Reddit API. Specifically, subreddit moderators are making their subs private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you guess that there are alternatives to Reddit, you guessed right. One that I knew about is &lt;a href=&quot;https://join-lemmy.org/&quot;&gt;Lemmy&lt;/a&gt;. However, I’ve also learned about &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ernestwisniewski/kbin&quot;&gt;Kbin&lt;/a&gt;. From what I understand, both are gaining new members. And I also have seen people join Mastodon and cite the Reddit meltdown as the reason why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all bears watching, particularly in terms of moderation and governance discussions. (And if you know more about what’s going on, please let me know!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warwick&quot;&gt;Warwick&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week, the Centre for Interdisciplinary Methods will host a &lt;a href=&quot;https://events.teams.microsoft.com/event/4d682da3-3b4e-4909-9239-743d86cc7dcc@09bacfbd-47ef-4465-9265-3546f2eaf6bc&quot;&gt;Mastodon Tools and Research workshop&lt;/a&gt;. I have the honor of giving the plenary address, and you can see the abstract in that link. Basically, I’ll be talking about the struggles of queer and Black members to make the fediverse a better space, and how the Association of Internet Researchers will need to acknowledge that history on its aoir.social instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program includes a lot of people on this list. I’m really looking forward to the event – I’m going to take a ton of notes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;noncentralized-origin-stories&quot;&gt;Noncentralized Origin Stories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, the Colorado Media Lab &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.edu/lab/medlab/2023/06/06/open-social-media-origin-stories&quot;&gt;hosted a discussion&lt;/a&gt; by Christine Lemmer-Webber, Rabble (aka Evan Henshaw-Plath), and Golda Vez. Each of these are heavily involved in noncentralized protocol development. Lemmer-Webber is a co-author of ActivityPub and is currently working on &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/spritely/ocappub&quot;&gt;OcaPPub&lt;/a&gt;. Rabble worked on Indymedia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secure_Scuttlebutt&quot;&gt;Secure Scuttlebutt&lt;/a&gt;, and now &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nostr&quot;&gt;Nostr&lt;/a&gt;. Vez is involved with BlueSky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conversation gets a bit technical at points, but there’s plenty of history and discussion of content moderation mixed in, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;humbernews&quot;&gt;Humber.news&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I don’t know if I shared this, but here’s an interesting pedagogical project: &lt;a href=&quot;https://humber.news&quot;&gt;humber.news&lt;/a&gt;, run by Mike Wise, a journalism professor at Humber College in Toronto. Mike tells me that humber.news is a Mastodon instance he’s using in teaching journalism students about the fediverse. In my view, it’s a much-needed project; journalists will have to adjust their approaches if they want to share news and get news from the fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="FOSS finds" /><summary type="html">NB: I’ve started an alternative social media email list, and I regularly email the list with news from the world of ASM. Since many ASM are free and open source software, it occurred to me that I should mirror those emails here on the blog. These might be the next iteration of “FOSS finds,” a series I ran in previous posts. If you are an ASM researcher and want to subscribe to the email list, contact me and I can add you. Or, just watch this space for (roughly) fortnightly updates. Here’s an update on the world of ASM – at least as I see it!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reading the Minutes of the Social Web Working Group, part 2</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/05/09/ActivityPub2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reading the Minutes of the Social Web Working Group, part 2" /><published>2023-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/05/09/ActivityPub2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/05/09/ActivityPub2.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NB: This is the second in a series of posts where I will share my notes on my readings of the minutes of the Social Web Working Group. The &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/20/ActivityPub1.html&quot;&gt;first one is here&lt;/a&gt;. Future posts to come.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned several months ago, my book about Mastodon and the rest of the fediverse can’t be complete without a deep understanding of ActivityPub, the protocol that powers the fediverse. ActivityPub itself is getting a bit of love in the press (see this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2023/4/20/23689570/activitypub-protocol-standard-social-network&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Verge&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt; for an example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to understand ActivityPub, we have to look at the group that created it, the W3C’s Social Web Working Group, or SocialWG for short. They posted their meeting minutes on the Web and I have read &lt;em&gt;all of them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post on the SocialWG minutes, I focused on the very early years, 2014 to 2015, finding that the period was dominated by organizational issues – how to meet, how to make decisions, and so on. In this section, I will cover the development of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-core/&quot;&gt;ActivityStreams 2.0&lt;/a&gt;, the first goal of the SocialWG charter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-a-social-syntax-corporate-refusal-and-user-stories&quot;&gt;Phase 2: A social syntax, corporate refusal, and user stories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;social-syntax&quot;&gt;Social Syntax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the SocialWG’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2013/socialweb/social-wg-charter.html&quot;&gt;chartered goals&lt;/a&gt; was the production of a “a common JSON-based syntax for social data.” One potential source for this was “ActivityStreams,” an already-existing format for labeling online activities. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Activity_Streams_(format)&amp;amp;oldid=1153983815&quot;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; on this gives an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The standard provides a general way to represent activities. For instance, the sentence “Jack added Hawaii to his list of places to visit” would be represented in ActivityStreams as actor:jack, verb:add, object:Hawaii, target:placestovisit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While ActivityStreams was already in wide use, unless I’m mistaken, it was not codified as an official W3C standard. The SocialWG was to draw on the work of the informal &lt;a href=&quot;https://activitystrea.ms/specs/json/1.0/&quot;&gt;ActivityStreams community&lt;/a&gt;. Fortunately, James Snell, one of the key members of the ActivityStreams Community, got involved in the SocialWG and helped with this process. Spoiler alert: ActivityStreams 2.0 would be the ultimate result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how far along ActivityStreams was prior to the SocialWG, what’s interesting about a “social syntax” is a fundamental question: how does one capture human sociality in a vocabulary? As SocialWG member wilkie &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-01-06-minutes&quot;&gt;stated&lt;/a&gt;: “we should get philosophical :) we are trying to capture the entirity of human creativity. the challenge is not getting overwhelmed while also not being too limiting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were fascinating discussions in the minutes about terms. An example is a debate that happened in April 2014: should Activity Streams 2.0 use “person” or “profile”? Here’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-04-14-minutes&quot;&gt;snippet of the discussion&lt;/a&gt; between Evan Prodromou and Amy Guy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;eprodrom: I feel like the Person is enough to justify a Profile, or if there are other kinds of profile, we could use other objects. such as Corporation etc having profiles for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… the biggest issue that a Person having a Profile that people may have other aspects or personalities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;rhiaro: a person can have multiple profiles, but maybe persons and profiles don’t need to be modelled separately in the vocab (unsure)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;eprodrom: for instance, my interest in baseball or poker may have different personalities facing different social areas
… I feel like it is a complicated and fine-tuned type of concept that can be mapped on multiple accounts
… my feeling is that requiring that all users have multiple profiles is unnecessarily complex for the general case&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, about a year later, they eventually resolved to use “Person,” with the caveat that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-05-04-minutes&quot;&gt;“person” need not be a “physical/real person”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see how complex this can get: standardizing online sociality in a set of vocabulary terms is no simple matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And I should note that the question of Person/Profile is still very much open, in spite of the SocialWG’s resolution. Consider Christine Lemmer-Webber’s current project &lt;a href=&quot;https://spritely.institute/goblins/&quot;&gt;Spritely Goblins&lt;/a&gt; and its emphasis on profiles.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;corporate-refusal&quot;&gt;Corporate Refusal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so to make a “social syntax,” one needs a vocabulary, a set of terms that describes what people do when they’re being social. Back in the mid-2010s, there was of course one key source for such knowledge: corporate social media sites, such as Facebook and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had APIs that no doubt did much of the work of describing the units of a social vocabulary, right? Indeed, back in 2009, Facebook even used the same &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20090430134956/http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;amp;articleId=9132182&amp;amp;intsrc=news_ts_head&quot;&gt;“activity streams” idea for its API&lt;/a&gt;, so clearly Facebook would get involved?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if the organization that &lt;em&gt;creates standards that power the World Wide Web&lt;/em&gt; – the W3C – is involved, then perhaps Twitter and other corporations should get involved, too, and have a hand in shaping resulting standards?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SocialWG minutes are marked by many instances of the group reaching out to Twitter, Facebook, Google, and other major corporations to get involved. Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-09-29-minutes&quot;&gt;but one of many&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;eprodrom: one thing i wanted to quickly point out is in previous converstaions we’ve talked about having some participation by non-members, inviting outside participation
… it may be good to think about what we want to do and so we can put out invitations to the public or specific developers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;tantek: i agree. i think the participation that we wanted to focus on previously is around implementers in particular
… specifically, implementers of social websites, popular existing social web services
… i have a bunch of contacts at twitter if they’d want to swing by for a bit, even informally&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2014-11-18-minutes&quot;&gt;studied the APIs of Twitter&lt;/a&gt; very early on, and so it makes sense they would want Twitter engineers involved in the SocialWG standard creation. Twitter never got involved, though. Later, after ActivityStreams 2.0 was finished, there was excitement that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2016-10-18-minutes&quot;&gt;Twitter might implement it&lt;/a&gt;. But Twitter never did this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading the minutes as a whole, over time, you can see the hope simply die that any corporate social media would get involved. Instead, at a certain point, not having corporate involvement became something of a virtue. Consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2016-06-06-minutes&quot;&gt;this statement from Tantek&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;tantek: we have seen with the examples of twitter and facebook there have been tons of business that have been built around either one of those, and ther ehas been a slow attrition of tightening apis, cutting off, etc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this prescient statement from Sandro Hawke (in the same meeting):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;sandro: all the media companies that are built around twitter don’t feel threatened or endangered by twitter
… if its started to be an unreliable or evil utility they would want some open replacement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this said, the corporate way of doing social was a constant touchpoint throughout the life of the SocialWG – the members constantly ask “how does Facebook do this?” or “How does Twitter describe that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;user-stories&quot;&gt;User Stories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if corporate social media is not involved, then how could the SocialWG specify a social syntax? The answer came in one of the most fascinating aspects of the SocialWG minutes: user stories (otherwise called “use cases”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea here is that they would write short stories about users doing social things, and then break those stories down into the terms they sought for their vocabulary. Here’s the first user story they adopted, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2005/Incubator/federatedsocialweb/wiki/SWAT0&quot;&gt;Social Web Acid Test&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;With his phone, Dave takes a photo of Tantek and uploads it using a service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Dave tags the photo with Tantek&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Tantek gets a notification on another service that he’s been tagged in a photo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Evan, who is subscribed to Dave, sees the photo on yet another service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Evan comments on the photo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;David and Tantek receive notifications that Evan has commented on the photo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/20/ActivityPub1.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, creating User Stories would be the responsibility of a sibling group, the Social Web Interest Group. That group would go on to produce about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/Social_API/User_stories&quot;&gt;90 user stories like the one above&lt;/a&gt;, but would &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-02-03-minutes&quot;&gt;ultimately settle on seven&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, user stories exemplify what I call &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Reverse-Engineering-Social-Media-Capitalism/dp/1439910359&quot;&gt;critical reverse engineering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; – taking apart existing practices, deriving abstractions from those practices, and then re-implementing those abstractions in a new (and better) way. Since corporate social media companies weren’t coming to the table to agree on a standard, the SocialWG simply told simple stories and developed their vocabulary (and Social API, the focus of a later post) from those stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;success&quot;&gt;Success!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While they weren’t able to attract representatives from corporate social media, the SocialWG did get their first win: ActivityStreams 2.0 drafts were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/2015-06-30-minutes&quot;&gt;published in June of 2015&lt;/a&gt; and the Candidate Recommendation appeared later that year. ActivityStreams 2.0 is now a key part of ActivityPub – but that’s a story for later.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="ActivityPub" /><summary type="html">NB: This is the second in a series of posts where I will share my notes on my readings of the minutes of the Social Web Working Group. The first one is here. Future posts to come. As I mentioned several months ago, my book about Mastodon and the rest of the fediverse can’t be complete without a deep understanding of ActivityPub, the protocol that powers the fediverse. ActivityPub itself is getting a bit of love in the press (see this Verge article for an example). And to understand ActivityPub, we have to look at the group that created it, the W3C’s Social Web Working Group, or SocialWG for short. They posted their meeting minutes on the Web and I have read all of them. In the previous post on the SocialWG minutes, I focused on the very early years, 2014 to 2015, finding that the period was dominated by organizational issues – how to meet, how to make decisions, and so on. In this section, I will cover the development of ActivityStreams 2.0, the first goal of the SocialWG charter.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AoIR Social’s Code of Conduct</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/03/15/AOIRsocialCOC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AoIR Social’s Code of Conduct" /><published>2023-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/03/15/AOIRsocialCOC</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/03/15/AOIRsocialCOC.html">&lt;p&gt;So, as I noted in the &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/03/03/AOIR-social.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, AoIR.social is &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social&quot;&gt;live&lt;/a&gt;! It’s in beta testing, so to speak, as we bring on board moderators to learn the system before rolling out to the Association of Internet Researchers membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And moderators can’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1plPyJdXKIY&quot;&gt;mount up&lt;/a&gt; and moderate without a Code of Conduct. Along with Sarah Roberts and Aram Sinnreich, we drafted a COC based on the successful one found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.social&quot;&gt;scholar.social&lt;/a&gt;. We posted it to AoIR.social this week, and the moderators are weighing in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is meant to document this process, not just for posterity, but also for the Fediverse writ large. Below, I’ll post the full AoIR.social COC and document the feedback the moderators are giving it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-coc-so-far&quot;&gt;The COC, So Far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Click the little arrow to see the AoIR.social Code of Conduct, March 2023&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; Code of Conduct&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;NB: This is a DRAFT Code of Conduct, based in part on the Code of Conduct from scholar.social. As of March 2023, it is being reviewed by volunteer moderators.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an instance for current members of the Association of Internet Researchers. Real names and credentials are only recommended if you plan to use your account on this instance for networking purposes; they are absolutely not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Encouraged uses of AoIR.Social&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brag about your publications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share references and resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network with other AoIR members&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put it on the last slide of your conference presentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recruit participants for academic surveys—formal, IRB-approved ones or even informal ones (just make sure to use content warnings so that others can consent and don&apos;t get too obnoxious about it; see below for more about research on AoIR.social&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Satire and activism are welcome here, but they must make a good-faith effort to punch up. (&quot;Punching up&quot;: making jokes or criticism at the expense of those with more power, higher status or greater privilege.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are an AoIR member in good standing, and you are willing to engage with others respectfully, and you will respect our community&apos;s efforts to make this a safe space for queer, BIPOC, and other structurally disadvantaged people, you are absolutely welcome here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your AoIR membership has lapsed for longer than 2 years, you will be contacted about renewing your membership. If you choose not to renew, you will have 60 days to download your data. You may move your data to another Mastodon instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Introduce yourself!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After signing up, post a message to the Local Timeline telling us who you are, what your academic interests are, and helping us to get to know you better. We have set the administrative account to automatically boost public posts tagged with #introductions. (But if you abuse this by using it for anything else, we will close your account without warning.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Content Warnings (CW&apos;s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please add CW&apos;s (content warnings) that are accurate and descriptive enough to enable reader consent to the following types of posts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt;strong language,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   selfies,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   current events (includes: US or non-US, local, national, international, and should be applied regardless of whether sources are academic or non-partisan), high-conflict or otherwise exhausting issues of popular debate (e.g. climate change, GMO&apos;s, privacy issues, elections, etc.),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   mentions of death or violence,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   photographs or illustrations of insects, genitals, wounds (even if they come from a scientific source)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   references or links to Facebook/Twitter/other big tech companies,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   spoilers of popular and recent TV shows or other media, ASCII art (this one is important to ensure that someone using a screen reader doesn&apos;t have to listen to an attempt to read out a bunch of obscure symbols)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   stresses particular to academia such as grades, exams, thesis progress, academic job market prospects, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   anything else where another user might want to decide for themselves whether or when they want to interact with your post.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a setting in your preferences to open all posts with Content Warnings automatically, if you don&apos;t want to click through each one.
Image descriptions (alt-text)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an expectation of this instance that you add accurate descriptions to all images and video that you post to aid in accessibility. (A description like &quot;image.jpg&quot; that does not aid in accessibility would not meet this expectation.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you post an image of a screenshot of text, it is an expectation of this instance that you transcribe the text in the image description. Here’s a guide on how and why to supply alt-text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Unwelcome conduct on AoIR.Social&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following will result in: a warning from the admin or having offending posts deleted, possibly without prior notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt; Providing unsolicited advice to strangers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Inappropriate un-CW&apos;d posts on the Local Timeline (see above for CW policies)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Posts with un-described images or video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Shortened links, e.g. bit.ly, t.ly, tinyurl.com, goo.gl, ift.tt, lnkd.in, is.gd or t.co (These are considered malicious because link-shorteners track users without their consent and obscure the destination address, which also prevents users from being able to decide whether they want to visit the link beforehand)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Advertisement or apologia for cryptocurrencies, NFT&apos;s, or multi-level marketing schemes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Unrequested solicitations to join religious, political, or other ideologically-defined organizations&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exceptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DOI links (e.g. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.k959) are allowed but the post must accurately describe the title/author/journal to allow the reader to decide for themselves whether they would like to follow the link. (In cases of very long titles, you may truncate it, and in cases of long author lists, &quot;First-Author et al&quot; will do.) Posts with DOI links where the target of the link is not described, or not described sufficiently, may be deleted without warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Things that will get your account closed, possibly without warning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;li&gt;   Racism, sexism, homophobia, transphobia, casteism, able-ism, etc. (will result in a permanent ban, you may not receive a prior warning)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Serious dishonesty that is hurtful to others (e.g. falsely representing oneself as a member of a minority; services offering to write academic papers to help students cheat; vaccine denialism; predatory conferences or journals; overt pseudoscience such as flat-earther-ism etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Anything that could be described as &quot;spam&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Impersonating other people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Harassment of any kind, including condemnations of individuals or institutions based on location, nationality, class, caste, religion, ethnicity, age, gender, or sexual identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   No bots and no &quot;institutional&quot; accounts operated by non-members please; AoIR.social is for people. The obvious exception is that the AoIR organization itself will post official communications here. Any official communications will be marked as such.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;   Accounts that automatically repeat a Twitter account, RSS feed, etc. must post to AoIR.social as Unlisted, not Public&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Regarding attempts to abuse these anti-abuse tools and policies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not attempt to weaponize our Community Standards or anti-abuse tools/policies against marginalized groups such as people of colour, women or queer people. Users of AoIR.social are expected to have the literacy to understand that &quot;reverse discrimination&quot; is not real, and so attempts to re-centre discussions of marginalized people around the feelings of the privileged will be taken as manipulative behaviour undertaken deliberately in bad-faith. (E.g. white people should not demand that people of colour put CW&apos;s on every discussion of race). Furthermore, the abuse of content moderation tools for targeted efforts to silence, smear, or otherwise harass any individual account holder, for any reason, will not be tolerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Use of AoIR.Social for research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers who wish to study AoIR.social or our users by collecting data using the API or through any other means that does not involve an &quot;opt-in&quot; from individual users are required to submit their protocol, analysis plan and all relevant ethics approval documentation from their institutional review board or departmental internal review documentation by email to the AoIR Fediverse admin account. You may also be required to submit code you plan to execute so that it can be tested to ensure it does not degrade the quality of service to other users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not apply to, e.g. surveys circulated on AoIR.social that individual users can consent to participating in. This does apply to database scraping software, or any means of recording user activity where our users might be surprised that they were included afterward, because they were not given a chance to consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AoIR is well known for being the leading organization developing ethical online research. Ethical research on this instance (and much of the fediverse) should be sensitive to the privacy expectations of its members. Many people came to the fediverse in order to avoid being included in unethical social media research, and so we place a higher value on conducting research on human subjects with informed consent than most other social media, in order to maintain high ethical standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the admin&apos;s discretion, you may be asked to submit your research protocol, and the institution that is providing ethical review, even in the case that it is an opt-in survey. Failure to disclose your research plan may result in closure of your account, or having your network banned from our service.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-feedback-so-far&quot;&gt;The Feedback, So Far&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;NB: I will provide attribution when I have the permission of the author. I’ll also add more as I observe it.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggestions coming from: Nancy Baym, Jean Burgess, Charlotte Spencer-Smith, Tama Leaver, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mission statement: we should include a bit more about what this server is about. Why have we set it up? What is it for?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similarly, another member noted that we should be clearer that socializing – in addition to being professional – is encouraged (indeed, that the very personal/professional divide in the academy needs to be troubled)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explanation for each section: for example, a bit more explaining why we ask for CWs. This would be good for new Mastodon members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moderation commitments: how many moderators do we have? What’s the typical turnaround for responding to issues?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bit more clarity about what we mean about no crypto-shilling, especially when we have scholars who &lt;em&gt;study&lt;/em&gt; cryptcurrencies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bit of clarity about sexual expression, e.g., discussions of sex work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarifying why a CW on a selfie is needed (it’s about eye contact, not about self-portraiture as such)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarification about blocklists and moderation speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Association of Internet Researchers" /><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="goal 1" /><summary type="html">So, as I noted in the last post, AoIR.social is live! It’s in beta testing, so to speak, as we bring on board moderators to learn the system before rolling out to the Association of Internet Researchers membership. And moderators can’t mount up and moderate without a Code of Conduct. Along with Sarah Roberts and Aram Sinnreich, we drafted a COC based on the successful one found at scholar.social. We posted it to AoIR.social this week, and the moderators are weighing in. This post is meant to document this process, not just for posterity, but also for the Fediverse writ large. Below, I’ll post the full AoIR.social COC and document the feedback the moderators are giving it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AOIR.social!</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/03/03/AOIR-social.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AOIR.social!" /><published>2023-03-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/03/03/AOIR%20social</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/03/03/AOIR-social.html">&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/12/11/AOIR-social.html&quot;&gt;wrote about the possibility of the Association on Internet Researchers running their own Mastodon instance&lt;/a&gt;. I discussed the major concerns the organization had about running such an instance, and the direction the project is heading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/aoir.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Association of Internet Researchers Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to announce that AOIR.social is going to happen. In fact, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social&quot;&gt;it’s live right now&lt;/a&gt;, but we’re not actively signing up AOIR members just yet. First, we’re going to let our volunteer moderators join to learn the tooling (and the tooting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have to do some work on preemptively blocking instances that don’t share our values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and we have to finalize our Code of Conduct (both for the Mastodon instance and for the organization as a whole).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to investigate signing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://joinmastodon.org/covenant&quot;&gt;Mastodon Server Covenant&lt;/a&gt;. (I want this to be a respectable part of the fediverse, after all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s probably more that I’m not thinking about, but in any case… it’s happening, people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, lots to do! Stay tuned, AOIRfriends!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Association of Internet Researchers" /><category term="Mastodon" /><summary type="html">A few months ago, I wrote about the possibility of the Association on Internet Researchers running their own Mastodon instance. I discussed the major concerns the organization had about running such an instance, and the direction the project is heading. I’m excited to announce that AOIR.social is going to happen. In fact, it’s live right now, but we’re not actively signing up AOIR members just yet. First, we’re going to let our volunteer moderators join to learn the tooling (and the tooting). And I have to do some work on preemptively blocking instances that don’t share our values. Oh, and we have to finalize our Code of Conduct (both for the Mastodon instance and for the organization as a whole). And I want to investigate signing the Mastodon Server Covenant. (I want this to be a respectable part of the fediverse, after all). There’s probably more that I’m not thinking about, but in any case… it’s happening, people! So, lots to do! Stay tuned, AOIRfriends!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bumps, Slumps and the Killer Hype Cycle</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bumps, Slumps and the Killer Hype Cycle" /><published>2023-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump.html">&lt;p&gt;Ok, you all probably remember last fall, when the Muskening happened. When Mastodon saw a massive influx of new members. When Mastodon admins were struggling to keep up with the influx but ultimately showed that the network can, in fact, scale up. It was, in my view, the biggest stress on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/&quot;&gt;ActivityPub&lt;/a&gt; protocol – and ActivityPub kicked ass. Millions of people signed up for Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the titular Mastodon “bump.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’ve published academic articles on Mastodon, during that Eternal Muskvember, I was approached by a lot of journalists (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/twitter-users-mastodon-meltdown/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rnz.co.nz/national/programmes/ninetonoon/audio/2018866818/twitter-users-seek-alternative-to-musk-run-platform&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketplace.org/shows/make-me-smart/unpacking-mastodon/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for example) to talk about Mastodon, answering questions ranging from “what is it?” to “will it replace Twitter?” It was an exciting and sometimes exasperating time. I basically told myself, “Self, this sort of media attention is rare. Enjoy it, but know that it won’t last.” And indeed, a few weeks later, the story died down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also told myself to expect the inevitable follow-up. That’s what I’m writing about here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many readers of this blog are likely aware, after the new year, Mastodon’s active user base dropped off. As with every wave of social media movement from platform to platform, some percentage of people just don’t stick with the new site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s the titular Mastodon “slump.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, I got an interview request from WIRED’s Amanda Hoover, who was working on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/the-mastodon-bump-is-now-a-slump/amp&quot;&gt;a story&lt;/a&gt; about how Mastodon’s drop in active users signaled that it had failed in its mission to replace Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, before I go any further I will say Hoover’s reporting on Mastodon has been excellent. She asks great questions, and she does more than just interview Eugen Rochko – she talks to instance admins, lawyers, and academics like myself. And, in fact, the article I’m going to critique is quite good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am going to use her latest WIRED article to illustrate an all-too-common trope in reporting on alternative social media: it’s what I call “The Killer Hype Cycle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-killer-hype-cycle&quot;&gt;The Killer Hype Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here’s the Killer Hype Cycle, as a couple colleagues and I describe it in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/objects/hc:29856/datastreams/CONTENT/content&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Media and Society&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Killer Hype Cycles are often seen in tech reporting on alternatives to mainstream social media platforms, such as Facebook and Twitter. The Cycle goes like this: first, a journalist notices a fledgling alternative social media system. Looking for a click-worthy angle, the journalist declares it the next ‘Facebook Killer’ or ‘Twitter
Killer,’ arguing that within months, the corporate social media giant will be ‘killed’ because its users will leave en masse for the new alternative. Later, when someone notices that Facebook or Twitter is still active despite the presence of the ‘Killer,’ another journalist (or even the original journalist) will declare the alternative a ‘failure’ or simply ‘dead,’ mainly because it did not attract hundreds of millions of new users in a matter of weeks. The cycle appears to end—that is, until another alternative is noticed by a tech reporter, and the cycle is repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;em&gt;New Media and Society&lt;/em&gt; article provides citations, but here I’ll quickly cover some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2010, when diaspora* was getting attention, journalists declared it to be a “Facebook killer,” and soon after, declared it to be a failure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2014, ello was dubbed a Facebook killer, and then weeks later it was called a failure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And in 2017, the same happened to… Mastodon, which was dubbed a “Twitter Killer” only to be written off for dead that same year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see the same thing over the past few months with Mastodon coverage. In the fall, journalists asked me if Mastodon will replace Twitter. My typical reply was something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve seen massive discontent over corporate social media many times (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2014/06/everything-we-know-about-facebooks-secret-mood-manipulation-experiment/373648/&quot;&gt;Emotional Contagion&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/news/series/cambridge-analytica-files&quot;&gt;Cambridge Analytica&lt;/a&gt;) and somehow people keep using Facebook and Twitter et al. So, probably not, although if Twitter went away, I’d be fine with it. Regardless, what Mastodon and its kin offer is an alternative to corporate social media for those of us concerned about surveillance, disinformation, and harassment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, no matter what I said, the very emphasis on “will it replace Twitter?” is not too far off of “will it kill Twitter?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to last week, and WIRED’s Hoover asked me if I was concerned about the dropoff in Mastodon active users. I didn’t write down my exact reply, but I said something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No, because these waves come and go, and while some percentage of new users might stop using Mastodon, Mastodon’s overall membership has gone up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also stressed the fact that the real lesson of the Fall of 2022 was that ActivityPub succeeded in scaling up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/the-mastodon-bump-is-now-a-slump/&quot;&gt;resulting article&lt;/a&gt; is actually quite good. I commend Hoover for the article because it covered things like emerging questions about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2022/12/user-generated-content-and-fediverse-legal-primer&quot;&gt;legal liability&lt;/a&gt; and the fact that the network did scale and because she interviewed a Mastodon admin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it does however imply that Mastodon is somehow failing because of the “slump.” It implies that Mastodon is dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know this because just a day after it came out, &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; reporter called to ask about Mastodon’s impending demise – and that reporter cited Hoover’s WIRED article.
That second reporter was working on a story about… new and emerging alternatives to corporate social media. And they were starting with the premise that Mastodon failed and it was time to find something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, that reporter was looking for the next Killer Hype Cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-do-about-this-trope&quot;&gt;What to do about this trope?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d recommend to tech journalists covering alternative social media to push past the “Killer” trope and consider each alternative on its own terms, rather than strictly in opposition to a corporate counterpart. Yes, some comparison is inevitable – after all, we understand “alternative” in relation to a “mainstream.” But these are not 1:1 replacements – they have their own logics and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, part of the appeal of the alternatives is the refusal of the growth logics of corporate social media. Mastodon admins, for example, don’t really want to run instances on the scale of Twitter. They want small instances that are more easily moderated at a human scale. Because of this, growth of Mastodon as a whole depends on the establishment of many new instances, which takes time and effort. As I say over and over, it’s not a matter of signing up at a central site, like Twitter.com. This is purposeful building of democratic social media, and growth is not always the best thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reporting in this space needs to focus on these nuances and eliminate the oversimplification “growth always equals good.” That’s hard to do when we’re conditioned by 20 years of corporate, venture capital, Silicon Valley thinking, but there is a world beyond the Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the rest of us in Mastodon and across the fediverse, I probably don’t need to say this, but I will, anyway: don’t be fazed. Keep on doing what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La lucha sigue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">Ok, you all probably remember last fall, when the Muskening happened. When Mastodon saw a massive influx of new members. When Mastodon admins were struggling to keep up with the influx but ultimately showed that the network can, in fact, scale up. It was, in my view, the biggest stress on the ActivityPub protocol – and ActivityPub kicked ass. Millions of people signed up for Mastodon. That’s the titular Mastodon “bump.” Since I’ve published academic articles on Mastodon, during that Eternal Muskvember, I was approached by a lot of journalists (here, here, and here, for example) to talk about Mastodon, answering questions ranging from “what is it?” to “will it replace Twitter?” It was an exciting and sometimes exasperating time. I basically told myself, “Self, this sort of media attention is rare. Enjoy it, but know that it won’t last.” And indeed, a few weeks later, the story died down. I also told myself to expect the inevitable follow-up. That’s what I’m writing about here. As many readers of this blog are likely aware, after the new year, Mastodon’s active user base dropped off. As with every wave of social media movement from platform to platform, some percentage of people just don’t stick with the new site. There’s the titular Mastodon “slump.” Last week, I got an interview request from WIRED’s Amanda Hoover, who was working on a story about how Mastodon’s drop in active users signaled that it had failed in its mission to replace Twitter. Now, before I go any further I will say Hoover’s reporting on Mastodon has been excellent. She asks great questions, and she does more than just interview Eugen Rochko – she talks to instance admins, lawyers, and academics like myself. And, in fact, the article I’m going to critique is quite good. But I am going to use her latest WIRED article to illustrate an all-too-common trope in reporting on alternative social media: it’s what I call “The Killer Hype Cycle.”</summary></entry></feed>