<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-06T14:33:48-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">ASM Update: Can this platform survive?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/06/survive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update: Can this platform survive?" /><published>2024-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/06/survive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/06/survive.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a pretty packed week, between the end of the semester, my participation in a small conference, and a sick kiddo at home. So this week’s ASM update is a short one.</p>

<p>Along with some colleagues at American University, I have a new publication out.</p>

<h2 id="can-this-platform-survive-governance-challenges-for-the-fediverse">Can This Platform Survive? Governance Challenges for the Fediverse</h2>

<p>This is a new paper from the <em><a href="https://ijoc.org/index.php/ijoc/article/view/22254">International Journal of Communication</a>,</em> written by Thomas Struett, Aram Sinnreich, Patricia Aufderheide, and myself.</p>

<p>Here’s the abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the wake of recent crises at commercial social media platforms like Twitter and Reddit, the “fediverse” has gained adoption and visibility as a noncommercial alternative for individuals, communities, and institutions to develop channels of public communication, dialogue, and debate. In this article, we draw on illustrative examples from the history of digital civic discourse and identify 6 ways in which history shows us how the potential benefits of the fediverse are at risk of subversion. We discuss several potential threats to these spaces of civil discourse, including challenges inherent to distributed governance, commercial platform capture, inclusive access, moderation at scale, reputational assaults by commercial competitors, and the neoliberal technoromanticism familiar from previous digital innovations. These threats must be addressed collectively and proactively by key fediverse stakeholders in an ecology whose ruling values are noncommercialism, decentralization, open source, free association, and wariness of traditional governance.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Academic publishing is slow. We worked this up over a year ago. It’s interesting to see what parts of the paper hold up – frankly, I think all of our challenges are still at play.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="publications" /><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been a pretty packed week, between the end of the semester, my participation in a small conference, and a sick kiddo at home. So this week’s ASM update is a short one. Along with some colleagues at American University, I have a new publication out. Can This Platform Survive? Governance Challenges for the Fediverse This is a new paper from the International Journal of Communication, written by Thomas Struett, Aram Sinnreich, Patricia Aufderheide, and myself. Here’s the abstract: In the wake of recent crises at commercial social media platforms like Twitter and Reddit, the “fediverse” has gained adoption and visibility as a noncommercial alternative for individuals, communities, and institutions to develop channels of public communication, dialogue, and debate. In this article, we draw on illustrative examples from the history of digital civic discourse and identify 6 ways in which history shows us how the potential benefits of the fediverse are at risk of subversion. We discuss several potential threats to these spaces of civil discourse, including challenges inherent to distributed governance, commercial platform capture, inclusive access, moderation at scale, reputational assaults by commercial competitors, and the neoliberal technoromanticism familiar from previous digital innovations. These threats must be addressed collectively and proactively by key fediverse stakeholders in an ecology whose ruling values are noncommercialism, decentralization, open source, free association, and wariness of traditional governance. Academic publishing is slow. We worked this up over a year ago. It’s interesting to see what parts of the paper hold up – frankly, I think all of our challenges are still at play.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marp!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/01/marp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marp!" /><published>2024-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/01/marp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/01/marp.html"><![CDATA[<p>As avid readers of my blog know, I am livin’ the <a href="/tags/fald.html">FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream</a>: I use FOSS tools to do my academic work. I use Nextcloud to manage files and <a href="/2021/09/25/Appointments.html">handle appointments</a>, Zotero and Zettlr to take notes, and LibreOffice Writer to write books and articles. This blog runs on Jekyll. I love it all!</p>

<p>But there has been one part of the Lifestyle that has consistently been a disappointment: <a href="https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/impress/">LibreOffice Impress</a>, the presentation software. While I use Writer all the time and enjoy doing so, Impress has always bothered me. But I’m not one to complain too much, since LibreOffice software is provided free-of-charge and with a FOSS license. I’ve soldiered on with it to make presentations for conferences and class teaching.</p>

<p>But that might change. <a href="https://marp.app/">Marp</a> – the Markdown Presentation Ecosystem – is poised to become a key part of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream. If you’re familiar with Markdown, Marp is a really awesome tool.
<!-- more --></p>

<h2 id="thank-you-linux-matters">Thank you, Linux Matters</h2>
<p>I learned about Marp from the <a href="https://linuxmatters.sh/43/"><em>Linux Matters</em> podcast</a>. Like any good podcast episode, their discussion of Marp made me drop everything to learn more. As Mark on <em>Linux Matters</em> explained, Marp allows for presentations to be built very quickly using Markdown. Since I use Markdown regularly to write up notes, particularly for class lectures, I was intrigued.</p>

<p>And when I started experimenting with Marp, I think Mark might have undersold it a bit!</p>

<h2 id="markdown-its-that-easy">Markdown: It’s That Easy</h2>
<p>So, let’s make a slide. Instead of firing up LibreOffice Impress, though, I just open a text editor a create a Markdown (.md) file.</p>

<p>First, I add “frontmatter,” which tells the system how to handle the file:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
marp: true
---
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>(You can do more with it than that, but we’ll keep it simple).</p>

<p>Next, I start adding slides:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
marp: true
---
# Slide Title

Slide Text
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>It’s that easy.</p>

<p>That sort of thing <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#3">looks like this</a>.</p>

<p>Let’s add another slide, this time with a list. Lists are handled in the Markdown way:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
marp: true
---
# Slide Title
Slide Text

---
# Slide with List
- List item 1
- List item 2
- List item 3
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here’s an <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#4">example of what that looks like</a>.</p>

<p>Of course, people often use more than just text in slides. I can add images, as well. Marp uses a syntax like this:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>![command](imagefile.jpg)
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Where “command” handles stuff like size, whether the image is in the background, opacity or the like. So a three-slide presentation with an image might look like this:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
marp: true
---
# Slide Title
Slide Text

---
# Slide with List
- List item 1
- List item 2
- List item 3

---
![command](imagefile.jpg)
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>However, as you’ll see, I prefer to do things with HTML, specifically the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;figure&gt;</code> semantic tag, and style with CSS.</p>

<h2 id="css-zen-presentations">CSS Zen Presentations</h2>
<p>I love CSS. It blew me away when I saw the <a href="https://csszengarden.com/">CSS Zen Garden</a>, which was launched in 2003 to promote the full separation of content and presentation. I am no designer – don’t ask me to come up with color schemes! But I did take the CSS Zen Garden idea and apply it to <a href="https://www.robertwgehl.org">my website</a>, where you can choose your style if you view it on a laptop/tablet.</p>

<p>Add in <a href="https://sass-lang.com/">SASS</a>, which allows for variables, and CSS is a really powerful tool.</p>

<p>So when I learned Marp uses CSS – with some SASS-like aspects – to handle the design of slides, I knew I would like it.</p>

<p>Marp comes with some default themes, but I was keen to build my own. It turns out that all I had to do was write a CSS file and point the Marp command line to it via a terminal:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>marp -w --theme ./CSS/custom.scss testPresentation.md
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here’s a tip for those of you wanting to style via CSS: Marp uses the HTML semantic tag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;section&gt;</code> for each slide. To customize the whole presentation, style <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;section&gt;</code>, rather than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;body&gt;</code>, and you’re good to go: the whole presentation will be formatted.</p>

<p>And what about specific slides? Marp uses an HTML-style comment you can add to Markdown: adding <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;!-- _class: CLASSNAME --&gt;</code> to the start of the specific slide adds a class that can be targeted. For example, I use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;!-- _class: title --&gt;</code> on title slides. <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#1">Here’s how that looks</a>.</p>

<h2 id="avoiding-death-by-powerpoint-the-css-way">Avoiding Death by Powerpoint the CSS way</h2>

<p>When I present, I do my best to avoid <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Iwpi1Lm6dFo">death by Powerpoint</a>. I use a lot of slides with minimal objects on a dark background.</p>

<p>Of course, with CSS, backgrounds are fully under my control. And since Marp allows SASS-like variables, I could just set a global value for the background (as well as other elements) in my custom.scss file:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>:root {
  font-family: "Cantarell Light", sans-serif;
  --text-color: #999999;
  --bg-color: #000;
  --standard-margin: 10%;
  --shadow: 20px 10px 10px #121212;
}
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here you’ll see I lazily set it to black. I will likely choose some other verydark color, but for now that will do. (And, if I want to change it, I just have to adjust that one value. That’s it!)</p>

<p>Avoiding Death by Powerpoint means I tend to use a lot of single images. Wth two little bits – some Markdown/HTML and some CSS – I can drop in images with formatting.</p>

<p>Here’s the example Markdown:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;!-- _class: one-column --&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="images/stage.jpg" alt="a picture of a theater stage"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A theater stage &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Notice I’ve moved away from the simpler <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">![command](image.jpg)</code> structure to an HTML5 semantic markup, complete with alt text and caption. It’s a bit more typing (or copypasting) but it will be worth it. Notice also the class, “one-column.”</p>

<p>Now here’s some corresponding CSS:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>section.one-column figure {
  float: left;
  width: 90%;
  margin-left:8%;
  margin-top: 4%;
}

img {
  width: 96%;
  float: left;
  z-index:-1;
}

figcaption {
  margin-top: -8%;
  font-size: 200%;
  width: 80%;
  line-height: 200%;
  float: left;
  text-align: center;
  background-color:var(--bg-color);
  opacity: .8;
  z-index:1;
}
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The result can <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#6">be seen here</a>. Here’s a screenshot, too:</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/presentationExample.png" alt="a screenshot of an example presentation slide. It's a picture of the woods on a black background." />
  <figcaption>A screenshot of the slide</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="i-can-make-it-do-things-libreoffice-impress-never-could">I can make it do things LibreOffice Impress never could</h2>

<p>Much like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lxNYAe85L20">Kurt with his magazines</a>, with CSS I can make presentations do whatever I like. Including something that has eluded me in LibreOffice Impress for years: captions for images. That picture of the woods above includes a caption, styled with CSS.</p>

<p>CSS has a lot of power, and I’m only scratching the surface of what could be done. Once my CSS template is complete, all I have to do from here on out is edit Markdown files. This can work for academic presentations as well as for class lectures (which I often base off Markdown files edited in Zettlr.)</p>

<h2 id="dont-forget-about-html">Don’t forget about HTML</h2>

<p>In the above example, I link to a <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#6">specific slide in the presentation.</a>. I can link to any point of the presentation. On the web. In beautiful HTML, with alt text for images.</p>

<p>This is so cool!</p>

<p>All I have to do is run a terminal command with marp-cli:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>marp -w --theme ./CSS/custom.scss testPresentation.md
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Marp autogenerates an HTML file with CSS included. I move that to a server and boom! The presentation is online. This is so cool!</p>

<p>And I’ve taken a look – it looks very similar across devices. Responsive!</p>

<p>Now, instead of futzing with a LibreOffice .OPD file (or worse, so much worse, a .PPTX file), I can just post my presentations to the web and run them from there. It includes a presentation view, which shows notes that I put in the corresponding Markdown file within HTML comments.</p>

<p>Or, if I want to run it off my local machine, I can just present a local HTML file.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h2>

<p>I’m going to do it: I’m going all-on on Marp for a while. If things go poorly, I’ll update this blog accordingly. But right now, I suspect Marp is a future fixture of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="FALD" /><category term="Marp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As avid readers of my blog know, I am livin’ the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream: I use FOSS tools to do my academic work. I use Nextcloud to manage files and handle appointments, Zotero and Zettlr to take notes, and LibreOffice Writer to write books and articles. This blog runs on Jekyll. I love it all! But there has been one part of the Lifestyle that has consistently been a disappointment: LibreOffice Impress, the presentation software. While I use Writer all the time and enjoy doing so, Impress has always bothered me. But I’m not one to complain too much, since LibreOffice software is provided free-of-charge and with a FOSS license. I’ve soldiered on with it to make presentations for conferences and class teaching. But that might change. Marp – the Markdown Presentation Ecosystem – is poised to become a key part of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream. If you’re familiar with Markdown, Marp is a really awesome tool.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM update: libraries, libraries everywhere</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/29/libraries.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM update: libraries, libraries everywhere" /><published>2024-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/29/libraries</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/29/libraries.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a simple, yet deep ASM update for this week. Last week, I posted about some <a href="/2024/11/22/ASMupdateResearch.html">recent research</a> in the realm of alternative social media. I also drew attention to the bibliography I maintain <a href="/bib.html">here on this blog</a>. In response to that post, folks on the fediverse alerted me to other bibliographic projects collecting research in related ideas. Here I want to highlight two of them.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="fediverse-observatory">Fediverse Observatory</h2>

<p>This is a <a href="https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861035/fediverse_observatory/items/LFCK293Q/library">Zotero Library</a> with dozens of entries, some dating back to 2005. As the name implies, much of it focuses on the fediverse, but there are sub-libraries focusing on topics like “migration” across social media, social media fatigue, and Musk and Threads.</p>

<h2 id="investigación-sobre-el-fediverso">Investigación sobre el Fediverso</h2>

<p>This is a <a href="https://www.pedrolr.es/research/infonomy2024/fediverseresearch.html">library</a> from Pedro Lázaro Rodríguez based in part on the citations from a <a href="https://infonomy.scimagoepi.com/index.php/infonomy/article/view/34">fediverse research paper</a> published in <em>Infonomy</em> 2024. It’s divided into two sections, one focusing on research that has emerged since the <em>Infonomy</em> paper, and the second with the original reference material for that paper.</p>

<h2 id="libraries">Libraries!</h2>

<p>While this ASM update is just these two links, as you can see, this area of research is rapidly growing. I am not going to lie: I will gleefully mine these libraries for use in my own. For new researchers and grad students, there is a wealth of materials out there to gain insights into the world of alternative social media. It’s such an exciting time!</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="Alternative Social Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s a simple, yet deep ASM update for this week. Last week, I posted about some recent research in the realm of alternative social media. I also drew attention to the bibliography I maintain here on this blog. In response to that post, folks on the fediverse alerted me to other bibliographic projects collecting research in related ideas. Here I want to highlight two of them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Update: New Research Edition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/22/ASMupdateResearch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update: New Research Edition" /><published>2024-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/22/ASMupdateResearch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/22/ASMupdateResearch.html"><![CDATA[<p>Bluesky continues to blow up. I hear about it everywhere. It’s so backed up the <a href="https://github.com/snarfed/bridgy-fed/issues/1520">Brid.gy system has slowed to a crawl</a>.</p>

<p>But instead of focusing yet again on Bluesky, this week I wanted to do something that is long overdue: I want to draw your attention to some new research in alternative social media. You can find these works in the <a href="/bib.html">bibliography page</a> of this blog, or reach out to me if you want to join the corresponding Zotero library.</p>

<p>Here will highlight some new papers, mostly focusing on Mastodon (and to a lesser extent the rest of the fediverse). As you will see, there’s a variety of concerns: archiving and curation, moderation, and news sharing. Links are in the titles below.</p>

<p>Also, I am now building an email listserv focused on academic research on alternative social media (broadly conceived). Are you an academic who wants to join the list? We have 50 colleagues there now! If you want to join, <a href="https://www.robertwgehl.org/contact.php">contact me</a> (preferably with a university email address) and give me some background info and I can add you to the group.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="frost-arnold-karen-2024-beyond-corporate-social-media-platforms-the-epistemic-promises-and-perils-of-alternative-social-media-topoi-october-httpsdoiorg101007s11245-024-10102-2">Frost-Arnold, Karen. 2024. “<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11245-024-10102-2">Beyond Corporate Social Media Platforms: The Epistemic Promises and Perils of Alternative Social Media</a>.” <em>Topoi</em>, October. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11245-024-10102-2.</h2>

<p>ABSTRACT: “In recent years, we have witnessed increased interest in alternatives to the dominant corporate social media sites, such as Facebook, Twitter (now X), and TikTok. Tired of disinformation, harassment, privacy violations, and the general degradation of platforms, users and technologists have looked for non-corporate alternatives. Not-for-profit social media platforms emerging from free/libre and open-source software (FLOSS) communities based on non-centralized infrastructure have emerged as promising alternatives. For applied epistemology of the internet, these alternative social media platforms present an opportunity to study different ways of producing knowledge together online. This paper evaluates the epistemic potential for such alternative, non-corporate social media. I present an epistemological framework for analyzing the epistemic promises and perils of alternative social media. Then I apply this framework to the case of Mastodon, a federated, open-source microblogging platform. Mastodon’s structure and culture of openness present opportunities to avoid many of the epistemic perils of biased and untrustworthy large corporate platforms. However, Mastodon’s risks include techno-elitism, white ignorance, and isolated, epistemically toxic communities.”</p>

<h2 id="lister-pen-2024-creating-a-city-for-all-of-us-the-possible-role-of-the-fediverse-in-archiving-civic-urban-memory-digital-society-3-3-53-httpsdoiorg101007s44206-024-00137-8-open-access">Lister, Pen. 2024. “<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s44206-024-00137-8">Creating a City for All of Us: The Possible Role of the Fediverse in Archiving Civic Urban Memory</a>.” Digital Society 3 (3): 53. https://doi.org/10.1007/s44206-024-00137-8. OPEN ACCESS</h2>

<p>ABSTRACT: “This paper attempts to build a case for adopting the model of the Fediverse to archive digital citizen-generated urban memory. Examining literature from several relevant fields of debate acts as a pragmatic foundation for reasoning to then outline potential core technical functionality for provision of such an archive, using the Mastodon app as an example. This ‘civic urban memory’ archive is considered as open, curated by citizens themselves and owned by them through civic public ownership in a context of technological sovereignty. Reflecting on issues of citizen self curated and moderated memory collection archives, and the potential for opt-in or anonymous archive posting may offer some mechanisms for fair and open curation, moderation and privacy protection in such archives. Conceptual backdrop for a civic urban memory archive is placed in current debates concerning civic technological platforms acting as a digital public good in a context of a techno-social contract for learning, with a co-constructed shared civic urban memory forming part of open incidental lifelong learning in a future learning city.”</p>

<h2 id="quian-alberto-xosé-lópez-garcía-and-xosé-soengas-pérez-2024-periodismo-y-redes-sociales-alternativas-del-fediverso-estudio-de-la-presencia-de-medios-nativos-digitales-y-matriciales-en-mastodon-revista-latina-de-comunicación-social-no-83-september-140-httpsdoiorg104185rlcs-2025-2338">Quian, Alberto, Xosé López-García, and Xosé Soengas-Pérez. 2024. “<a href="https://nuevaepoca.revistalatinacs.org/index.php/revista/article/view/2338">Periodismo y Redes Sociales Alternativas Del Fediverso: Estudio de La Presencia de Medios Nativos Digitales y Matriciales En Mastodon</a>.” Revista Latina de Comunicación Social, no. 83 (September), 1–40. https://doi.org/10.4185/rlcs-2025-2338.</h2>

<p>ABSTRACT: “Introducción: Se analiza la presencia de periódicos en Mastodon, la plataforma social más popular del Fediverso y alternativa a X (Twitter) en este ecosistema de redes descentralizadas e interoperables. Metodología: De una muestra (n=38) de nativos digitales y matriciales de España se obtuvo una submuestra de periódicos (n=20) y cuentas (n=28) en Mastodon. Se identificaron cuentas oficiales y no oficiales, bots y no automatizadas, activas e inactivas, instancias en las que se alojan y accesos directos en los sitios web de los medios. También se identificó la fecha de creación de las cuentas para comprobar si aparecieron antes o después de la compra de Twitter por parte de Elon Musk, operación que disparó la popularidad de Mastodon. Resultados: Identificamos 13 cuentas oficiales (10 nativos y 3 matriciales), ninguna en instancias propias, y 15 cuentas no oficiales (9 matriciales y 6 nativos) conectadas por RSS por administradores de instancias de Mastodon. Los matriciales muestran mayor proporción de cuentas activas que los nativos digitales. La proporción de cuentas automatizadas es alta para ambas categorías. Se observa un “efecto Musk” en la creación de cuentas. Solo elDiario.es y El Salto (nativos digitales) ofrecen accesos en sus sitios web. El País (matricial) tiene la cuenta más antigua y El Salto es el que mayor compromiso muestra con esta red. Discusión: Los medios analizados no aprovechan todo el potencial de la soberanía tecnológica que proporciona Mastodon. Conclusiones: La plantilla usada y los resultados abren vías de investigación sobre una plataforma social (Mastodon) y un ecosistema (Fediverso) apenas explorados en el campo periodístico.”</p>

<p>My rough translation: this paper examines Spanish news organizations’ adooption of Mastodon, particularly after Musk’s purchase of Twitter/X. They find that most Spanish news organizations are present in the form of unofficial automated bots. They also find that “digital native” news organizations are the least likely to have embraced Mastodon. Overall, they find that news organizations are not taking advantage of the possibilities afforded by the fediverse.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="alternative social media" /><category term="bibliography" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bluesky continues to blow up. I hear about it everywhere. It’s so backed up the Brid.gy system has slowed to a crawl. But instead of focusing yet again on Bluesky, this week I wanted to do something that is long overdue: I want to draw your attention to some new research in alternative social media. You can find these works in the bibliography page of this blog, or reach out to me if you want to join the corresponding Zotero library. Here will highlight some new papers, mostly focusing on Mastodon (and to a lesser extent the rest of the fediverse). As you will see, there’s a variety of concerns: archiving and curation, moderation, and news sharing. Links are in the titles below. Also, I am now building an email listserv focused on academic research on alternative social media (broadly conceived). Are you an academic who wants to join the list? We have 50 colleagues there now! If you want to join, contact me (preferably with a university email address) and give me some background info and I can add you to the group.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Updates: Bluesky growth continues</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/16/ASMupdate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Updates: Bluesky growth continues" /><published>2024-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/16/ASMupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/16/ASMupdate.html"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s what caught my eye (and ear) this week in the world of alternative social media. I didn’t plan this, but it turns out a lot of this is coming from <em><a href="https://www.404media.co">404 Media</a></em> – shout out to them! If you aren’t reading their articles… do it now!
<!-- more --></p>

<h2 id="the-bluesky-bump-continues">The Bluesky Bump continues</h2>
<p>The coverage of Bluesky’s growth is everywhere. I just watched my local CBC station present a story on it during the 6 PM news.</p>

<p>You can read lots of takes, but the one that caught my eye is <a href="https://www.404media.co/the-great-migration-to-bluesky-gives-me-hope-for-the-future-of-the-internet/">Jason Koebler’s article</a> in <em>404 Media</em>. He talks about the rapid growth of Bluesky, but also puts it in conversation with Mastodon – a system he had <a href="https://www.404media.co/mastodon-is-the-good-one/">previously been excited about</a>. While Bluesky is growing, Mastodon “feels” to Koebler to be more stagnant. His theory is that this is due to Meta’s Threads:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Threads’s uneven entry into the Fediverse feels like it has made my personal feeds deader. My theory and fear is that Threads has allowed people to perform the act of federating by having their Threads posts go to the fediverse, but it does not allow people on Threads to respond to people on Mastodon. This gives people a permission structure to abandon their Mastodon accounts, use Threads, and sort of passively invest in the future of decentralized social media while actually just giving more power to Mark Zuckerberg’s side project.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In contrast, he argues Bluesky feels vibrant and human.</p>

<p>Having watched the <a href="/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump.html">“Killer Hype Cycle”</a> play out with Mastodon back in late 2022 and then seeing articles within a few months stating the fediverse had failed, I wonder at what point we will see articles with headlines such as “Remember Bluesky?”</p>

<p><em>Maybe</em> this time will be different. In some ways, it has to be – Bluesky has accepted venture capital, and that brings with it the expectations of growth and profit. Which makes it hard for me to consider Bluesky a Twitter alternative. It strikes me as yet another corporate social media platform – with all the downsides that brings with it.</p>

<h2 id="ai-and-social-engineering">AI and social engineering</h2>
<p>What downsides, you might ask? Well, speaking of <em>404 Media</em>, their podcast <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/how-ai-is-being-used-by-hackers-and-criminals-sponsored/id1703615331?i=1000677104448">just released an episode</a> featuring an interview with a cybersecurity expert Rachel Tobac on how generative AI is currently being integrated into social engineering. Tobac adeptly walks us through how deep fakes, voice cloning, and other AI tools are being used by scammers and computer hackers. For example, she discussed the case of a <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2024/02/04/asia/deepfake-cfo-scam-hong-kong-intl-hnk/index.html">social engineering attack using deepfake Zoom corporate clones</a> resulting in a loss of $25 million USD.</p>

<p>I’ve been researching and writing about this with a colleague, Sean Lawson, for some years now (e.g., <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262543453/social-engineering/">our book</a> and <a href="https://theconversation.com/chatbots-can-be-used-to-create-manipulative-content-understanding-how-this-works-can-help-address-it-207187">this article</a>). While I was not <em>particularly</em> shocked by what Tobac talked about, I did not find it comforting to hear she thinks such AI-powered social engineering can only be stopped with stronger privacy regulations, particularly of tech companies and social media corporations. I say this because that’s exactly what Sean and I have been arguing, and it seems like my native country the USA won’t be engaging regulations any time soon.</p>

<p>Why not? Well, we’ve basically granted too much power to corporate social media and other big tech companies. Their lobbying power in the US was incredible before the recent presidential election, and it’s only going to be more powerful with Trump in office. The lack of privacy regulations forces US citizens into an opt-in setup where their personal data are ripe for the taking, fueling attention-grabbing <a href="https://www.404media.co/zuckerberg-the-ai-slop-will-continue-until-morale-improves/">AI slop</a> – and thus also tools easily adopted for targeted scams.</p>

<p>I should note there’s nothing in <a href="https://bsky.social/about/support/privacy-policy">Bluesky’s Privacy Policy</a> that leads me to believe Bluesky won’t partipate in similar data abuses if it means providing a return on investement to its backers. It’s also unclear to me that they are truly committed to moving the ATProto to the IETF – it’s been <a href="https://docs.bsky.app/blog/protocol-roadmap">more than a year since they floated that goal</a>. A defacto corporate-controlled protocol – as open as it might be – is still a corporate-controlled protocol.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="bluesky" /><category term="ASM update" /><category term="social engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s what caught my eye (and ear) this week in the world of alternative social media. I didn’t plan this, but it turns out a lot of this is coming from 404 Media – shout out to them! If you aren’t reading their articles… do it now!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hey, Journalists: X is Now Truth Social</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMandTFG.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hey, Journalists: X is Now Truth Social" /><published>2024-11-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMandTFG</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMandTFG.html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey, journalists, it’s time to get off X. Today. And switch to the fediverse.</p>

<p>Here’s why.</p>

<!-- more -->
<p>When Elon Musk bought Twitter in 2022, rebranded it X, and converted it from the ostensible “public town square” into his own personal right-wing techbro platform, many many people left it for the fediverse.</p>

<p>But a key group did not: journalists. Sure, there was some flirtation with the fediverse, and to be fair, some journalists did make the switch. But many stayed on X, arguing that the audience and the movers and shakers were still there, in spite of Musk’s <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-features/elon-musk-twitter-misinformation-timeline-1235076786/">gutting of content moderation on the platform</a>.</p>

<p>OK, that’s an excuse to stay on X, journalists, but it’s increasingly a flimsy one. Especially today. What excuse do you have now? Now that we’ve seen how <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/social-media/elon-musk-turned-x-trump-echo-chamber-rcna174321">Musk made X into a machine to help propel Trump</a> back into the White House?</p>

<p>By legitimizing X, you’ve legitimized Musk’s insinuation into the halls of power – and you helped fund his efforts. You kept eyes on X, which put eyes on the ads. You kept people’s attention on the rage machine, on the disinformation and conspiracy theories. (And if the first Trump term is any guide, this is all going to get worse.) Enough already.</p>

<p>While you were sticking to X (and probably calling it “Twitter” out of nostalgia) millions of people were working away to make the fediverse a strongly moderated, calmer social media space where people do in fact discuss the news of the day and have <a href="https://medium.com/fedi-curious/lessons-on-the-road-to-reviving-journalism-via-the-fediverse-01b3748cacc5">welcomed journalists and news organizations</a>.</p>

<p>“But the fediverse is hard!” I can hear you protest. “And it would be too much work to have an X account and a fediverse account.”</p>

<p>To which I reply: what about Truth Social?</p>

<p>Since its launch in 2021, <a href="https://www.wbur.org/endlessthread/2024/11/01/truth-social">reporters have signed up for accounts</a> on Truth to access Trump’s ALL CAPS SCREEDS and dutifully post them in news sites in the name of balance. No doubt, journalists will be logging into Truth even more now, since it’s the main source for Trump’s thoughts. After all, <a href="https://theweek.com/donald-trump/1013599/trump-must-post-on-truth-social-before-posting-on-twitter-sec-filing-says">he must post there to keep the stock price inflated</a>.</p>

<p>Maybe I’m wrong, but I doubt reporters are using Truth to engage with audiences or to talk to their friends. They’re using other social media for that. Apparently, then, it’s not hard for reporters to have an account on Truth and still use other social media.</p>

<p>So, say it with me: <strong>X is now Truth Social.</strong> If you must keep an account there, dip into it to see what’s going on (you know, to watch as Trump’s attorney general announces the arrests of his political rivals) and then go back to your fediverse account. Just like you’ve been doing with Truth Social. You dip into Truth, copypaste Trump’s screeds, and get out.</p>

<p>Now, do that with X. Dip in, get out.</p>

<p>And put your energy into something that won’t be bought by a billionaire and converted to a fascism promotion machine.</p>

<h2 id="postscript-what-about-bluesky">Postscript: What about Bluesky?</h2>
<p>To be honest, I go back and forth on Bluesky. I know many people are enthused about Bluesky, particularly because they’re building their own protocol. But their recent <a href="https://bsky.social/about/blog/10-24-2024-series-a">acceptance of venture capital from cryptocurrency investors</a> begs the question: what will Bluesky do when the VC funders demand a return? As Cory Doctorow argues, it will <a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/11/02/ulysses-pact/">likely be something shitty</a>. If you want to put your eggs into another corporate basket, go ahead. It didn’t turn out well the last time.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="journalism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hey, journalists, it’s time to get off X. Today. And switch to the fediverse. Here’s why.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Update for November 8, 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMupdate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update for November 8, 2024" /><published>2024-11-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMupdate.html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/tags/asm update.html">ASM updates</a> are back! Now that I’m done <a href="/2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">drafting my book</a>, I want to get back to doing this regularly.</p>

<p>In this ASM update, here are three things that caught my eye this week. Well, besides that other big thing that happened this week.</p>

<p>This has been edited to fix an error.
<!-- more --></p>
<h2 id="on-fediblock">On #Fediblock</h2>

<p>One of the most used hashtags on the fediverse is <strong>#fediblock.</strong> Created by Marcia X and Ginger, that hashtag is essential for admins who want to learn about problematic accounts and instances. But the history of fediblock is not well-known. Now, Marcia X has <a href="https://subscriptions.boricua.style/fediblock-a-tiny-history-2/">written a short history</a> to help shed some light. We learn it came out of personal experience: “I started the tag so that bad actors doing quite obvious trolling or isms could just easily posted about to other people with whom I didn’t share a server with could see. Like a serial misogynistic harasser. There were no set rules put in place.”</p>

<h2 id="flatlining">Flatlining?</h2>

<p><a href="https://privacy.thenexus.today/flatness/">Jon Pincus argues</a> that <del>the ActivityPub fediverse</del> [edit: my mistake!] Mastodon is <strong>flatlining,</strong> particularly in relation to Bluesky. He puts the blame on the main Mastodon project, hoping that it changes for the better: “Whether or not there’s a hard fork, the same opportunities are there for the official Mastodon project if its direction and leadership structure evolves. The official project has some big advantages – including funding – so let’s hope that happens. And it’s not an either-or situation; forks don’t have to be hostile, and there are lots of potential synergies if they can work together effectively (as well as challenges).”</p>

<h2 id="but-just-say-no-to-bluesky">But Just Say ‘No’ to Bluesky</h2>

<p>And yet, <a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/11/02/ulysses-pact/">Cory Doctorow notes</a> that he’s not going to ever use Bluesky. “I will never again devote my energies to building up an audience on a platform whose management can sever my relationship to that audience at will.”</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ASM updates are back! Now that I’m done drafting my book, I want to get back to doing this regularly. In this ASM update, here are three things that caught my eye this week. Well, besides that other big thing that happened this week. This has been edited to fix an error.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">York Circle Lecture: Fleeing Facebook and Exiting X</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/yorkcirclelecture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="York Circle Lecture: Fleeing Facebook and Exiting X" /><published>2024-11-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/yorkcirclelecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/yorkcirclelecture.html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I gave a presentation at York University in Toronto as part of their York Circle program. The audience was comprised of York alumni.</p>

<p>My presentation was “Fleeing Facebook and Exiting X: How activists show the path away from corporate social media.” Here’s the abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The purchase of Twitter by Elon Musk in 2022, coupled with Meta’s blocking of Canadian news sites, has prompted people in Canada to consider their social media options. Social media has now fragmented, with a small but growing population of people turning to non-corporate, alternative social media, such as Mastodon and the fediverse. This talk will discuss how non-corporate, alternative social media provide Canadians not just with a path away from Facebook or X, but also provide a new way to engage in online democracy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If that sounds interesting, well… read on! This is a version of that presentation, edited into blog form. (Note: this is another long post.)</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h2>

<p>Before I get too far, I want to acknowledge a couple things. First, this research has been supported thanks in part to funding from the Canada First Research Excellence Fund.</p>

<p>Second, some of what I’m going to talk about comes from a collaboration between myself and Alex Martin, who is a PhD student here at York in the Science and Technology Studies program.</p>

<h2 id="introduction-news-and-social-media-in-canada">Introduction: News and Social Media in Canada</h2>

<p>Let’s start this conversation about social media in Regina, Saskatchewan. Specifically, let’s talk about what could be the top news company in Regina. It is, arguably, a garbage company.</p>

<p>According to <a href="https://www.canadaland.com/podcast/1042-the-city-that-gets-its-news-from-a-dumpster-company/"><em>Canadaland</em></a>, the most trafficked news site for Regina
residents is a Facebook page run by Just Bins, a garbage can company. (I also should credit <em>Canadaland</em> another way – I kind of stole this intro from them!)</p>

<p>In fact, the Just Bins Facebook page won a “best of” award for news in Regina.</p>

<p>This isn’t to say there is no local paper. But the local paper, the <em>Regina Leader Post</em>, is seeing dramatic drops in circulation and no longer prints the paper locally.</p>

<p>That news reporting in Canada is in a crisis is not new, but it is certainly getting worse. Layoffs abound.</p>

<p>One major issue has been Meta. Because of the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/canadian-heritage/services/online-news.html">Online News Act</a>, Meta has now refused to let people link to Canadian news in Facebook and Instagram. This is in part what led to Just Bins Facebook page being able to become the top news site in Regina. As Jesse Brown of <em>Canadaland</em> said, “It appalls me that [Just Bins] can build a massive audience specifically because [it’s] not news. I can’t publish to Facebook, and [they] can <em>because</em> [it’s] not news.”</p>

<p>Regardless of how you feel about the Online News Act, it is coming from the recognition that a handful of media corporations have too much power over Canadian news. Let me put this a different way. Another, albeit different case in point: Elon Musk’s X. Unlike Meta, news organizations are certainly welcome on X. But at what price? As <a href="https://www.disinfo.eu/publications/disinformation-on-x/">multiple</a> <a href="https://www.isi.edu/news/55932/new-twitter-now-with-more-hate/">studies</a> and <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/musk-lashes-out-at-advertisers-leaving-x-over-rise-in-hate-speech">news reports</a> are finding, disinformation, trolling, and harassment are on the rise on X. And often the disinformation and trolling comes from the top, such as when Musk labeled the CBC as <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/cbc-twitter-label-69-government-funded-media-elon-musk-2023-4">“69% government funded”</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-do-we-go">Where do we go?</h2>
<p>Meta and X have me wondering: Where do we go if we want to leave Facebook or X?</p>

<p>What about TikTok? LinkedIn? Reddit? Maybe. But all of these share in the same basic problem: they are all social media that is controlled by for-profit companies that, at the end of the day, make their money by monitoring our lives. They can be bought and sold.</p>

<p>I’ve been researching this question – where do we go? – for my entire academic career, from my days as a PhD student in the 2000s to the writing of my first book, <em><a href="https://tupress.temple.edu/books/reverse-engineering-social-media">Reverse Engineering Social Media</a></em> in 2014 to today, when I am finalizing my fourth book, <em>Move Slowly and Build Bridges</em>, for Oxford. (For more on my academic career, <a href="/2024/10/18/GMUpresentation.html">see this post</a>)</p>

<p>The answer to the “where do we go?” question has been given for many, many years by people I have been calling “critical reverse engineers.” These are activists who take apart corporate social media – Facebook, Instagram, Twitter/X, YouTube – to make something better. I have interviewed dozens of these critical reverse engineers, studied the code and interfaces of the systems they’ve built, and have even operated some of the social media they’ve created.</p>

<p>It turns out that quite a few of these critical reverse engineers are right here in Canada.</p>

<p>Let me say a bit more about critical reverse engineering. And to do that, I should talk quickly about reverse engineering in general.</p>

<p>Basically, reverse engineering is forward engineering in reverse. Rather than starting with plans and them implementing them in material objects, reverse engineers start with the material object and seek to figure out how it works, often discovering clues about the creators’ intentions.</p>

<p>Reverse engineers do this work for a range of purposes. It might be to make a competing project – a famous example here is the reverse engineering of the IBM PC in the 1980s. Or it might be for military purposes, reverse engineering captured equipment – a famous case is that of the Russian Tu-4 bomber, which was a reverse engineered US B-29.</p>

<p>Now, these aren’t particularly critical. I’m using “critical” in the sense of critical theory – the examination of power in society, with the goal of making a more just and ethical society.</p>

<p>And I think that social media admits to critical inquiry. Social media has had a major impact on how we live our lives. We can talk about the benefits of social media. It has been used by social justice movements (Idle No More, Me Too, Black Lives Matter). There’s the simple pleasures of sharing and connection. And there’s local and global news sharing. And we can also talk about its harms: Facebook’s emotional contagion experiments. The Cambridge Analytica scandal. Gamergate harassment on Twitter. And concerns over mental health, particularly of teens.</p>

<p>There’s a lot at stake when we consider social media. So, let’s consider reverse engineering social media, but not just to make competing products. I am interested in activists who are reverse engineering social media to create systems that are better than the corporate versions – alternatives that are under our control, that push away some of the negative aspects of corporate social media away in favor of more beneficial aspects. I have been studying projects that produce new innovations in social media outside of the predominantly Silicon Valley model.</p>

<h2 id="the-fediverse-innovations-and-canada">The fediverse, innovations, and Canada</h2>

<p>Specifically, I will highlight the fediverse – social media that is comprised of thousands of small community-run social media sites linked together in a global network. As a project that critically reverse engineers corporate social media, the fediverse brings about many innovations.</p>

<p>I will talk about four such innovations:</p>
<ul>
  <li>a new topology</li>
  <li>no surveillance capitalism</li>
  <li>ecological innovations</li>
  <li>online democracy</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="a-new-topology-noncentralized">A New Topology: Noncentralized</h2>

<p>I argue the fediverse provides a new way of doing social media, one that’s not centralized or concentrated.</p>

<p>I say new, but really what I’m going to say is quite similar to email. Email is federated. If I have an account on Protonmail, and a friend has an account on Gmail, and another runs their own server using Roundcube software, we can all still contact each other. We can do so in spite of the fact that all three are provided by different organizations in different locations.</p>

<p>This is because email runs on a shared, standardized protocol called Send Mail Transfer Protocol, or SMTP. SMTP dates back to the early 1980s.</p>

<p>Much more recently, critical reverse engineers have created a social media protocol that works much like email, but for social data. It works like this. Let’s say I’m using a system called PeerTube, which is a video-sharing service. I can connect to someone using Pixelfed, which is an image-sharing service. And that person can connect to someone on a Mastodon server, which is a Twitter-like system. And so on.</p>

<p>This is possible because of a new standard called <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub</a>, which, a bit like email, presents social data in the form of inboxes and outboxes. The ActivityPub protocol was authored by Christine Lemmer-Webber, Jessica Tallon, Erin Shepherd, Amy Guy, and Evan Prodromou. Here’s a Canadian connection! Evan Prodromou, who has been actively working on social media alternative since the late 2000s, is a Canadian. Thanks to Prodromou, Lemmer-Webber, and the rest of the creators of this protocol, we now have a global network of interconnected social media servers.</p>

<p>And, as a testament to their engineering feat, consider the fact that the ActivityPub-based fediverse was able to absorb a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/news/datablog/2023/jan/08/elon-musk-drove-more-than-a-million-people-to-mastodon-but-many-arent-sticking-around">massive wave of new users happening in late 2022</a> – that is, right when Musk finalized his purchase of Twitter.</p>

<p>The upsides of this noncentralized system are twofold. For one, it’s less vulnerable to being simply taken over (e.g., as in the case of Twitter/X). Second, it is open to many groups participating in running their own social media.</p>

<h2 id="no-surveillance-capitalism">No Surveillance Capitalism</h2>

<p>As for the refusal to engage in surveillance capitalism, consider <a href="https://mstdn.ca/explore">Mstdn.ca</a>, a Mastodon server that provides Twitter-like features
to Canadians.</p>

<p>If you’re considering joining Mstdn.ca, you might notice that they ask for donations. Why? Well, they don’t sell advertising space. Unlike corporate social media, which is in the business of selling our attention to advertisers, Mstdn.ca does not sell user data. This is typical of the rest of the fediverse.</p>

<p>In my study of Mastodon and the rest of the fediverse, I’ve found that the vast majority of instances use donations or other mutual aid-style approaches to funding. They use a variety of nonprofit organizational structures, from informal to formal. And Mastodon and fediverse software do not include the tools needed to do targeted, surveillance-based advertising.</p>

<p>There are some possible upsides here. Since people cannot buy advertising space, there’s far less incentive to promote outrageous, attention-grabbing posts. Moreover, current disinformation practices rely in part on the ability to buy targeted advertisements – you can do that on Facebook and Youtube, but you cannot do that on the fediverse.</p>

<p>I should note I say “possible” because I think it is early to tell if these advantages will play out. However, in my interviews with fediverse users, they do report that they have a calmer experience on the fediverse. In addition, I am part of a group of researchers monitoring the fediverse for disinformation – a big concern as we head into a US presidential election – and so far, so good on that front.</p>

<h2 id="ecological-innovations">Ecological innovations</h2>

<p>On to ecological innovations. The brute fact is that, in spite of the promise that digital media will be light and airy, digital media is having a massive impact on the climate. Social media data centers – and the turn to generative AI – are <a href="https://direct.mit.edu/glep/article/24/2/9/120588/Generative-AI-and-Social-Media-May-Exacerbate-the">straining energy systems</a>. And data centers are <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/2023/04/25/data-centers-drought-water-use/">notorious for their demands for drinking water</a>. Speaking as someone who has lived in both the US and Canadian Rockies, this is a major concern of mine.</p>

<p>Let’s say people leave behind X and Facebook for the fediverse. Will the fediverse replicate these issues? Not necessarily. Because the fediverse is community-run, it is possible for groups to experiment with it to reduce its energy and water demands.</p>

<p>Consider the work of <a href="https://www.trentu.ca/culturalstudies/faculty-research/undergraduate-faculty/anne-pasek">Anne Pasek of Trent University</a>. Anne and her colleagues are developing solar-powered fediverse social media.</p>

<p>This isn’t far-fetched. A few years ago, an online publication called <a href="https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/">Low Tech Magazine</a> demonstrated that it is possible for a website to be powered by a small solar panel. Likewise, Pasek and her colleagues are working on powering a fediverse server with a small, consumer-grade solar panel.</p>

<p>This is experimental. Time will tell if it works. But if projects like Anne’s are successful, we could see a reduction in the carbon footprint of social media.</p>

<p>In addition, I can say that there are some clear ecological benefits to the fediverse when we compare it to corporate social media. I mentioned previously that the fediverse avoids surveillance capitalism. This does mean that, right out of the box, the fediverse should have less ecological impact than corporate social media, since it does not require the infrastructure of behavioral advertising.</p>

<h2 id="online-democracy">Online Democracy</h2>

<p>Finally, let’s talk online democracy. Here I’d point to <a href="https://cosocial.ca/explore">Cosocial.ca</a>. This is a social media site run by Canadian cooperative organization. As a collective, Cosocial members have developed their own, <a href="https://cosocial.ca/about">local moderation rules</a>.</p>

<p>Here’s a sampling of their code:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Treat all persons fairly and with respect, courtesy and dignity.</li>
  <li>Be sensitive to cultural and social differences and practices.</li>
  <li>Be careful in your use of language that may be disrespectful or demeaning.”</li>
  <li>They also have prohibitions against racism, transphobia, and violence.</li>
</ul>

<p>This can work because Cosocial is not large – it has 100 active members. It’s much easier to have such a code of conduct for a small number of folks.</p>

<p>So, you might think: 100 people? That’s not a lot. That’s nothing compared to corporate social media!</p>

<p>But Cosocial isn’t alone. Cosocial can connect to another Canadian instance, <a href="https://ottawa.place/about">Ottawa.place</a>. Like Cosocial, Ottawa.place has a code of conduct with similar values. So those two can connect without clashing about their ethical values.</p>

<p>And Cosocial and Ottawa.place can connect to another instance, <a href="https://scholar.social/about">Scholar.social</a>. Scholar.social is a well-moderated, large instance run by a person in Montreal. Like the others, Scholar.social has a similar code of conduct. And all these servers can connect to others in Canada.</p>

<p>But this isn’t just in Canada. These servers can connect others located around the world, forming a global network. And if they connect to other servers with similar codes of conduct, we see an emergent set of ethical values. This network of servers share a commitment to active moderation, not only against racism or transphobia, but also against disinformation. Studies are showing that there is a shared set of ethical values across much of the fediverse. I think this is most exciting aspect.</p>

<p>This is a structure a co-author and I call “<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400">the covenantal fediverse</a>”: a global network of ethically-aligned digital communities.</p>

<p>Here, we get the benefits of locally-run and moderated systems, but with the reach of a global network.</p>

<h2 id="but-what-about-news-in-canada">But What About News in Canada?</h2>

<p>But what about news? I started out with a note about the sorry state     of news in Canada – including a discussion about social media’s role in news sharing. Can Canadians share and receive news on federated, non-corporate social media?</p>

<p>This is an area Alex Martin, a PhD student, is working on. The short answer is: yes, Canadians can share and are sharing news on the fediverse.</p>

<p>Alex has taken the lead in a research project where we interview Canadians who are running or using federated social media. A big question Alex is asking: are Canadians sharing news on the fediverse? And what sorts of news are they sharing?</p>

<p>We’re hearing Canadians across the country note that the fediverse has become a viable source of breaking news. This includes local happenings as well as global events. And we’re also discovering people and groups who recognize this and want to make local federated social media so that people can share news.</p>

<p>What about news organizations? This is emerging, too, albeit a bit slower. <a href="https://mstdn.ca/@thetyee">The Tyee</a>, <a href="https://flipboard.com/@ConversationCA">Conversation Canada</a>, <a href="https://mstdn.ca/@thenarwhal">The Narwhal</a>, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@livewirecalgary">Livewire Calgary</a>, and <a href="https://medium.com/@marilync/canadian-journalism-on-mastodon-15eeb4f5b9df">a host of journalists</a> are posting to the fediverse.</p>

<p>I think there really ought to be more. In addition, both <a href="https://theconversation.com/canadas-public-broadcaster-should-use-mastodon-to-provide-a-social-media-service-194116">Fen McKelvey of Concordia University and I</a> have argued the CBC should set up their own presence on the fediverse. They could establish a server and provide their journalists with accounts. Those journalists could post to the network and have global reach while at the same time being on a server run under CBC standards – not under the standards of Elon Musk.</p>

<p>Were the CBC to start their own fediverse server, they wouldn’t be alone. Globally, there are public news organizations starting to operate their own fediverse servers – most notably, the BBC has experimented with <a href="https://theconversation.com/canadas-public-broadcaster-should-use-mastodon-to-provide-a-social-media-service-194116">its own Mastodon server</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The fediverse has a great deal of potential for Canadian social media:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Canadians are, right now, running their own social media
        outside of the dominant Silicon Valley systems.</li>
  <li>They can moderate and govern themselves locally, and yet
        have access not only to the rest of Canada but the rest of
        the world</li>
  <li>They can experiment with solutions to the climate crisis</li>
  <li>They can stave off the privacy violations of surveillance
        capitalism</li>
  <li>And they can share both local and global news</li>
</ul>

<p>In other words, Canadians are doing the work of critically reverse engineering social media, and are showing folks a            possible path away from X or Facebook.</p>

<p>This isn’t to say that the fediverse is a flawless system. I present plenty of criticisms of it in my book. But given the growing set of problems posed not just in Canada, but globally, but corporate social media, I believe serious scholarship that highlights the fediverse and critical reverse engineering is needed.</p>

<p>Incidentally, if you’re Canadian and want to try the fediverse, here are a couple options to look at. <a href="https://mstdn.ca/auth/sign_up">Mstdn.ca is open for registrations</a>. Or, if you want a more regional/localized instance, the <a href="https://mastodonserver.ca/">Mastodon Server
site</a> has a list.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="goal 2" /><category term="presentations" /><category term="journalism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday, I gave a presentation at York University in Toronto as part of their York Circle program. The audience was comprised of York alumni. My presentation was “Fleeing Facebook and Exiting X: How activists show the path away from corporate social media.” Here’s the abstract: The purchase of Twitter by Elon Musk in 2022, coupled with Meta’s blocking of Canadian news sites, has prompted people in Canada to consider their social media options. Social media has now fragmented, with a small but growing population of people turning to non-corporate, alternative social media, such as Mastodon and the fediverse. This talk will discuss how non-corporate, alternative social media provide Canadians not just with a path away from Facebook or X, but also provide a new way to engage in online democracy. If that sounds interesting, well… read on! This is a version of that presentation, edited into blog form. (Note: this is another long post.)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From reverse engineering to building bridges: adventures in alternative social media</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/GMUpresentation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From reverse engineering to building bridges: adventures in alternative social media" /><published>2024-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/GMUpresentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/GMUpresentation.html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently gave a presentation to the <a href="https://culturalstudies.gmu.edu/">Cultural Studies PhD program at George Mason University</a>. That’s the program where I earned my PhD, so it was an honor to come back and talk to my professors as well as some of the new students currently in the program.</p>

<p>I took the presentation as an opportunity to reflect on my academic career from my time at Mason (2005-2010) to my <a href="/2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">latest book project</a>. I’ve modified it for this blog. Take a look at the abstract and, if piques your interest, feel free to read it! (It’s a bit long.)</p>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>In my time as a PhD student in GMU’s Cultural Studies program, I learned
that I must let my object of study tell me what methods to use to
analyze it. I also learned not to merely interpret the object, but seek
to change it. Since I chose to study what was then called “Web 2.0” and
what I now call “corporate social media,” I needed to bring Marxian
political economy, science and technology studies, and software studies
to bear on the object. And I began to examine the practices of activists
who sought to make something better than corporate social media:
alternative social media. Over a decade ago I began my adventures in
alternative social media, chasing it through hacker collectives,
cyberlibertarian organizations, and even onto the dark web. Through
digital ethnography, close examinations of code, and hands-on experience
running alternative social media, I developed an approach I call
“critical reverse engineering.” Here I present critical reverse
engineering as a methodology for activist engagement with digital
technologies. To illustrate this approach, I will draw on insights from
my forthcoming book, <em>Move Slowly and Build Bridges: Mastodon, the
Fediverse, and the Struggle for Ethical Social Media</em> (Oxford, 2025).</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="introduction-do-we-call-it-x-or-twitter">Introduction: Do we call it X or Twitter?</h2>

<p>Is it X? Or is it Twitter?</p>

<p>Because I’ve heard media critics use both names, even well after Musk bought
Twitter in 2022.</p>

<p>I hear media critics say, “X is out of control. It’s full of
disinformation and pornbots. Musk is slowly destroying it, indicating
the fundamental problem of billionaires owning social media.”</p>

<p>And then, I often hear those same media critics tell their readers and
listeners, “Please follow me on Twitter.”</p>

<p>It’s “X” when you hate it and “Twitter” when you love it.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/democracynow.webp" alt="A screenshot of the Democracy Now website, showing stories critical of Elon Musk, yet allowing you to share the story on Musk's X." />
    <figcaption>
        While Democracy Now! is critiquing Elon Musk, they still contribute to his bottom line by using Musk's X.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This screenshot of <em>Democracy Now!</em> doesn’t quite illustrate my point,
but it gets close. Here are stories about billionaire media owners – including Elon Musk – who run
amok. But please do follow us on the very platforms we decry.</p>

<p>This encapsulates the contradictions of corporate social media: we may
complain about them, about surveillance capitalism, exploitation of our
sociality, algorithms that push content on us, about addiction.</p>

<p>And yet we also believe they are the only tool we have to speak up, to
organize, or more humbly, to connect and share with our friends.</p>

<h3 id="leaving-corporate-social-media">Leaving Corporate Social Media</h3>

<p>In contrast, my career has largely been dedicated to the idea that we
can and must leave corporate social media behind. That we can maintain
their pleasures while effectively taking them over. For over a decade now, I’ve been talking to activists and technologists seeking to make something better than X or Facebook.</p>

<p>This presentation is a bit of a reflection on my academic career and how I came to study alternative social media. It starts with my time in Cultural Studies at Mason (2005-2010), then the
period around the writing of my first book, <a href="https://tupress.temple.edu/books/reverse-engineering-social-media"><em>Reverse Engineering Social
Media</em></a> a decade ago, and culminating in my current book, <em>Move Slowly
and Build Bridges,</em> which should come out next year.</p>

<p>My plan for this is roughly chronological:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Part 1: Cultural Studies and Web 2.0</li>
  <li>Part 2: Seeking Critical Reverse Engineers</li>
  <li>Part 3: Adventures in Alternative Social Media</li>
  <li>Part 4: New Critical Reverse Engineers on the Fediverse</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="part-1-gmu-cultural-studies-web-20-2005--2010">Part 1: GMU Cultural Studies, Web 2.0 (2005 – 2010)</h2>

<p>Thinking back, what I learned during my time in the Cultural Studies PhD progam at Mason were two lessons:</p>

<ul>
  <li>First, what does the object of study need you to do to understand
it? How does the object demand particular methodologies?</li>
  <li>Second, “<a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1845/theses/theses.htm">the point is to change it</a>.” That is, the point of our work is to make a better world.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="finding-an-object-web-20">Finding an Object: Web 2.0</h3>
<p>First I needed an object of study.</p>

<p>I came to the object of my study during a class with GMU Cultural Studies professor <a href="https://historyarthistory.gmu.edu/people/alandsb1">Alison Landsberg</a>.
She said, “someone ought to take a look at Youtube,” in her Visual Cultures class.</p>

<p>At the time, YouTube was making headlines because of its eye-popping <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/id/wbna15196982">sale to Google for $1.65 billion USD</a>.</p>

<p>Like many people, professor Landsberg was perhaps wondering how a relatively obscure website could be sold for such a sum. Prior to Google’s purchase, YouTube was best known as a place where people either <a href="https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2799/2577">uploaded pirated videos</a> or made “vlogs,” personal, self-confessional
video blogs (as well as “vlogs” that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonelygirl15">turned out to be fictional, yet compelling</a>).</p>

<p>The users had made YouTube what it was – contributing videos, commenting on them, building a culture. Were they getting a cut of the $1.65 billion?</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/battelleoreilly.jpg" alt="John Battelle and Tim O'Reilly at the Web 2.0 summit" />
    <figcaption>
        John Battelle and Tim O'Reilly at the Web 2.0 summit. My understanding is that we may be on Web3 now. Or Web 4.0. Or Web 10.0. I'm not even sure anymore.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The case of YouTube led me to what at the time was called <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/pub/a/web2/archive/what-is-web-20.html">Web 2.0</a>, where, as Tim
O’Reilly and John Batelle argued in 2004, users of digital technologies do the work of building businesses. Where users create data – about the world, and about themselves – that companies can harvest for new ideas and profit.</p>

<p>Were Youtube’s users getting a cut, then? No. From a note I took around the time, I wrote “These companies ask us to build them, and then expect us to consume their products, without compensation beyond a ‘richer’ user experience.”</p>

<p>And of course I wasn’t the first to say this – <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/social-text/article-abstract/18/2%20(63)/33/33433/Free-LaborPRODUCING-CULTURE-FOR-THE-DIGITAL?redirectedFrom=fulltext">Tiziana Terranova had already theorized free labor</a> in digital media, and <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/international-review-of-social-history/article/emerging-sources-of-labor-on-the-internet-the-case-of-america-online-volunteers/56D287B6007BCF167FC254EF4ED166CF">many others</a> had taken
up that concept.</p>

<p>Now of course many people recognize what’s going on, and call this “surveillance capitalism.” It’s an idea so recognizable that even the <a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/09/ftc-staff-report-finds-large-social-media-video-streaming-companies-have-engaged-vast-surveillance">US Federal Trade Commission has just now noticed it happening</a>!</p>

<p>Welcome to the party, FTC. We’ve been talking about this since the 2000s.</p>

<h3 id="methods-marxian-political-economy-science-and-technology-studies-and-software-studies">Methods: Marxian political economy, science and technology studies, and software studies</h3>

<p>So my object became Web 2.0, or surveillance capitalism, or specifically what I now call <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/2056305115604338">corporate social media</a>.</p>

<p>What methods could I bring to bear?</p>

<p>These are digital technologies and they involve communicative practices, and they are embedded deeply in capitalism. They rely upon user-generated content – that is, freely given labor – to produce valuable digital artifacts that attract attention.</p>

<p>The object spoke, and one thing it said to me was “use Marxian political economy to understand me.” <a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1857/grundrisse/">Marx’s <em>Grundrisse</em></a> turned out to be valuable – particularly as <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/0950238032000114868">Stuart Hall</a>] and <a href="https://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/?id=p067952">Nick Dyer-Witheford</a> had interpreted it.</p>

<p>The object also told me to use science and technology studies – particularly conceptions of heterogeneity found in the work of <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/books/book/2030/ComplexitiesSocial-Studies-of-Knowledge-Practices">John Law and and
Annemarie Mol</a>.</p>

<p>And because Web 2.0 relies on software, I also turned to <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262062749/software-studies/">software studies</a> to help understand the underlying digital and material layers of Web 2.0. In particular, I turned to analysis of software engineering as a practice, especially the <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/social-text/article/30/2%20(111)/99/33725/Real-Software-AbstractionsOn-the-Rise-of-Facebook">specific ideas of abstraction</a> in software engineering.</p>

<p>Together, the above gave me conceptual tools to decompose Web 2.0 – what I now would call “corporate social media” – and engage in a critical approach to technology, using concepts such as <em>labor, value, exploitation, abstraction</em>, and <em>engineering</em>.</p>

<h3 id="the-point-is-to-change-it">The Point is to Change It</h3>

<p>But, taking a cue from <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/22860236">Andrew Feenberg</a>, it is not simply enough to
decompose the object with concepts.</p>

<p>As <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2470750">I write elsewhere</a> (basically paraphrasing Feenberg), “Rather than
start with an ideal and bemoaning a world that doesn't live up to it, critical theory seeks out contradictions within the objects it
encounters. These fissures provide us with tangible ways forward, new possibilities that are not simply abstract, timeless ethical ideals.”</p>

<p>Again: this is the other lesson I received from my time at Mason. The point is to change it.</p>

<p>But how could I help change it? I was an English major. Particularly back during my PhD studies, I was not skilled in coding. I was not (and largely still am not) “technical.”</p>

<p>But I could look for people – activists, technologists – who were challenging the rising corporate domination of the internet.</p>

<h2 id="part-2-seeking-critical-reverse-engineers-2008--2014">Part 2: Seeking Critical Reverse Engineers (2008 – 2014)</h2>

<p>My PhD studies led me to the study of people I call “critical reverse engineers,” activists who are taking apart the technologies we face, learning how
they work, and building better systems.</p>

<p>First, I’ll say a bit more about how I’m thinking about critical reverse engineering. Examining the technical literature on reverse engineering, <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2470750">I argue</a> that
a critical form of reverse engineering involves the four following orientations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pragmatic</li>
  <li>Genealogical</li>
  <li>Legal</li>
  <li>Normative</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-pragmatic-orientation">The Pragmatic Orientation</h3>

<p>Reverse engineers do not imagine an ideal technology. Instead, they start with existing technical objects, taking them apart to see how they
have been constructed.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/hacf_re.jpg" alt="A scene from the TV show Halt and Catch Fire. Two men are in a garage. They are looking into an open computer." />
    <figcaption>
        In Season 1 of the AMC show Halt and Catch Fire, two characters reverse engineered an IBM PC to make a new computer.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>A scene from the AMC show <em>Halt and Catch Fire</em> illustrates this. A
two-person team set out to make a new computer called The Giant. Instead
of building the ideal machine, they simply reverse-engineered the IBM PC
to make a PC clone.</p>

<p>As that scene illustrates, a great deal of this process entails the
discovery of 'facts' discerned through thick, close, detailed
empirical analysis of technical objects. How does the technology work?
What is it comprised of? Who built it? What might their intentions have
been? What can we do with it?</p>

<h3 id="genealogical">Genealogical</h3>

<p>Drawing on Foucauldian thinking, particularly as interpreted by <a href="https://iupress.org/9780253006233/genealogy-as-critique/">Colin Koopman</a>,
I argue that there is a genealogical aspect to reverse engineering.</p>

<p>That is, “reverse engineering” is “forward engineering” in reverse. Engineering typically is a process of developing abstract requirements,
then specification documents, and then the specifications are implemented in material.</p>

<p>Reverse engineering starts with the implemented object and then moves backward towards abstract conceptions that may have preceded.</p>

<p>In addition, a reverse engineer engages in what <a href="https://noehernandezcortez.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/nietzsche-genealogy-history.pdf">Foucault might call</a> the “gray, meticulous, and patiently documentary” work of poring through comments in code, scrounging for specification documents, or studying the discourses of the organization that created the object under scrutiny.</p>

<h3 id="legal">Legal</h3>

<p>The familiar caveat: I am not a lawyer!</p>

<p>But, according to legal scholars who look at reverse engineering – particularly <a href="https://www.yalelawjournal.org/article/the-law-and-economics-of-reverse-engineering">Pamela Samuelson</a> – reverse engineering has a tradition of legal protections in contexts such as the United States and the European Union. In traditional manufacturing, U.S. courts have held that the sale of an object is akin to its publication, and thus the legal owner of any object is free to take it apart, study it, and even produce a copy of it for sale.</p>

<p>This situation is a bit more complex with software. Lines of code are protected by copyright; I cannot copy lines of code from a
copyrighted program into a new program. But in terms of the functional side, unless it has been protected by a patent, we are free to replicate
the functionality of existing software. And in order to do that, we are in fact allowed to open up, probe, test, and disassemble software –
even to make copies of it in the process.</p>

<h3 id="normative">Normative</h3>

<p>However, none of the above is necessarily critical. Someone can reverse engineer a technology merely to make a competing product.</p>

<p>To become “critical reverse engineering,” we need a critical, normative approach – we need ethics. That is, we disassemble technical artifacts, produce knowledge from that disassembly, and construct new artifacts that further efforts towards economic and social justice.</p>

<p>So I have been seeking activists engaged in critical reverse engineering of corporate social media – people who are pragmatic in their relation to technology, use genealogical thinking, exercise their rights to reverse engineer, and do so to make a better world.</p>

<h2 id="part-3-adventures-in-alternative-social-media-2010--2016">Part 3: Adventures in Alternative Social Media (2010 – 2016)</h2>

<p>Seeking out critical reverse engineers of corporate social media set me
off on adventures in alternative social media in the years 2010-2016.</p>

<p>Most of the alternatives <a href="https://twentysix.fibreculturejournal.org/fcj-190-building-a-better-twitter-a-study-of-the-twitter-alternatives-gnu-social-quitter-rstat-us-and-twister/">I studied</a> were Twitter alternatives, such as GNU social and Twister.</p>

<p><a href="https://gnusocial.network/">GNU social</a> is a microblogging system that is free to download, install,
and run. It was was developed by Free Software activists who want to eliminate
proprietary software. It is federated (more on this in a bit).</p>

<p><a href="http://twister.net.co/">Twister</a> was a fascinating case – made by Miguel Freitas, a Brazilian
software engineer who wanted to provide protesters with censorship-resistant microblogging. He developed a peer-to-peer version of Twitter using both blockchain and bittorrent-style technologies.</p>

<p>I <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2955827">also studied</a> Facebook alternatives, such as <a href="https://diasporafoundation.org/">diaspora</a>. diaspora was inspired by a presentation from law professor Eben Moglen to a bunch of NYU students in 2010 – so keep this in mind as you
present your research – technologists may be listening!</p>

<p>And <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1461444814554900">my work even took me onto the dark web</a> – networks where both
readers and producers of websites are anonymized. I studied several dark web social networking systems, where people relied on pseudonyms to engage in social media activities. Many of these systems run on the anonymizing <a href="https://www.torproject.org/">Tor network</a>, but I found examples on <a href="https://geti2p.net/en/">I2P</a> and <a href="https://www.hyphanet.org/index.html">Freenet</a>, as well. Indeed, this work led me to write <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262038263/weaving-the-dark-web/">a book about the dark web</a>.</p>

<p>So, how are these critical reverse engineering projects? Let’s go back to the four orientations. These projects are</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Pragmatic</em>: They very often emulate Twitter, since Twitter’s
functionality is decidedly recognizable as social media but is
relatively simple to implement.</li>
  <li><em>Genealogical:</em> Not only do they examine corporate social media and
work back towards the original requirements, they also tend to be
built in reaction to the constant changes made to corporate social
media</li>
  <li><em>Legal:</em> They rely on the rights of reverse engineering. Freitas in particular talked to me about clean-room
requirements engineering.</li>
  <li><em>Normative</em>: All of these projects make claims to being more ethical
than corporate social media for a variety of reasons.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="critiques-of-their-normative-stances">Critiques of their normative stances</h3>
<p>However, I began to notice some shortcomings in that last, normative aspect.</p>

<p>One major reason the activists develop these systems is to shun surveillance capitalism. That’s obviously hugely important.</p>

<p>But the overarching philosophy of many of these projects is a very particular version of “freedom” that results in less just outcomes.</p>

<p>As I mention above, GNU social was developed by the Free Software Foundation, which touts Free Software and the “Four Freedoms.” These relate in part to freedom of speech, particularly in the face of government restrictions. Along for ride are discourses about openness and cyberlibertarian governance.</p>

<p>This program is extremely individual-centric. Taken to its extreme, it is about the eradication of the network in favor of the completely
sovereign individual. The desire seems to be an unfettered subject capable of wielding technology to openly speaking to anyone, anywhere.</p>

<p>Or, as Andrew Ross says in <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40068391">a critique of free software</a>, “Voices proclaiming freedom in every direction, but justice in none.” (I’m taking him a bit out of context, but I think it’s fair.)</p>

<p>There are many consequences of this freedom myopia.</p>

<p>One consequence of this is that it raises the specter of what the philosopher Herbert Marcuse called <a href="https://www.marcuse.org/herbert/publications/1960s/1965-repressive-tolerance-fulltext.html">“repressive tolerance,”</a> where the speech of the marginalized is eradicated through being made equal to
the speech of the dominant.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/bluelm.jpg" alt="The Blue Lives Matter flag flying in front of a banner that says 'Black Lives Matter.'" />
    <figcaption>
        This is the most visually coherent example of repressive tolerance I can think of. By stating "Blue lives matter," the ideas of the Black Lives Matter movement become eradicated by being placed on equal footing to those who are already in power -- the police.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>While Marcuse supplies good examples from the 1960s, I explain repressive tolerance to students using the example of the utterance
“Blue Lives Matter” – a means to eradicate the Black Lives Matter movement by placing those already in power on an equal footing to Black
victims of police violence.</p>

<p>We saw this play out in the US and elsewhere in the form of the Alt-Right – <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262549417/gaming-democracy/">Adrienne Massanari has done excellent work</a> linking Gamergate, Silicon Valley ideologies, and rising fascism in the USA. The desire of repressive tolerance is to eradicate the presence of women, gender minorities, or racialized minorities from technical, leisure, and political spaces by maintaining the status quo.</p>

<p>We can also see repressive tolerance at work in the validation of the internet Edgelord – a phenomenon <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262529877/this-is-why-we-cant-have-nice-things/">best explored by Whitney Phillips</a>.</p>

<p>We saw the Gamergate and alt-right movements gain a great deal of traction on Twitter, but the fact is that they have also had a dominant presence on
alternative social media, as well, particularly those that have a sociotechnical imaginary of freedom and openness.</p>

<p>The brute fact is, it became increasingly difficult for me to find daylight between many of the alternative projects and Twitter during Gamergate.
“Alternative” began to seem, in many ways, to not be very alternative.</p>

<p>That brings me to the present.</p>

<h2 id="part-4-new-critical-reverse-engineers-on-the-fediverse-2017--present">Part 4: New Critical Reverse Engineers on the Fediverse (2017 – Present)</h2>

<p>The object spoke again, saying things I was unable to hear when I
started my career. I needed to seek new critical reverse engineers.</p>

<p>And that I needed to do the reading in Black philosophy, feminist
theory, and queer media studies: authors like <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/the-case-for-rage-9780197557341">Myisha Cherry</a>, <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1132416482">André
Brock</a>, <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1266907273">Catherine Knight Steele</a>, <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1374489678">Avery Dame-Griff</a>.</p>

<p>It will take a new wave of critical reverse engineers to reveal how
contemporary alternative social media can shed repressive tolerance.</p>

<h3 id="the-struggle-for-the-fediverse">The struggle for the fediverse</h3>

<p>This is, in large part, the focus of <a href="2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">my current book</a>, which examines
Mastodon and the Fediverse.</p>

<p>Because the fediverse includes a wide range of technologies, I focus on
<a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">Mastodon</a>, a microblogging software package that can be installed and run
on modern web servers.</p>

<p>Mastodon provides a window not only into software engineering, but also
social and political interventions – particularly from marginalized
critical reverse engineers – in alternative social media.</p>

<h3 id="from-ostatus-to-activitypub">From OStatus to ActivityPub</h3>

<p>When many people speak about Mastodon, they often place it relation to
Twitter. This predates the Musk takeover of Twitter, but it has
certainly been amplified since then.</p>

<p>Mastodon appears to be an example of critical reverse engineering of
Twitter, and was hailed from its earliest days as such. <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/mastodon-is-like-twitter-without-nazis-so-why-are-we-not-using-it/">“Twitter without
the Nazis”</a> was a common descriptor.</p>

<p>But as I show in my book, Mastodon’s founder, Eugen Rochko, actually meant to critically reverse engineer another alternative, GNU social, in 2016. Mastodon was meant to be an alternative to an alternative. And this brought it into conflict with ideologies of freedom and openness – the ideologies of repressive tolerance.</p>

<p>Mastodon servers were initially able to communicate with GNU social over
a protocol called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OStatus">OStatus</a>. OStatus was a very Web 2.0 technology – it was about openness, the idea
that all of us should participate openly in discussion.</p>

<p>One goal among Mastodon’s developers was to provide safety tools to protect
marginalized folks, particularly queer and trans folks, allowing for users to
address their posts to particular, limited audiences and have more
control over who could reply.</p>

<p>These were features not available in GNU social (or, for that matter,
Twitter).</p>

<p>However, this grated against the everything-must-be-open-and-free ethos
of GNU social.</p>

<p>I won’t go into too much detail here, but one major issue was privacy
violations on the part of GNU social users, who would publicly expose
private posts from queer and trans Mastodon users in the name of
“openness” and “freedom.”</p>

<p>Fortunately, the <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub protocol</a> was being developed in 2016-2017,
and it had more robust privacy capacities. Four of the five authors self-identify
as queer, which might explain the new protocol’s affordances, including the
use of post addressing as a means to protect people.</p>

<p>Mastodon adopted ActivityPub, denying the repressive forms of openness
of OStatus in favor of safety for marginalized people.</p>

<h3 id="codes-of-conduct">Codes of Conduct</h3>

<p>Another anti-repressive tolerance move: the inclusion of codes of
conduct, as advocated for by activists such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coraline_Ada_Ehmke">Coraline Ada Ehmke</a>. Codes
of conduct are important in Mastodon’s history.</p>

<p>Ehmke’s work reflects feminist/trans activism in tech – the struggle
against meritocracy. This struggle emerged from projects like the <a href="https://geekfeminism.fandom.com/wiki/Geek_Feminism_Wiki">Geek Feminism wiki</a>, which
documented misogyny and transphobia at tech conventions.</p>

<p>These practices were cited as the reason why technology – particularly
FOSS technology – has had <a href="https://www.wired.com/2017/06/diversity-open-source-even-worse-tech-overall/">a significant lack of contributions from
women and racialized minorities</a>.</p>

<p>Ehmke and her allies laid the feet of such behavior at the ideology of meritocracy in
tech, where, as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Cathedral_and_the_Bazaar">Eric Raymond argued</a>, the only thing that matters is
great code. Implicitly, being a sexual abuser or racist is ok so long as
you can code.</p>

<p>Other scholars and activists have pointed to <a href="https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/4291">“pushyocracy,”</a> where it’s
not about great code but about who can shout the loudest, as a reason
why marginalized people avoided getting involved in the tech indstury.
(Linus Torvalds has been a key example of this, though he has since
sought forgiveness.)</p>

<p>Instead of meritocracy at tech conventions, Ehmke and her allies have
argued for Codes of Conduct, which have been largely adopted by both
tech conventions and free and open source projects.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/mastodonCovenant.png" alt="The website for the Mastodon server covenant, which includes the requirement for 'active moderation against racism, sexism, homophobia and transphobia.'" />
    <figcaption>
        While the Mastodon server covenant seems rather simple, the idea that a federated network of servers may all agree to things like "active moderation" is a cultural achievement. This is quite different from previous alternative social media.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I show in the book, these Codes have <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/covenant">also been adopted by many
Mastodon servers</a>. I argue these act as fundamental diplomatic documents
in noncentralized social media: codes of conduct help structure
relations on the network. The active association among instances who
share ethical values indicates an ethical consensus is emerging across
the network including values of anti-racism and anti-transphobia.</p>

<h3 id="fediblock-and-blocklists">#Fediblock and Blocklists</h3>

<p>While much of the code of conduct discussion is about shared ethical
values, what about times when fediverse instances violate these
agreements? Another anti-repressive tolerance move can be found among those who
advocate severing connections.</p>

<p>Here I turn to another critical reverse engineer, Ro, founder of an
early Mastodon instance called “Playvicious.social.”</p>

<p>Playvicious was likely the first Black-run instance on Mastodon. But Ro shut it down in 2020, citing racist harassment of the moderators.
You can <a href="https://roiskinda.cool/2023/12/recuerda-pv-chapter-7-the-dark-and-ugly.html">read about it on his blog</a> – but I warn you, it’s heavy.</p>

<p>The Playvicious episode – and many others – reflected what Jonathan Flowers would later call <a href="https://www.techpolicy.press/the-whiteness-of-mastodon/">“the whiteness of
Mastodon,”</a> the deeply embedded practices of whiteness that not only
include overt racism, but the subtle forms philosopher Myisha Cherry
calls “white skepticism” and “white empathy.”</p>

<p>But, to quote Flowers, Black critical reverse engineers continue to
contribute in spite of whiteness. In Ro’s case, he returned to the
network with a new project, a shared blocklist called <a href="https://thebad.space/">The Bad Space</a>.</p>

<p>Blocklists are now <a href="https://about.iftas.org/activities/moderation-as-a-service/fedicheck/">an emergent governance and moderation tool on the
fediverse</a>, enabling independent instances to import lists of known bad
actors and prevent them from interacting with instance members. Ro’s Bad Space isn’t the only project, though it is one that seems to attract the most criticism – recapitulating the Playvicious episode in a new form.</p>

<p>There’s another critical reverse engineer to cite here. Ro took inspiration for his blocklist from former Playvicious moderator
<a href="https://www.artistmarciax.com/">Marcia X</a>. Like many Black feminists, Marcia has contributed to the network,
co-creating a hashtag, #fediblock, for public discussions over how to
block racist instances and accounts on the network.</p>

<p>I’ve put their work into practice. The work of Black critical reverse
engineers has aided me directly – I now help run <a href="https://aoir.social">AoIR.social</a>, the Mastodon
instance for the Association of Internet Researchers, and we rely on
blocklists and #fediblock to prevent racists and transphobes from
interacting with our members.</p>

<h3 id="towards-the-covenantal-fediverse">Towards the Covenantal Fediverse</h3>

<p>Taken as a whole, these new critical reverse engineers have helped bring
about a new form of alternative social media.</p>

<p>It is a form a <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400">colleague and I have called</a> “the covenantal fediverse,” a
non-centralized, large network of small communities that associate
through shared ethical values.</p>

<p>Here is a new normative critical reverse engineering of corporate social
media. Returning to the four orientations of critical reverse engineering, let’s turn back to the normative orientation.</p>

<p>The normative aspect of Mastodon and the covenantal fediverse relates to previous alternative social media. In some ways, the fediverse continues older normative practices. It inherits the anti-surveillance capitalism aspects of previous alternatives, of course. Most of the fediverse operates on a non-capitalist, mutual aid economy. Much of it avoids behavioral advertising.</p>

<p>However, the older cyberlibertarianism is replaced – often in a messy and uneven way – with freedom of association. By accident or design, the Instance is a powerful unit. I would suggest that our understanding of the fediverse <a href="/2024/03/14/Instances-and-Individuals.html">needs to account more heavily for instances-as-communities</a> instead of the individual user (as has been privileged in cyberlibertarian thinking).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-will-this-survive">Conclusion: Will this survive?</h2>
<p>Now I have traced a new form of critical reverse engineering, one
operating on both corporate social media and previous alternative social
media. I believe it is best existing path away from corporate social
media.</p>

<p>And yet, while millions of people took up Mastodon after Musk’s purchase
of Twitter, billions remain on corporate social media.</p>

<p>To return to where I started, even critical media organizations that
speak of non-corporate media continue to use corporate social media!</p>

<p>We might ask “can this platform survive?” as <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4598303">several colleagues from
American University and I do</a> in a forthcoming paper in the <em>International
Journal of Communication</em>.</p>

<p>And my answer is: I don’t know. Many alternative projects have failed.</p>

<p>But let’s again listen to the object. Alternative social media speaks of hope, even
in the face of failure (however we define that idea!). To use a term
from speculative fiction, alternative social media speaks of <em>porvir
otimista.</em></p>

<p>Don’t despair in the face of the sociotechnical systems you confront.
Instead, critically reverse engineer them.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="critical reverse engineering" /><category term="presentations" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently gave a presentation to the Cultural Studies PhD program at George Mason University. That’s the program where I earned my PhD, so it was an honor to come back and talk to my professors as well as some of the new students currently in the program. I took the presentation as an opportunity to reflect on my academic career from my time at Mason (2005-2010) to my latest book project. I’ve modified it for this blog. Take a look at the abstract and, if piques your interest, feel free to read it! (It’s a bit long.) Abstract In my time as a PhD student in GMU’s Cultural Studies program, I learned that I must let my object of study tell me what methods to use to analyze it. I also learned not to merely interpret the object, but seek to change it. Since I chose to study what was then called “Web 2.0” and what I now call “corporate social media,” I needed to bring Marxian political economy, science and technology studies, and software studies to bear on the object. And I began to examine the practices of activists who sought to make something better than corporate social media: alternative social media. Over a decade ago I began my adventures in alternative social media, chasing it through hacker collectives, cyberlibertarian organizations, and even onto the dark web. Through digital ethnography, close examinations of code, and hands-on experience running alternative social media, I developed an approach I call “critical reverse engineering.” Here I present critical reverse engineering as a methodology for activist engagement with digital technologies. To illustrate this approach, I will draw on insights from my forthcoming book, Move Slowly and Build Bridges: Mastodon, the Fediverse, and the Struggle for Ethical Social Media (Oxford, 2025).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goodbye, Firefox?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/18/goodbyeFirefox.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goodbye, Firefox?" /><published>2024-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/18/goodbyeFirefox</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/18/goodbyeFirefox.html"><![CDATA[<p>I think I’m going to stop using Firefox altogether. It was a tiny little weather app that did it.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/firefoxNotDefault.png" alt="Firefox is no longer my default browser, and it has a sad face. I'm sad about it, too." />
  <figcaption>Firefox is no longer my default browser, and it has a sad face. I'm sad about it, too.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>So, one day I opened a new tab in Firefox and there it was: a weather report. A tiny little temp reading for my area. I didn’t think about it much, but someone on the fediverse noted that this little weather app is sponsored by AccuWeather, a company <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-adventure/environment/project-2025-paywall-weather/">long criticized for its attempt to privatize public weather information</a>. Hovering over the little temp reading revealed this to be true – it said, “Sponsored by AccuWeather.”</p>

<p>And that broke me.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>To be fair, it’s not the only thing. <a href="https://connect.mozilla.org/t5/discussions/firefox-changing-my-settings-on-update/m-p/14155">Like others</a>, I’ve started to see privacy settings being reset every time I update Firefox. I set the default search to be Startpage instead of Google – an update wiped that and set it to Google, again. I set my homepage to not have Pocket or sponsored links – an update wiped that.</p>

<p>Pretty soon each new tab suggested I go to Facebook. <em>Fucking Facebook</em>.</p>

<p>Mozilla bashing has become kind of a common sport, so much so that one of my favorite podcasts, <em>Late Night Linux</em>, has gotten bored of doing it. But once I saw the little AccuWeather thingy, I started watching for critical comments on Mozilla. And I saw what many others have already pointed out:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/home-and-office/networking/the-fall-of-firefox-mozillas-once-popular-web-browser-slides-into-irrelevance/">Firefox browser share plummeting in inverse proportion to CEO pay</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/en/mozilla/mozilla-anonym-raising-the-bar-for-privacy-preserving-digital-advertising/">weird ideas about integrating ad-tech</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.mozilla.ai/_">AI bullshit</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/mozilla-social-faq">and an end to the laudable experiment with the fediverse</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>My attitude towards these critical takes has long been to ignore them. “Whatever Mozilla wants to do is fine as long as they make a good browser,” I said to myself. But lately it seems like they’re actively trying to kill off Firefox rather than continuing to make a great browser.</p>

<p>The thing is, with all the papercuts, Firefox is still quite good. But this is FOSS. Forks are a thing. I’m now testing out <a href="https://librewolf.net/">LibreWolf</a>, a privacy-conscious fork of Firefox, and so far, so good.</p>

<p>What’s sad about this, though, is that I’ve been using Firefox for nearly two decades – almost as long as Firefox has been around. It was my <a href="/2020/12/15/FOSS-Journey.html">introduction point into the world of FOSS</a>. First it, then OpenOffice, then Ubuntu, and now I run as much FOSS as I can.</p>

<p>Maybe I will come back to Firefox, but if not, I’m still grateful for its role in my career.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="FALD" /><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="Firefox" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I think I’m going to stop using Firefox altogether. It was a tiny little weather app that did it. Firefox is no longer my default browser, and it has a sad face. I'm sad about it, too. So, one day I opened a new tab in Firefox and there it was: a weather report. A tiny little temp reading for my area. I didn’t think about it much, but someone on the fediverse noted that this little weather app is sponsored by AccuWeather, a company long criticized for its attempt to privatize public weather information. Hovering over the little temp reading revealed this to be true – it said, “Sponsored by AccuWeather.” And that broke me.]]></summary></entry></feed>