<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-08T21:11:08+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hey, Journalists: X is Now Truth Social</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMandTFG.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hey, Journalists: X is Now Truth Social" /><published>2024-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMandTFG</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMandTFG.html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey, journalists, it’s time to get off X. Today. And switch to the fediverse.</p>

<p>Here’s why.</p>

<!-- more -->
<p>When Elon Musk bought Twitter in 2022, rebranded it X, and converted it from the ostensible “public town square” into his own personal right-wing techbro platform, many many people left it for the fediverse.</p>

<p>But a key group did not: journalists. Sure, there was some flirtation with the fediverse, and to be fair, some journalists did make the switch. But many stayed on X, arguing that the audience and the movers and shakers were still there, in spite of Musk’s <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-features/elon-musk-twitter-misinformation-timeline-1235076786/">gutting of content moderation on the platform</a>.</p>

<p>OK, that’s an excuse to stay on X, journalists, but it’s increasingly a flimsy one. Especially today. What excuse do you have now? Now that we’ve seen how <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/social-media/elon-musk-turned-x-trump-echo-chamber-rcna174321">Musk made X into a machine to help propel Trump</a> back into the White House?</p>

<p>By legitimizing X, you’ve legitimized Musk’s insinuation into the halls of power – and you helped fund his efforts. You kept eyes on X, which put eyes on the ads. You kept people’s attention on the rage machine, on the disinformation and conspiracy theories. (And if the first Trump term is any guide, this is all going to get worse.) Enough already.</p>

<p>While you were sticking to X (and probably calling it “Twitter” out of nostalgia) millions of people were working away to make the fediverse a strongly moderated, calmer social media space where people do in fact discuss the news of the day and have <a href="https://medium.com/fedi-curious/lessons-on-the-road-to-reviving-journalism-via-the-fediverse-01b3748cacc5">welcomed journalists and news organizations</a>.</p>

<p>“But the fediverse is hard!” I can hear you protest. “And it would be too much work to have an X account and a fediverse account.”</p>

<p>To which I reply: what about Truth Social?</p>

<p>Since its launch in 2021, <a href="https://www.wbur.org/endlessthread/2024/11/01/truth-social">reporters have signed up for accounts</a> on Truth to access Trump’s ALL CAPS SCREEDS and dutifully post them in news sites in the name of balance. No doubt, journalists will be logging into Truth even more now, since it’s the main source for Trump’s thoughts. After all, <a href="https://theweek.com/donald-trump/1013599/trump-must-post-on-truth-social-before-posting-on-twitter-sec-filing-says">he must post there to keep the stock price inflated</a>.</p>

<p>Maybe I’m wrong, but I doubt reporters are using Truth to engage with audiences or to talk to their friends. They’re using other social media for that. Apparently, then, it’s not hard for reporters to have an account on Truth and still use other social media.</p>

<p>So, say it with me: <strong>X is now Truth Social.</strong> If you must keep an account there, dip into it to see what’s going on (you know, to watch as Trump’s attorney general announces the arrests of his political rivals) and then go back to your fediverse account. Just like you’ve been doing with Truth Social. You dip into Truth, copypaste Trump’s screeds, and get out.</p>

<p>Now, do that with X. Dip in, get out.</p>

<p>And put your energy into something that won’t be bought by a billionaire and converted to a fascism promotion machine.</p>

<h2 id="postscript-what-about-bluesky">Postscript: What about Bluesky?</h2>
<p>To be honest, I go back and forth on Bluesky. I know many people are enthused about Bluesky, particularly because they’re building their own protocol. But their recent <a href="https://bsky.social/about/blog/10-24-2024-series-a">acceptance of venture capital from cryptocurrency investors</a> begs the question: what will Bluesky do when the VC funders demand a return? As Cory Doctorow argues, it will <a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/11/02/ulysses-pact/">likely be something shitty</a>. If you want to put your eggs into another corporate basket, go ahead. It didn’t turn out well the last time.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="journalism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hey, journalists, it’s time to get off X. Today. And switch to the fediverse. Here’s why.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Update for November 8, 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMupdate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update for November 8, 2024" /><published>2024-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/08/ASMupdate.html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/tags/asm update.html">ASM updates</a> are back! Now that I’m done <a href="/2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">drafting my book</a>, I want to get back to doing this regularly.</p>

<p>In this ASM update, here are three things that caught my eye this week. Well, besides that other big thing that happened this week.</p>

<!-- more -->
<h2 id="on-fediblock">On #Fediblock</h2>

<p>One of the most used hashtags on the fediverse is <strong>#fediblock.</strong> Created by Marcia X and Ginger, that hashtag is essential for admins who want to learn about problematic accounts and instances. But the history of fediblock is not well-known. Now, Marcia X has <a href="https://subscriptions.boricua.style/fediblock-a-tiny-history-2/">written a short history</a> to help shed some light. We learn it came out of personal experience: “I started the tag so that bad actors doing quite obvious trolling or isms could just easily posted about to other people with whom I didn’t share a server with could see. Like a serial misogynistic harasser. There were no set rules put in place.”</p>

<h2 id="flatlining">Flatlining?</h2>

<p><a href="https://privacy.thenexus.today/flatness/">Jon Pincus argues</a> that the ActivityPub fediverse is <strong>flatlining,</strong> particularly in relation to Bluesky. He puts the blame on the main Mastodon project, hoping that it changes for the better: “Whether or not there’s a hard fork, the same opportunities are there for the official Mastodon project if its direction and leadership structure evolves. The official project has some big advantages – including funding – so let’s hope that happens. And it’s not an either-or situation; forks don’t have to be hostile, and there are lots of potential synergies if they can work together effectively (as well as challenges).”</p>

<h2 id="but-just-say-no-to-bluesky">But Just Say ‘No’ to Bluesky</h2>

<p>And yet, <a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/11/02/ulysses-pact/">Cory Doctorow notes</a> that he’s not going to ever use Bluesky. “I will never again devote my energies to building up an audience on a platform whose management can sever my relationship to that audience at will.”</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ASM updates are back! Now that I’m done drafting my book, I want to get back to doing this regularly. In this ASM update, here are three things that caught my eye this week. Well, besides that other big thing that happened this week.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">York Circle Lecture: Fleeing Facebook and Exiting X</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/yorkcirclelecture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="York Circle Lecture: Fleeing Facebook and Exiting X" /><published>2024-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/yorkcirclelecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/yorkcirclelecture.html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I gave a presentation at York University in Toronto as part of their York Circle program. The audience was comprised of York alumni.</p>

<p>My presentation was “Fleeing Facebook and Exiting X: How activists show the path away from corporate social media.” Here’s the abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The purchase of Twitter by Elon Musk in 2022, coupled with Meta’s blocking of Canadian news sites, has prompted people in Canada to consider their social media options. Social media has now fragmented, with a small but growing population of people turning to non-corporate, alternative social media, such as Mastodon and the fediverse. This talk will discuss how non-corporate, alternative social media provide Canadians not just with a path away from Facebook or X, but also provide a new way to engage in online democracy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If that sounds interesting, well… read on! This is a version of that presentation, edited into blog form. (Note: this is another long post.)</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h2>

<p>Before I get too far, I want to acknowledge a couple things. First, this research has been supported thanks in part to funding from the Canada First Research Excellence Fund.</p>

<p>Second, some of what I’m going to talk about comes from a collaboration between myself and Alex Martin, who is a PhD student here at York in the Science and Technology Studies program.</p>

<h2 id="introduction-news-and-social-media-in-canada">Introduction: News and Social Media in Canada</h2>

<p>Let’s start this conversation about social media in Regina, Saskatchewan. Specifically, let’s talk about what could be the top news company in Regina. It is, arguably, a garbage company.</p>

<p>According to <a href="https://www.canadaland.com/podcast/1042-the-city-that-gets-its-news-from-a-dumpster-company/"><em>Canadaland</em></a>, the most trafficked news site for Regina
residents is a Facebook page run by Just Bins, a garbage can company. (I also should credit <em>Canadaland</em> another way – I kind of stole this intro from them!)</p>

<p>In fact, the Just Bins Facebook page won a “best of” award for news in Regina.</p>

<p>This isn’t to say there is no local paper. But the local paper, the <em>Regina Leader Post</em>, is seeing dramatic drops in circulation and no longer prints the paper locally.</p>

<p>That news reporting in Canada is in a crisis is not new, but it is certainly getting worse. Layoffs abound.</p>

<p>One major issue has been Meta. Because of the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/canadian-heritage/services/online-news.html">Online News Act</a>, Meta has now refused to let people link to Canadian news in Facebook and Instagram. This is in part what led to Just Bins Facebook page being able to become the top news site in Regina. As Jesse Brown of <em>Canadaland</em> said, “It appalls me that [Just Bins] can build a massive audience specifically because [it’s] not news. I can’t publish to Facebook, and [they] can <em>because</em> [it’s] not news.”</p>

<p>Regardless of how you feel about the Online News Act, it is coming from the recognition that a handful of media corporations have too much power over Canadian news. Let me put this a different way. Another, albeit different case in point: Elon Musk’s X. Unlike Meta, news organizations are certainly welcome on X. But at what price? As <a href="https://www.disinfo.eu/publications/disinformation-on-x/">multiple</a> <a href="https://www.isi.edu/news/55932/new-twitter-now-with-more-hate/">studies</a> and <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/musk-lashes-out-at-advertisers-leaving-x-over-rise-in-hate-speech">news reports</a> are finding, disinformation, trolling, and harassment are on the rise on X. And often the disinformation and trolling comes from the top, such as when Musk labeled the CBC as <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/cbc-twitter-label-69-government-funded-media-elon-musk-2023-4">“69% government funded”</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-do-we-go">Where do we go?</h2>
<p>Meta and X have me wondering: Where do we go if we want to leave Facebook or X?</p>

<p>What about TikTok? LinkedIn? Reddit? Maybe. But all of these share in the same basic problem: they are all social media that is controlled by for-profit companies that, at the end of the day, make their money by monitoring our lives. They can be bought and sold.</p>

<p>I’ve been researching this question – where do we go? – for my entire academic career, from my days as a PhD student in the 2000s to the writing of my first book, <em><a href="https://tupress.temple.edu/books/reverse-engineering-social-media">Reverse Engineering Social Media</a></em> in 2014 to today, when I am finalizing my fourth book, <em>Move Slowly and Build Bridges</em>, for Oxford. (For more on my academic career, <a href="/2024/10/18/GMUpresentation.html">see this post</a>)</p>

<p>The answer to the “where do we go?” question has been given for many, many years by people I have been calling “critical reverse engineers.” These are activists who take apart corporate social media – Facebook, Instagram, Twitter/X, YouTube – to make something better. I have interviewed dozens of these critical reverse engineers, studied the code and interfaces of the systems they’ve built, and have even operated some of the social media they’ve created.</p>

<p>It turns out that quite a few of these critical reverse engineers are right here in Canada.</p>

<p>Let me say a bit more about critical reverse engineering. And to do that, I should talk quickly about reverse engineering in general.</p>

<p>Basically, reverse engineering is forward engineering in reverse. Rather than starting with plans and them implementing them in material objects, reverse engineers start with the material object and seek to figure out how it works, often discovering clues about the creators’ intentions.</p>

<p>Reverse engineers do this work for a range of purposes. It might be to make a competing project – a famous example here is the reverse engineering of the IBM PC in the 1980s. Or it might be for military purposes, reverse engineering captured equipment – a famous case is that of the Russian Tu-4 bomber, which was a reverse engineered US B-29.</p>

<p>Now, these aren’t particularly critical. I’m using “critical” in the sense of critical theory – the examination of power in society, with the goal of making a more just and ethical society.</p>

<p>And I think that social media admits to critical inquiry. Social media has had a major impact on how we live our lives. We can talk about the benefits of social media. It has been used by social justice movements (Idle No More, Me Too, Black Lives Matter). There’s the simple pleasures of sharing and connection. And there’s local and global news sharing. And we can also talk about its harms: Facebook’s emotional contagion experiments. The Cambridge Analytica scandal. Gamergate harassment on Twitter. And concerns over mental health, particularly of teens.</p>

<p>There’s a lot at stake when we consider social media. So, let’s consider reverse engineering social media, but not just to make competing products. I am interested in activists who are reverse engineering social media to create systems that are better than the corporate versions – alternatives that are under our control, that push away some of the negative aspects of corporate social media away in favor of more beneficial aspects. I have been studying projects that produce new innovations in social media outside of the predominantly Silicon Valley model.</p>

<h2 id="the-fediverse-innovations-and-canada">The fediverse, innovations, and Canada</h2>

<p>Specifically, I will highlight the fediverse – social media that is comprised of thousands of small community-run social media sites linked together in a global network. As a project that critically reverse engineers corporate social media, the fediverse brings about many innovations.</p>

<p>I will talk about four such innovations:</p>
<ul>
  <li>a new topology</li>
  <li>no surveillance capitalism</li>
  <li>ecological innovations</li>
  <li>online democracy</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="a-new-topology-noncentralized">A New Topology: Noncentralized</h2>

<p>I argue the fediverse provides a new way of doing social media, one that’s not centralized or concentrated.</p>

<p>I say new, but really what I’m going to say is quite similar to email. Email is federated. If I have an account on Protonmail, and a friend has an account on Gmail, and another runs their own server using Roundcube software, we can all still contact each other. We can do so in spite of the fact that all three are provided by different organizations in different locations.</p>

<p>This is because email runs on a shared, standardized protocol called Send Mail Transfer Protocol, or SMTP. SMTP dates back to the early 1980s.</p>

<p>Much more recently, critical reverse engineers have created a social media protocol that works much like email, but for social data. It works like this. Let’s say I’m using a system called PeerTube, which is a video-sharing service. I can connect to someone using Pixelfed, which is an image-sharing service. And that person can connect to someone on a Mastodon server, which is a Twitter-like system. And so on.</p>

<p>This is possible because of a new standard called <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub</a>, which, a bit like email, presents social data in the form of inboxes and outboxes. The ActivityPub protocol was authored by Christine Lemmer-Webber, Jessica Tallon, Erin Shepherd, Amy Guy, and Evan Prodromou. Here’s a Canadian connection! Evan Prodromou, who has been actively working on social media alternative since the late 2000s, is a Canadian. Thanks to Prodromou, Lemmer-Webber, and the rest of the creators of this protocol, we now have a global network of interconnected social media servers.</p>

<p>And, as a testament to their engineering feat, consider the fact that the ActivityPub-based fediverse was able to absorb a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/news/datablog/2023/jan/08/elon-musk-drove-more-than-a-million-people-to-mastodon-but-many-arent-sticking-around">massive wave of new users happening in late 2022</a> – that is, right when Musk finalized his purchase of Twitter.</p>

<p>The upsides of this noncentralized system are twofold. For one, it’s less vulnerable to being simply taken over (e.g., as in the case of Twitter/X). Second, it is open to many groups participating in running their own social media.</p>

<h2 id="no-surveillance-capitalism">No Surveillance Capitalism</h2>

<p>As for the refusal to engage in surveillance capitalism, consider <a href="https://mstdn.ca/explore">Mstdn.ca</a>, a Mastodon server that provides Twitter-like features
to Canadians.</p>

<p>If you’re considering joining Mstdn.ca, you might notice that they ask for donations. Why? Well, they don’t sell advertising space. Unlike corporate social media, which is in the business of selling our attention to advertisers, Mstdn.ca does not sell user data. This is typical of the rest of the fediverse.</p>

<p>In my study of Mastodon and the rest of the fediverse, I’ve found that the vast majority of instances use donations or other mutual aid-style approaches to funding. They use a variety of nonprofit organizational structures, from informal to formal. And Mastodon and fediverse software do not include the tools needed to do targeted, surveillance-based advertising.</p>

<p>There are some possible upsides here. Since people cannot buy advertising space, there’s far less incentive to promote outrageous, attention-grabbing posts. Moreover, current disinformation practices rely in part on the ability to buy targeted advertisements – you can do that on Facebook and Youtube, but you cannot do that on the fediverse.</p>

<p>I should note I say “possible” because I think it is early to tell if these advantages will play out. However, in my interviews with fediverse users, they do report that they have a calmer experience on the fediverse. In addition, I am part of a group of researchers monitoring the fediverse for disinformation – a big concern as we head into a US presidential election – and so far, so good on that front.</p>

<h2 id="ecological-innovations">Ecological innovations</h2>

<p>On to ecological innovations. The brute fact is that, in spite of the promise that digital media will be light and airy, digital media is having a massive impact on the climate. Social media data centers – and the turn to generative AI – are <a href="https://direct.mit.edu/glep/article/24/2/9/120588/Generative-AI-and-Social-Media-May-Exacerbate-the">straining energy systems</a>. And data centers are <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/2023/04/25/data-centers-drought-water-use/">notorious for their demands for drinking water</a>. Speaking as someone who has lived in both the US and Canadian Rockies, this is a major concern of mine.</p>

<p>Let’s say people leave behind X and Facebook for the fediverse. Will the fediverse replicate these issues? Not necessarily. Because the fediverse is community-run, it is possible for groups to experiment with it to reduce its energy and water demands.</p>

<p>Consider the work of <a href="https://www.trentu.ca/culturalstudies/faculty-research/undergraduate-faculty/anne-pasek">Anne Pasek of Trent University</a>. Anne and her colleagues are developing solar-powered fediverse social media.</p>

<p>This isn’t far-fetched. A few years ago, an online publication called <a href="https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/">Low Tech Magazine</a> demonstrated that it is possible for a website to be powered by a small solar panel. Likewise, Pasek and her colleagues are working on powering a fediverse server with a small, consumer-grade solar panel.</p>

<p>This is experimental. Time will tell if it works. But if projects like Anne’s are successful, we could see a reduction in the carbon footprint of social media.</p>

<p>In addition, I can say that there are some clear ecological benefits to the fediverse when we compare it to corporate social media. I mentioned previously that the fediverse avoids surveillance capitalism. This does mean that, right out of the box, the fediverse should have less ecological impact than corporate social media, since it does not require the infrastructure of behavioral advertising.</p>

<h2 id="online-democracy">Online Democracy</h2>

<p>Finally, let’s talk online democracy. Here I’d point to <a href="https://cosocial.ca/explore">Cosocial.ca</a>. This is a social media site run by Canadian cooperative organization. As a collective, Cosocial members have developed their own, <a href="https://cosocial.ca/about">local moderation rules</a>.</p>

<p>Here’s a sampling of their code:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Treat all persons fairly and with respect, courtesy and dignity.</li>
  <li>Be sensitive to cultural and social differences and practices.</li>
  <li>Be careful in your use of language that may be disrespectful or demeaning.”</li>
  <li>They also have prohibitions against racism, transphobia, and violence.</li>
</ul>

<p>This can work because Cosocial is not large – it has 100 active members. It’s much easier to have such a code of conduct for a small number of folks.</p>

<p>So, you might think: 100 people? That’s not a lot. That’s nothing compared to corporate social media!</p>

<p>But Cosocial isn’t alone. Cosocial can connect to another Canadian instance, <a href="https://ottawa.place/about">Ottawa.place</a>. Like Cosocial, Ottawa.place has a code of conduct with similar values. So those two can connect without clashing about their ethical values.</p>

<p>And Cosocial and Ottawa.place can connect to another instance, <a href="https://scholar.social/about">Scholar.social</a>. Scholar.social is a well-moderated, large instance run by a person in Montreal. Like the others, Scholar.social has a similar code of conduct. And all these servers can connect to others in Canada.</p>

<p>But this isn’t just in Canada. These servers can connect others located around the world, forming a global network. And if they connect to other servers with similar codes of conduct, we see an emergent set of ethical values. This network of servers share a commitment to active moderation, not only against racism or transphobia, but also against disinformation. Studies are showing that there is a shared set of ethical values across much of the fediverse. I think this is most exciting aspect.</p>

<p>This is a structure a co-author and I call “<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400">the covenantal fediverse</a>”: a global network of ethically-aligned digital communities.</p>

<p>Here, we get the benefits of locally-run and moderated systems, but with the reach of a global network.</p>

<h2 id="but-what-about-news-in-canada">But What About News in Canada?</h2>

<p>But what about news? I started out with a note about the sorry state     of news in Canada – including a discussion about social media’s role in news sharing. Can Canadians share and receive news on federated, non-corporate social media?</p>

<p>This is an area Alex Martin, a PhD student, is working on. The short answer is: yes, Canadians can share and are sharing news on the fediverse.</p>

<p>Alex has taken the lead in a research project where we interview Canadians who are running or using federated social media. A big question Alex is asking: are Canadians sharing news on the fediverse? And what sorts of news are they sharing?</p>

<p>We’re hearing Canadians across the country note that the fediverse has become a viable source of breaking news. This includes local happenings as well as global events. And we’re also discovering people and groups who recognize this and want to make local federated social media so that people can share news.</p>

<p>What about news organizations? This is emerging, too, albeit a bit slower. <a href="https://mstdn.ca/@thetyee">The Tyee</a>, <a href="https://flipboard.com/@ConversationCA">Conversation Canada</a>, <a href="https://mstdn.ca/@thenarwhal">The Narwhal</a>, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@livewirecalgary">Livewire Calgary</a>, and <a href="https://medium.com/@marilync/canadian-journalism-on-mastodon-15eeb4f5b9df">a host of journalists</a> are posting to the fediverse.</p>

<p>I think there really ought to be more. In addition, both <a href="https://theconversation.com/canadas-public-broadcaster-should-use-mastodon-to-provide-a-social-media-service-194116">Fen McKelvey of Concordia University and I</a> have argued the CBC should set up their own presence on the fediverse. They could establish a server and provide their journalists with accounts. Those journalists could post to the network and have global reach while at the same time being on a server run under CBC standards – not under the standards of Elon Musk.</p>

<p>Were the CBC to start their own fediverse server, they wouldn’t be alone. Globally, there are public news organizations starting to operate their own fediverse servers – most notably, the BBC has experimented with <a href="https://theconversation.com/canadas-public-broadcaster-should-use-mastodon-to-provide-a-social-media-service-194116">its own Mastodon server</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The fediverse has a great deal of potential for Canadian social media:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Canadians are, right now, running their own social media
        outside of the dominant Silicon Valley systems.</li>
  <li>They can moderate and govern themselves locally, and yet
        have access not only to the rest of Canada but the rest of
        the world</li>
  <li>They can experiment with solutions to the climate crisis</li>
  <li>They can stave off the privacy violations of surveillance
        capitalism</li>
  <li>And they can share both local and global news</li>
</ul>

<p>In other words, Canadians are doing the work of critically reverse engineering social media, and are showing folks a            possible path away from X or Facebook.</p>

<p>This isn’t to say that the fediverse is a flawless system. I present plenty of criticisms of it in my book. But given the growing set of problems posed not just in Canada, but globally, but corporate social media, I believe serious scholarship that highlights the fediverse and critical reverse engineering is needed.</p>

<p>Incidentally, if you’re Canadian and want to try the fediverse, here are a couple options to look at. <a href="https://mstdn.ca/auth/sign_up">Mstdn.ca is open for registrations</a>. Or, if you want a more regional/localized instance, the <a href="https://mastodonserver.ca/">Mastodon Server
site</a> has a list.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="goal 2" /><category term="presentations" /><category term="journalism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday, I gave a presentation at York University in Toronto as part of their York Circle program. The audience was comprised of York alumni. My presentation was “Fleeing Facebook and Exiting X: How activists show the path away from corporate social media.” Here’s the abstract: The purchase of Twitter by Elon Musk in 2022, coupled with Meta’s blocking of Canadian news sites, has prompted people in Canada to consider their social media options. Social media has now fragmented, with a small but growing population of people turning to non-corporate, alternative social media, such as Mastodon and the fediverse. This talk will discuss how non-corporate, alternative social media provide Canadians not just with a path away from Facebook or X, but also provide a new way to engage in online democracy. If that sounds interesting, well… read on! This is a version of that presentation, edited into blog form. (Note: this is another long post.)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From reverse engineering to building bridges: adventures in alternative social media</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/GMUpresentation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From reverse engineering to building bridges: adventures in alternative social media" /><published>2024-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/GMUpresentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/GMUpresentation.html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently gave a presentation to the <a href="https://culturalstudies.gmu.edu/">Cultural Studies PhD program at George Mason University</a>. That’s the program where I earned my PhD, so it was an honor to come back and talk to my professors as well as some of the new students currently in the program.</p>

<p>I took the presentation as an opportunity to reflect on my academic career from my time at Mason (2005-2010) to my <a href="/2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">latest book project</a>. I’ve modified it for this blog. Take a look at the abstract and, if piques your interest, feel free to read it! (It’s a bit long.)</p>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>In my time as a PhD student in GMU’s Cultural Studies program, I learned
that I must let my object of study tell me what methods to use to
analyze it. I also learned not to merely interpret the object, but seek
to change it. Since I chose to study what was then called “Web 2.0” and
what I now call “corporate social media,” I needed to bring Marxian
political economy, science and technology studies, and software studies
to bear on the object. And I began to examine the practices of activists
who sought to make something better than corporate social media:
alternative social media. Over a decade ago I began my adventures in
alternative social media, chasing it through hacker collectives,
cyberlibertarian organizations, and even onto the dark web. Through
digital ethnography, close examinations of code, and hands-on experience
running alternative social media, I developed an approach I call
“critical reverse engineering.” Here I present critical reverse
engineering as a methodology for activist engagement with digital
technologies. To illustrate this approach, I will draw on insights from
my forthcoming book, <em>Move Slowly and Build Bridges: Mastodon, the
Fediverse, and the Struggle for Ethical Social Media</em> (Oxford, 2025).</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="introduction-do-we-call-it-x-or-twitter">Introduction: Do we call it X or Twitter?</h2>

<p>Is it X? Or is it Twitter?</p>

<p>Because I’ve heard media critics use both names, even well after Musk bought
Twitter in 2022.</p>

<p>I hear media critics say, “X is out of control. It’s full of
disinformation and pornbots. Musk is slowly destroying it, indicating
the fundamental problem of billionaires owning social media.”</p>

<p>And then, I often hear those same media critics tell their readers and
listeners, “Please follow me on Twitter.”</p>

<p>It’s “X” when you hate it and “Twitter” when you love it.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/democracynow.webp" alt="A screenshot of the Democracy Now website, showing stories critical of Elon Musk, yet allowing you to share the story on Musk's X." />
    <figcaption>
        While Democracy Now! is critiquing Elon Musk, they still contribute to his bottom line by using Musk's X.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This screenshot of <em>Democracy Now!</em> doesn’t quite illustrate my point,
but it gets close. Here are stories about billionaire media owners – including Elon Musk – who run
amok. But please do follow us on the very platforms we decry.</p>

<p>This encapsulates the contradictions of corporate social media: we may
complain about them, about surveillance capitalism, exploitation of our
sociality, algorithms that push content on us, about addiction.</p>

<p>And yet we also believe they are the only tool we have to speak up, to
organize, or more humbly, to connect and share with our friends.</p>

<h3 id="leaving-corporate-social-media">Leaving Corporate Social Media</h3>

<p>In contrast, my career has largely been dedicated to the idea that we
can and must leave corporate social media behind. That we can maintain
their pleasures while effectively taking them over. For over a decade now, I’ve been talking to activists and technologists seeking to make something better than X or Facebook.</p>

<p>This presentation is a bit of a reflection on my academic career and how I came to study alternative social media. It starts with my time in Cultural Studies at Mason (2005-2010), then the
period around the writing of my first book, <a href="https://tupress.temple.edu/books/reverse-engineering-social-media"><em>Reverse Engineering Social
Media</em></a> a decade ago, and culminating in my current book, <em>Move Slowly
and Build Bridges,</em> which should come out next year.</p>

<p>My plan for this is roughly chronological:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Part 1: Cultural Studies and Web 2.0</li>
  <li>Part 2: Seeking Critical Reverse Engineers</li>
  <li>Part 3: Adventures in Alternative Social Media</li>
  <li>Part 4: New Critical Reverse Engineers on the Fediverse</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="part-1-gmu-cultural-studies-web-20-2005--2010">Part 1: GMU Cultural Studies, Web 2.0 (2005 – 2010)</h2>

<p>Thinking back, what I learned during my time in the Cultural Studies PhD progam at Mason were two lessons:</p>

<ul>
  <li>First, what does the object of study need you to do to understand
it? How does the object demand particular methodologies?</li>
  <li>Second, “<a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1845/theses/theses.htm">the point is to change it</a>.” That is, the point of our work is to make a better world.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="finding-an-object-web-20">Finding an Object: Web 2.0</h3>
<p>First I needed an object of study.</p>

<p>I came to the object of my study during a class with GMU Cultural Studies professor <a href="https://historyarthistory.gmu.edu/people/alandsb1">Alison Landsberg</a>.
She said, “someone ought to take a look at Youtube,” in her Visual Cultures class.</p>

<p>At the time, YouTube was making headlines because of its eye-popping <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/id/wbna15196982">sale to Google for $1.65 billion USD</a>.</p>

<p>Like many people, professor Landsberg was perhaps wondering how a relatively obscure website could be sold for such a sum. Prior to Google’s purchase, YouTube was best known as a place where people either <a href="https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2799/2577">uploaded pirated videos</a> or made “vlogs,” personal, self-confessional
video blogs (as well as “vlogs” that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonelygirl15">turned out to be fictional, yet compelling</a>).</p>

<p>The users had made YouTube what it was – contributing videos, commenting on them, building a culture. Were they getting a cut of the $1.65 billion?</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/battelleoreilly.jpg" alt="John Battelle and Tim O'Reilly at the Web 2.0 summit" />
    <figcaption>
        John Battelle and Tim O'Reilly at the Web 2.0 summit. My understanding is that we may be on Web3 now. Or Web 4.0. Or Web 10.0. I'm not even sure anymore.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The case of YouTube led me to what at the time was called <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/pub/a/web2/archive/what-is-web-20.html">Web 2.0</a>, where, as Tim
O’Reilly and John Batelle argued in 2004, users of digital technologies do the work of building businesses. Where users create data – about the world, and about themselves – that companies can harvest for new ideas and profit.</p>

<p>Were Youtube’s users getting a cut, then? No. From a note I took around the time, I wrote “These companies ask us to build them, and then expect us to consume their products, without compensation beyond a ‘richer’ user experience.”</p>

<p>And of course I wasn’t the first to say this – <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/social-text/article-abstract/18/2%20(63)/33/33433/Free-LaborPRODUCING-CULTURE-FOR-THE-DIGITAL?redirectedFrom=fulltext">Tiziana Terranova had already theorized free labor</a> in digital media, and <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/international-review-of-social-history/article/emerging-sources-of-labor-on-the-internet-the-case-of-america-online-volunteers/56D287B6007BCF167FC254EF4ED166CF">many others</a> had taken
up that concept.</p>

<p>Now of course many people recognize what’s going on, and call this “surveillance capitalism.” It’s an idea so recognizable that even the <a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/09/ftc-staff-report-finds-large-social-media-video-streaming-companies-have-engaged-vast-surveillance">US Federal Trade Commission has just now noticed it happening</a>!</p>

<p>Welcome to the party, FTC. We’ve been talking about this since the 2000s.</p>

<h3 id="methods-marxian-political-economy-science-and-technology-studies-and-software-studies">Methods: Marxian political economy, science and technology studies, and software studies</h3>

<p>So my object became Web 2.0, or surveillance capitalism, or specifically what I now call <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/2056305115604338">corporate social media</a>.</p>

<p>What methods could I bring to bear?</p>

<p>These are digital technologies and they involve communicative practices, and they are embedded deeply in capitalism. They rely upon user-generated content – that is, freely given labor – to produce valuable digital artifacts that attract attention.</p>

<p>The object spoke, and one thing it said to me was “use Marxian political economy to understand me.” <a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1857/grundrisse/">Marx’s <em>Grundrisse</em></a> turned out to be valuable – particularly as <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/0950238032000114868">Stuart Hall</a>] and <a href="https://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/?id=p067952">Nick Dyer-Witheford</a> had interpreted it.</p>

<p>The object also told me to use science and technology studies – particularly conceptions of heterogeneity found in the work of <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/books/book/2030/ComplexitiesSocial-Studies-of-Knowledge-Practices">John Law and and
Annemarie Mol</a>.</p>

<p>And because Web 2.0 relies on software, I also turned to <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262062749/software-studies/">software studies</a> to help understand the underlying digital and material layers of Web 2.0. In particular, I turned to analysis of software engineering as a practice, especially the <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/social-text/article/30/2%20(111)/99/33725/Real-Software-AbstractionsOn-the-Rise-of-Facebook">specific ideas of abstraction</a> in software engineering.</p>

<p>Together, the above gave me conceptual tools to decompose Web 2.0 – what I now would call “corporate social media” – and engage in a critical approach to technology, using concepts such as <em>labor, value, exploitation, abstraction</em>, and <em>engineering</em>.</p>

<h3 id="the-point-is-to-change-it">The Point is to Change It</h3>

<p>But, taking a cue from <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/22860236">Andrew Feenberg</a>, it is not simply enough to
decompose the object with concepts.</p>

<p>As <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2470750">I write elsewhere</a> (basically paraphrasing Feenberg), “Rather than
start with an ideal and bemoaning a world that doesn't live up to it, critical theory seeks out contradictions within the objects it
encounters. These fissures provide us with tangible ways forward, new possibilities that are not simply abstract, timeless ethical ideals.”</p>

<p>Again: this is the other lesson I received from my time at Mason. The point is to change it.</p>

<p>But how could I help change it? I was an English major. Particularly back during my PhD studies, I was not skilled in coding. I was not (and largely still am not) “technical.”</p>

<p>But I could look for people – activists, technologists – who were challenging the rising corporate domination of the internet.</p>

<h2 id="part-2-seeking-critical-reverse-engineers-2008--2014">Part 2: Seeking Critical Reverse Engineers (2008 – 2014)</h2>

<p>My PhD studies led me to the study of people I call “critical reverse engineers,” activists who are taking apart the technologies we face, learning how
they work, and building better systems.</p>

<p>First, I’ll say a bit more about how I’m thinking about critical reverse engineering. Examining the technical literature on reverse engineering, <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2470750">I argue</a> that
a critical form of reverse engineering involves the four following orientations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pragmatic</li>
  <li>Genealogical</li>
  <li>Legal</li>
  <li>Normative</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-pragmatic-orientation">The Pragmatic Orientation</h3>

<p>Reverse engineers do not imagine an ideal technology. Instead, they start with existing technical objects, taking them apart to see how they
have been constructed.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/hacf_re.jpg" alt="A scene from the TV show Halt and Catch Fire. Two men are in a garage. They are looking into an open computer." />
    <figcaption>
        In Season 1 of the AMC show Halt and Catch Fire, two characters reverse engineered an IBM PC to make a new computer.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>A scene from the AMC show <em>Halt and Catch Fire</em> illustrates this. A
two-person team set out to make a new computer called The Giant. Instead
of building the ideal machine, they simply reverse-engineered the IBM PC
to make a PC clone.</p>

<p>As that scene illustrates, a great deal of this process entails the
discovery of 'facts' discerned through thick, close, detailed
empirical analysis of technical objects. How does the technology work?
What is it comprised of? Who built it? What might their intentions have
been? What can we do with it?</p>

<h3 id="genealogical">Genealogical</h3>

<p>Drawing on Foucauldian thinking, particularly as interpreted by <a href="https://iupress.org/9780253006233/genealogy-as-critique/">Colin Koopman</a>,
I argue that there is a genealogical aspect to reverse engineering.</p>

<p>That is, “reverse engineering” is “forward engineering” in reverse. Engineering typically is a process of developing abstract requirements,
then specification documents, and then the specifications are implemented in material.</p>

<p>Reverse engineering starts with the implemented object and then moves backward towards abstract conceptions that may have preceded.</p>

<p>In addition, a reverse engineer engages in what <a href="https://noehernandezcortez.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/nietzsche-genealogy-history.pdf">Foucault might call</a> the “gray, meticulous, and patiently documentary” work of poring through comments in code, scrounging for specification documents, or studying the discourses of the organization that created the object under scrutiny.</p>

<h3 id="legal">Legal</h3>

<p>The familiar caveat: I am not a lawyer!</p>

<p>But, according to legal scholars who look at reverse engineering – particularly <a href="https://www.yalelawjournal.org/article/the-law-and-economics-of-reverse-engineering">Pamela Samuelson</a> – reverse engineering has a tradition of legal protections in contexts such as the United States and the European Union. In traditional manufacturing, U.S. courts have held that the sale of an object is akin to its publication, and thus the legal owner of any object is free to take it apart, study it, and even produce a copy of it for sale.</p>

<p>This situation is a bit more complex with software. Lines of code are protected by copyright; I cannot copy lines of code from a
copyrighted program into a new program. But in terms of the functional side, unless it has been protected by a patent, we are free to replicate
the functionality of existing software. And in order to do that, we are in fact allowed to open up, probe, test, and disassemble software –
even to make copies of it in the process.</p>

<h3 id="normative">Normative</h3>

<p>However, none of the above is necessarily critical. Someone can reverse engineer a technology merely to make a competing product.</p>

<p>To become “critical reverse engineering,” we need a critical, normative approach – we need ethics. That is, we disassemble technical artifacts, produce knowledge from that disassembly, and construct new artifacts that further efforts towards economic and social justice.</p>

<p>So I have been seeking activists engaged in critical reverse engineering of corporate social media – people who are pragmatic in their relation to technology, use genealogical thinking, exercise their rights to reverse engineer, and do so to make a better world.</p>

<h2 id="part-3-adventures-in-alternative-social-media-2010--2016">Part 3: Adventures in Alternative Social Media (2010 – 2016)</h2>

<p>Seeking out critical reverse engineers of corporate social media set me
off on adventures in alternative social media in the years 2010-2016.</p>

<p>Most of the alternatives <a href="https://twentysix.fibreculturejournal.org/fcj-190-building-a-better-twitter-a-study-of-the-twitter-alternatives-gnu-social-quitter-rstat-us-and-twister/">I studied</a> were Twitter alternatives, such as GNU social and Twister.</p>

<p><a href="https://gnusocial.network/">GNU social</a> is a microblogging system that is free to download, install,
and run. It was was developed by Free Software activists who want to eliminate
proprietary software. It is federated (more on this in a bit).</p>

<p><a href="http://twister.net.co/">Twister</a> was a fascinating case – made by Miguel Freitas, a Brazilian
software engineer who wanted to provide protesters with censorship-resistant microblogging. He developed a peer-to-peer version of Twitter using both blockchain and bittorrent-style technologies.</p>

<p>I <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2955827">also studied</a> Facebook alternatives, such as <a href="https://diasporafoundation.org/">diaspora</a>. diaspora was inspired by a presentation from law professor Eben Moglen to a bunch of NYU students in 2010 – so keep this in mind as you
present your research – technologists may be listening!</p>

<p>And <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1461444814554900">my work even took me onto the dark web</a> – networks where both
readers and producers of websites are anonymized. I studied several dark web social networking systems, where people relied on pseudonyms to engage in social media activities. Many of these systems run on the anonymizing <a href="https://www.torproject.org/">Tor network</a>, but I found examples on <a href="https://geti2p.net/en/">I2P</a> and <a href="https://www.hyphanet.org/index.html">Freenet</a>, as well. Indeed, this work led me to write <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262038263/weaving-the-dark-web/">a book about the dark web</a>.</p>

<p>So, how are these critical reverse engineering projects? Let’s go back to the four orientations. These projects are</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Pragmatic</em>: They very often emulate Twitter, since Twitter’s
functionality is decidedly recognizable as social media but is
relatively simple to implement.</li>
  <li><em>Genealogical:</em> Not only do they examine corporate social media and
work back towards the original requirements, they also tend to be
built in reaction to the constant changes made to corporate social
media</li>
  <li><em>Legal:</em> They rely on the rights of reverse engineering. Freitas in particular talked to me about clean-room
requirements engineering.</li>
  <li><em>Normative</em>: All of these projects make claims to being more ethical
than corporate social media for a variety of reasons.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="critiques-of-their-normative-stances">Critiques of their normative stances</h3>
<p>However, I began to notice some shortcomings in that last, normative aspect.</p>

<p>One major reason the activists develop these systems is to shun surveillance capitalism. That’s obviously hugely important.</p>

<p>But the overarching philosophy of many of these projects is a very particular version of “freedom” that results in less just outcomes.</p>

<p>As I mention above, GNU social was developed by the Free Software Foundation, which touts Free Software and the “Four Freedoms.” These relate in part to freedom of speech, particularly in the face of government restrictions. Along for ride are discourses about openness and cyberlibertarian governance.</p>

<p>This program is extremely individual-centric. Taken to its extreme, it is about the eradication of the network in favor of the completely
sovereign individual. The desire seems to be an unfettered subject capable of wielding technology to openly speaking to anyone, anywhere.</p>

<p>Or, as Andrew Ross says in <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40068391">a critique of free software</a>, “Voices proclaiming freedom in every direction, but justice in none.” (I’m taking him a bit out of context, but I think it’s fair.)</p>

<p>There are many consequences of this freedom myopia.</p>

<p>One consequence of this is that it raises the specter of what the philosopher Herbert Marcuse called <a href="https://www.marcuse.org/herbert/publications/1960s/1965-repressive-tolerance-fulltext.html">“repressive tolerance,”</a> where the speech of the marginalized is eradicated through being made equal to
the speech of the dominant.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/bluelm.jpg" alt="The Blue Lives Matter flag flying in front of a banner that says 'Black Lives Matter.'" />
    <figcaption>
        This is the most visually coherent example of repressive tolerance I can think of. By stating "Blue lives matter," the ideas of the Black Lives Matter movement become eradicated by being placed on equal footing to those who are already in power -- the police.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>While Marcuse supplies good examples from the 1960s, I explain repressive tolerance to students using the example of the utterance
“Blue Lives Matter” – a means to eradicate the Black Lives Matter movement by placing those already in power on an equal footing to Black
victims of police violence.</p>

<p>We saw this play out in the US and elsewhere in the form of the Alt-Right – <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262549417/gaming-democracy/">Adrienne Massanari has done excellent work</a> linking Gamergate, Silicon Valley ideologies, and rising fascism in the USA. The desire of repressive tolerance is to eradicate the presence of women, gender minorities, or racialized minorities from technical, leisure, and political spaces by maintaining the status quo.</p>

<p>We can also see repressive tolerance at work in the validation of the internet Edgelord – a phenomenon <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262529877/this-is-why-we-cant-have-nice-things/">best explored by Whitney Phillips</a>.</p>

<p>We saw the Gamergate and alt-right movements gain a great deal of traction on Twitter, but the fact is that they have also had a dominant presence on
alternative social media, as well, particularly those that have a sociotechnical imaginary of freedom and openness.</p>

<p>The brute fact is, it became increasingly difficult for me to find daylight between many of the alternative projects and Twitter during Gamergate.
“Alternative” began to seem, in many ways, to not be very alternative.</p>

<p>That brings me to the present.</p>

<h2 id="part-4-new-critical-reverse-engineers-on-the-fediverse-2017--present">Part 4: New Critical Reverse Engineers on the Fediverse (2017 – Present)</h2>

<p>The object spoke again, saying things I was unable to hear when I
started my career. I needed to seek new critical reverse engineers.</p>

<p>And that I needed to do the reading in Black philosophy, feminist
theory, and queer media studies: authors like <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/the-case-for-rage-9780197557341">Myisha Cherry</a>, <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1132416482">André
Brock</a>, <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1266907273">Catherine Knight Steele</a>, <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1374489678">Avery Dame-Griff</a>.</p>

<p>It will take a new wave of critical reverse engineers to reveal how
contemporary alternative social media can shed repressive tolerance.</p>

<h3 id="the-struggle-for-the-fediverse">The struggle for the fediverse</h3>

<p>This is, in large part, the focus of <a href="2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">my current book</a>, which examines
Mastodon and the Fediverse.</p>

<p>Because the fediverse includes a wide range of technologies, I focus on
<a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">Mastodon</a>, a microblogging software package that can be installed and run
on modern web servers.</p>

<p>Mastodon provides a window not only into software engineering, but also
social and political interventions – particularly from marginalized
critical reverse engineers – in alternative social media.</p>

<h3 id="from-ostatus-to-activitypub">From OStatus to ActivityPub</h3>

<p>When many people speak about Mastodon, they often place it relation to
Twitter. This predates the Musk takeover of Twitter, but it has
certainly been amplified since then.</p>

<p>Mastodon appears to be an example of critical reverse engineering of
Twitter, and was hailed from its earliest days as such. <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/mastodon-is-like-twitter-without-nazis-so-why-are-we-not-using-it/">“Twitter without
the Nazis”</a> was a common descriptor.</p>

<p>But as I show in my book, Mastodon’s founder, Eugen Rochko, actually meant to critically reverse engineer another alternative, GNU social, in 2016. Mastodon was meant to be an alternative to an alternative. And this brought it into conflict with ideologies of freedom and openness – the ideologies of repressive tolerance.</p>

<p>Mastodon servers were initially able to communicate with GNU social over
a protocol called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OStatus">OStatus</a>. OStatus was a very Web 2.0 technology – it was about openness, the idea
that all of us should participate openly in discussion.</p>

<p>One goal among Mastodon’s developers was to provide safety tools to protect
marginalized folks, particularly queer and trans folks, allowing for users to
address their posts to particular, limited audiences and have more
control over who could reply.</p>

<p>These were features not available in GNU social (or, for that matter,
Twitter).</p>

<p>However, this grated against the everything-must-be-open-and-free ethos
of GNU social.</p>

<p>I won’t go into too much detail here, but one major issue was privacy
violations on the part of GNU social users, who would publicly expose
private posts from queer and trans Mastodon users in the name of
“openness” and “freedom.”</p>

<p>Fortunately, the <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub protocol</a> was being developed in 2016-2017,
and it had more robust privacy capacities. Four of the five authors self-identify
as queer, which might explain the new protocol’s affordances, including the
use of post addressing as a means to protect people.</p>

<p>Mastodon adopted ActivityPub, denying the repressive forms of openness
of OStatus in favor of safety for marginalized people.</p>

<h3 id="codes-of-conduct">Codes of Conduct</h3>

<p>Another anti-repressive tolerance move: the inclusion of codes of
conduct, as advocated for by activists such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coraline_Ada_Ehmke">Coraline Ada Ehmke</a>. Codes
of conduct are important in Mastodon’s history.</p>

<p>Ehmke’s work reflects feminist/trans activism in tech – the struggle
against meritocracy. This struggle emerged from projects like the <a href="https://geekfeminism.fandom.com/wiki/Geek_Feminism_Wiki">Geek Feminism wiki</a>, which
documented misogyny and transphobia at tech conventions.</p>

<p>These practices were cited as the reason why technology – particularly
FOSS technology – has had <a href="https://www.wired.com/2017/06/diversity-open-source-even-worse-tech-overall/">a significant lack of contributions from
women and racialized minorities</a>.</p>

<p>Ehmke and her allies laid the feet of such behavior at the ideology of meritocracy in
tech, where, as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Cathedral_and_the_Bazaar">Eric Raymond argued</a>, the only thing that matters is
great code. Implicitly, being a sexual abuser or racist is ok so long as
you can code.</p>

<p>Other scholars and activists have pointed to <a href="https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/4291">“pushyocracy,”</a> where it’s
not about great code but about who can shout the loudest, as a reason
why marginalized people avoided getting involved in the tech indstury.
(Linus Torvalds has been a key example of this, though he has since
sought forgiveness.)</p>

<p>Instead of meritocracy at tech conventions, Ehmke and her allies have
argued for Codes of Conduct, which have been largely adopted by both
tech conventions and free and open source projects.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/mastodonCovenant.png" alt="The website for the Mastodon server covenant, which includes the requirement for 'active moderation against racism, sexism, homophobia and transphobia.'" />
    <figcaption>
        While the Mastodon server covenant seems rather simple, the idea that a federated network of servers may all agree to things like "active moderation" is a cultural achievement. This is quite different from previous alternative social media.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I show in the book, these Codes have <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/covenant">also been adopted by many
Mastodon servers</a>. I argue these act as fundamental diplomatic documents
in noncentralized social media: codes of conduct help structure
relations on the network. The active association among instances who
share ethical values indicates an ethical consensus is emerging across
the network including values of anti-racism and anti-transphobia.</p>

<h3 id="fediblock-and-blocklists">#Fediblock and Blocklists</h3>

<p>While much of the code of conduct discussion is about shared ethical
values, what about times when fediverse instances violate these
agreements? Another anti-repressive tolerance move can be found among those who
advocate severing connections.</p>

<p>Here I turn to another critical reverse engineer, Ro, founder of an
early Mastodon instance called “Playvicious.social.”</p>

<p>Playvicious was likely the first Black-run instance on Mastodon. But Ro shut it down in 2020, citing racist harassment of the moderators.
You can <a href="https://roiskinda.cool/2023/12/recuerda-pv-chapter-7-the-dark-and-ugly.html">read about it on his blog</a> – but I warn you, it’s heavy.</p>

<p>The Playvicious episode – and many others – reflected what Jonathan Flowers would later call <a href="https://www.techpolicy.press/the-whiteness-of-mastodon/">“the whiteness of
Mastodon,”</a> the deeply embedded practices of whiteness that not only
include overt racism, but the subtle forms philosopher Myisha Cherry
calls “white skepticism” and “white empathy.”</p>

<p>But, to quote Flowers, Black critical reverse engineers continue to
contribute in spite of whiteness. In Ro’s case, he returned to the
network with a new project, a shared blocklist called <a href="https://thebad.space/">The Bad Space</a>.</p>

<p>Blocklists are now <a href="https://about.iftas.org/activities/moderation-as-a-service/fedicheck/">an emergent governance and moderation tool on the
fediverse</a>, enabling independent instances to import lists of known bad
actors and prevent them from interacting with instance members. Ro’s Bad Space isn’t the only project, though it is one that seems to attract the most criticism – recapitulating the Playvicious episode in a new form.</p>

<p>There’s another critical reverse engineer to cite here. Ro took inspiration for his blocklist from former Playvicious moderator
<a href="https://www.artistmarciax.com/">Marcia X</a>. Like many Black feminists, Marcia has contributed to the network,
co-creating a hashtag, #fediblock, for public discussions over how to
block racist instances and accounts on the network.</p>

<p>I’ve put their work into practice. The work of Black critical reverse
engineers has aided me directly – I now help run <a href="https://aoir.social">AoIR.social</a>, the Mastodon
instance for the Association of Internet Researchers, and we rely on
blocklists and #fediblock to prevent racists and transphobes from
interacting with our members.</p>

<h3 id="towards-the-covenantal-fediverse">Towards the Covenantal Fediverse</h3>

<p>Taken as a whole, these new critical reverse engineers have helped bring
about a new form of alternative social media.</p>

<p>It is a form a <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400">colleague and I have called</a> “the covenantal fediverse,” a
non-centralized, large network of small communities that associate
through shared ethical values.</p>

<p>Here is a new normative critical reverse engineering of corporate social
media. Returning to the four orientations of critical reverse engineering, let’s turn back to the normative orientation.</p>

<p>The normative aspect of Mastodon and the covenantal fediverse relates to previous alternative social media. In some ways, the fediverse continues older normative practices. It inherits the anti-surveillance capitalism aspects of previous alternatives, of course. Most of the fediverse operates on a non-capitalist, mutual aid economy. Much of it avoids behavioral advertising.</p>

<p>However, the older cyberlibertarianism is replaced – often in a messy and uneven way – with freedom of association. By accident or design, the Instance is a powerful unit. I would suggest that our understanding of the fediverse <a href="/2024/03/14/Instances-and-Individuals.html">needs to account more heavily for instances-as-communities</a> instead of the individual user (as has been privileged in cyberlibertarian thinking).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-will-this-survive">Conclusion: Will this survive?</h2>
<p>Now I have traced a new form of critical reverse engineering, one
operating on both corporate social media and previous alternative social
media. I believe it is best existing path away from corporate social
media.</p>

<p>And yet, while millions of people took up Mastodon after Musk’s purchase
of Twitter, billions remain on corporate social media.</p>

<p>To return to where I started, even critical media organizations that
speak of non-corporate media continue to use corporate social media!</p>

<p>We might ask “can this platform survive?” as <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4598303">several colleagues from
American University and I do</a> in a forthcoming paper in the <em>International
Journal of Communication</em>.</p>

<p>And my answer is: I don’t know. Many alternative projects have failed.</p>

<p>But let’s again listen to the object. Alternative social media speaks of hope, even
in the face of failure (however we define that idea!). To use a term
from speculative fiction, alternative social media speaks of <em>porvir
otimista.</em></p>

<p>Don’t despair in the face of the sociotechnical systems you confront.
Instead, critically reverse engineer them.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="critical reverse engineering" /><category term="presentations" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently gave a presentation to the Cultural Studies PhD program at George Mason University. That’s the program where I earned my PhD, so it was an honor to come back and talk to my professors as well as some of the new students currently in the program. I took the presentation as an opportunity to reflect on my academic career from my time at Mason (2005-2010) to my latest book project. I’ve modified it for this blog. Take a look at the abstract and, if piques your interest, feel free to read it! (It’s a bit long.) Abstract In my time as a PhD student in GMU’s Cultural Studies program, I learned that I must let my object of study tell me what methods to use to analyze it. I also learned not to merely interpret the object, but seek to change it. Since I chose to study what was then called “Web 2.0” and what I now call “corporate social media,” I needed to bring Marxian political economy, science and technology studies, and software studies to bear on the object. And I began to examine the practices of activists who sought to make something better than corporate social media: alternative social media. Over a decade ago I began my adventures in alternative social media, chasing it through hacker collectives, cyberlibertarian organizations, and even onto the dark web. Through digital ethnography, close examinations of code, and hands-on experience running alternative social media, I developed an approach I call “critical reverse engineering.” Here I present critical reverse engineering as a methodology for activist engagement with digital technologies. To illustrate this approach, I will draw on insights from my forthcoming book, Move Slowly and Build Bridges: Mastodon, the Fediverse, and the Struggle for Ethical Social Media (Oxford, 2025).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goodbye, Firefox?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/18/goodbyeFirefox.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goodbye, Firefox?" /><published>2024-09-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/18/goodbyeFirefox</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/18/goodbyeFirefox.html"><![CDATA[<p>I think I’m going to stop using Firefox altogether. It was a tiny little weather app that did it.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/firefoxNotDefault.png" alt="Firefox is no longer my default browser, and it has a sad face. I'm sad about it, too." />
  <figcaption>Firefox is no longer my default browser, and it has a sad face. I'm sad about it, too.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>So, one day I opened a new tab in Firefox and there it was: a weather report. A tiny little temp reading for my area. I didn’t think about it much, but someone on the fediverse noted that this little weather app is sponsored by AccuWeather, a company <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-adventure/environment/project-2025-paywall-weather/">long criticized for its attempt to privatize public weather information</a>. Hovering over the little temp reading revealed this to be true – it said, “Sponsored by AccuWeather.”</p>

<p>And that broke me.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>To be fair, it’s not the only thing. <a href="https://connect.mozilla.org/t5/discussions/firefox-changing-my-settings-on-update/m-p/14155">Like others</a>, I’ve started to see privacy settings being reset every time I update Firefox. I set the default search to be Startpage instead of Google – an update wiped that and set it to Google, again. I set my homepage to not have Pocket or sponsored links – an update wiped that.</p>

<p>Pretty soon each new tab suggested I go to Facebook. <em>Fucking Facebook</em>.</p>

<p>Mozilla bashing has become kind of a common sport, so much so that one of my favorite podcasts, <em>Late Night Linux</em>, has gotten bored of doing it. But once I saw the little AccuWeather thingy, I started watching for critical comments on Mozilla. And I saw what many others have already pointed out:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.zdnet.com/home-and-office/networking/the-fall-of-firefox-mozillas-once-popular-web-browser-slides-into-irrelevance/">Firefox browser share plummeting in inverse proportion to CEO pay</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/en/mozilla/mozilla-anonym-raising-the-bar-for-privacy-preserving-digital-advertising/">weird ideas about integrating ad-tech</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.mozilla.ai/_">AI bullshit</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/mozilla-social-faq">and an end to the laudable experiment with the fediverse</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>My attitude towards these critical takes has long been to ignore them. “Whatever Mozilla wants to do is fine as long as they make a good browser,” I said to myself. But lately it seems like they’re actively trying to kill off Firefox rather than continuing to make a great browser.</p>

<p>The thing is, with all the papercuts, Firefox is still quite good. But this is FOSS. Forks are a thing. I’m now testing out <a href="https://librewolf.net/">LibreWolf</a>, a privacy-conscious fork of Firefox, and so far, so good.</p>

<p>What’s sad about this, though, is that I’ve been using Firefox for nearly two decades – almost as long as Firefox has been around. It was my <a href="/2020/12/15/FOSS-Journey.html">introduction point into the world of FOSS</a>. First it, then OpenOffice, then Ubuntu, and now I run as much FOSS as I can.</p>

<p>Maybe I will come back to Firefox, but if not, I’m still grateful for its role in my career.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="FALD" /><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="Firefox" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I think I’m going to stop using Firefox altogether. It was a tiny little weather app that did it. Firefox is no longer my default browser, and it has a sad face. I'm sad about it, too. So, one day I opened a new tab in Firefox and there it was: a weather report. A tiny little temp reading for my area. I didn’t think about it much, but someone on the fediverse noted that this little weather app is sponsored by AccuWeather, a company long criticized for its attempt to privatize public weather information. Hovering over the little temp reading revealed this to be true – it said, “Sponsored by AccuWeather.” And that broke me.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Update: Mastodon Research Ethics and the Ethical Quandaries of Tech Advocacy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/06/ASMupdate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update: Mastodon Research Ethics and the Ethical Quandaries of Tech Advocacy" /><published>2024-09-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/06/ASMupdate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/06/ASMupdate.html"><![CDATA[<p>In this ASM update, I’ll write at length about <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11616-024-00855-6">a new research study on Mastodon</a> that gets the ethics of research right – even though they pulled data from my home Mastodon instance. I’ll also discuss <a href="https://latenightlinux.com/late-night-linux-episode-297/">a recent podcast episode</a> that talks about the ethics of using and promoting FOSS.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="aoirsocial-data-were-included-in-an-academic-study--and-thats-ok">AoIR.social data were included in an academic study – and that’s OK</h2>
<p>I’m one of the admins of <a href="https://aoir.social">AoIR.social</a>, a Mastodon instance for members of the Association of Internet Researchers. In the AoIR.social Code of Conduct, we include the following bit about research:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Researchers who wish to study AoIR.social or our users by collecting data using the API or through any other means that does not involve an “opt-in” from individual users are required to submit their protocol, analysis plan and all relevant ethics approval documentation from their institutional review board or departmental internal review documentation by email to the AoIR Fediverse admin account. You may also be required to submit code you plan to execute so that it can be tested to ensure it does not degrade the quality of service to other users.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I just found a study that most likely included data culled from AoIR.social via the Mastodon API, and… I’m not mad! I don’t think they violated our Code. In fact, I think the authors did the fediverse a huge service.</p>

<p>The study in question is <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11616-024-00855-6">“‘Don’t research us’ – How Mastodon instance rules connect to research ethics,”</a> by Marco Wähner et al. It appeared in <em>Publizistik</em> a few weeks ago.</p>

<p>The authors are asking whether and how Mastodon instances signal their preferences for the collection and use of data for research purposes, as well as what ethical issues arise when researchers gather data from Mastodon’s API.</p>

<p>Through the use of the Mastodon API, they pulled in codes of conduct from over 4000 active English-language Mastodon instances. They then quantitatively and qualitatively examine those codes. While they found that many COCs emphasize rules of behavior on the instance (e.g., no racism, no transphobia), only 31 English-language instances actually address research ethics and discuss data usage.</p>

<p>Undoubtedly, AoIR.social is in their dataset, since we address the topic explicitly. So, why am I not upset with Wähner et al’s own paper, then?</p>

<p>It’s because this research team did not study <em>individuals</em>, but rather focused on <em>instances</em>. This is exactly <a href="https://www.cell.com/patterns/fulltext/S2666-3899(23)00323-9">the point I’ve made elsewhere</a> with fellow fediverse researcher Roel Roscam Abbing. I also <a href="/2024/03/14/Instances-and-Individuals.html">posted a bit more</a> about the individual/instance distinction on this blog. We need these studies and data – maps of the fediverse, population data, and trends in codes of conduct language are valuable insights.</p>

<p>And not only will the fediverse benefit from Wähner et al’s work, I agree with their claim that pulling instance codes of conduct does no harm to fediverse members. I do not see it as a violation when people do instance-level studies of the fediverse without getting the consent of fediverse admins.</p>

<p>In light of the fact that only a small number of instances post explicit rules about research data use, the authors offer some recommendations to researchers. I’ll get to them, but first, let’s talk about implications for instance admins like me.</p>

<p>One implication of their study is that Mastodon and fediverse instances ought to include rules about research in their codes of conduct. This may be a wise thing for instance admins and community members to consider. However, I think we should not merely make this recommendation. It puts too much burden on instance admins and communities. If fediverse instances must write rules for every unethical case they might possibly encounter, their codes of conduct will shift from human-readable, community documents to legalese-drenched Terms of Service agreements found more often in corporate social media.</p>

<p>No, the answer here is that researchers, not instances, need more ethical training and thinking. One approach might be to consider codes of conduct in the aggregate and proceed from the assumption that a prohibition on a handful of instances indicates a much broader – if unstated – prohibition across the fediverse itself. Researchers might protest at this, arguing this would stifle their work, but I would argue that ethical approaches to fediverse research should meet an extremely high bar.</p>

<p>In fact, Wähner et al make this same point:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The characteristics of the user community may lead to the expectation that users may hold a (more) critical stance towards user data collection on Mastodon. Of course, as stated before, the total number of 31 instance rules explicitly addressing data use for research purposes is quite low. Providing a detailed explanation for why there are not more instance rules reflecting on research data collection is beyond the scope of this paper. However, based on research on the general lack of awareness for the fact that researchers are using data collected from social media platforms (Breuer et al. 2023; Quinton and Reynolds 2017), we assume that this is also true for a substantial share (if not the majority) of Mastodon users (Wähner et al., 2024, p. 16).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For those who wish to examine individual-level data, Wähner et al go on to offer several suggestions for researchers of the fediverse, including paying attention to instance rules. They note that if an instance explicitly prohibits the use of member data, researchers ought to expunge it – even in cases where the data will be anonymized. They also recommend reaching out to – and collaborating with! – instance admins in research design. Admins can be useful guides in getting informed consent among fediverse members.</p>

<p>I agree, and thus I recommend this study to future fediverse researchers. I’ll definitely put this study in <a href="/bib.html">the Bibliography</a>.</p>

<h2 id="late-night-linux-tackles-the-ethics-of-advocating-foss">Late Night Linux tackles the ethics of advocating FOSS</h2>
<p>Speaking of ethics, the crew at the Late Night Linux podcast just raised a bunch of ethical issues in FOSS, ones that I tackle in my <a href="/2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">forthcoming book about Mastodon and the fediverse</a>. In <a href="https://latenightlinux.com/late-night-linux-episode-297/">their latest episode</a>, the hosts talk about what to do when we deal with unethical Internet corporations. Cloudflare is one they highlight. X is another. Is it unethical to use their products? Or to give your custom to companies that do?</p>

<p>Both of these examples are quite germane to my book. In it, I definitely talk about how the actions of X have prompted a shift from that platform to the fediverse (among other alternatives). I also talk about a somewhat shameful secret of the noncentralized fediverse: that it often relies on <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3355369.3355572">centralized cloud hosting services (such as Amazon) and technologies (such as Cloudflare) to function</a>.</p>

<p>So, should we despair if we cannot escape unethical corporations? The LNL crew largely said, no. You try your best, and you do better over time.</p>

<p>But the real answer came in their next segment, which was about advocating that Windows Subsystem for Linux users make the switch to mainline Linux. The LNL crew <a href="https://mastodon.cloud/@LateNightLinux/113005956969609375">posted this question to Mastodon</a>, and the dominant answer was: no. Let people solve problems in the way that works. The best you can do is show them the benefits of the better stuff you use.</p>

<p>I think the same is true of the fediverse. We could berate people for using corporate social media. I’ve found over many years, however, that that doesn’t work. Instead, show people what you use and talk about why it’s better. If they switch, great! If not, that’s ok. The fediverse isn’t about infinite or rapid growth. It’s about growing slowly and purposely.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="research ethics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this ASM update, I’ll write at length about a new research study on Mastodon that gets the ethics of research right – even though they pulled data from my home Mastodon instance. I’ll also discuss a recent podcast episode that talks about the ethics of using and promoting FOSS.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zotero 7 Early Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/13/Zotero-7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zotero 7 Early Review" /><published>2024-08-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/08/13/Zotero%207</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/13/Zotero-7.html"><![CDATA[<p>I took a family vacation, so I was away from my work laptop when I learned <a href="https://www.zotero.org/blog/zotero-7/">Zotero has launched version 7, a major upgrade</a>. While I enjoyed my vacation, I was naturally eager to get home to try it out!</p>

<p>In my initial review, I found an improved interface design with small changes that improve (instead of interrupt) my workflow, as well as some nice improvements to the PDF Reader (which is now really an Attachment Reader).</p>

<p>I may do a more substantial review as I use Zotero 7 to get stuff done, but my first glance leaves me quite happy with this new version.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="easy-to-upgrade-and-easy-on-the-eyes">Easy to upgrade, and easy on the eyes</h2>
<p>Upgrading was easy in Linux – I just used Zotero’s “check for updates” option and upgraded from Zotero 6 to 7. The only thing that “broke” was the application icon, but I just edited my menu to point to the new icon.</p>

<p>On first run, it gave me an option between “Comfortable” and “Compact” layouts. I could toggle between the two to quickly see the differences. I choose Compact, which tightens up the gaps between entries and text. The overall look is clean while still very familiar. (I don’t know about you, but I really can’t stand major interface upgrades, which is a big reason I use Linux – I prefer to keep things stable for years).</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/resm_zoteroPreview.png" alt="A preview of my first book in the Zotero Item Preview pane" />
  <figcaption>My first book as shown in Zotero's new Item Preview pane</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The new Item Preview is particularly attractive. One upshot is that it shows “Related” items in a more visible manner than in past Zotero iterations. I think this could be quite useful. In my experience, relating items really didn’t provide much insight for me. I did it, anyway, on the theory that maybe in the future the data would be useful. Perhaps the time is now?</p>

<p>And a change that is very welcome is dark mode! I had installed a third-party dark mode theme in Zotero 6, so this didn’t jump out at me. That is, until I saw <strong>dark mode in PDFs</strong>! Amazing! I tried to hack this on my own (and largely failed), but it’s working natively now.</p>

<h2 id="cool-new-features">Cool new features</h2>
<p>Speaking of PDF annotation, it now includes underlining text in various colors in addition to highlighting. And, either can be converted to the other with just a click. This is a feature I didn’t even know I wanted, but now I think I like it! I can see myself doing underlining instead of highlighting from here on out.</p>

<p>And the PDF reader does a bunch more than load PDFs! It also can handle EPUBs, and – importantly for me – it shows Web snapshots! It’s more of an Attachment Reader now. And those snapshots can be marked up in a similar fashion as PDFs. However, I did see some bugs – in my first test of the snapshot annotation feature, it didn’t show underlines, and it barely showed highlights. I can imagine it’s a tricky matter to code an annotation for heterogeneous HTML and CSS.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/snapshot_Highlighting.png" alt="An example of editing a web snapshot in Zotero" />
  <figcaption>Editing my snapshot of the Post-Meritocratic Manifesto in Zotero. One problem here is highlights and underlines don't show up well.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In spite of this problem, it’s going to be a useful feature.</p>

<p>Other interface improvements include tab selection with a drop-down. This is a really cool idea, letting me select tabs in a drop-down menu. This might be good for those who use a lot of tabs. I can also search across tabs. So far, it appears to be limited to item titles.</p>

<p>As far as performance goes, Zotero opens at least as fast as before, and it uses 2GB of RAM. It’s clear version 7 is not a downgrade in terms of speed. In fact, PDFs seem to load slightly faster into the reader. I don’t really do benchmarking, but in my experience, their claim that there are performance improvements holds up.</p>

<p>Turning to in-text citation system, I noticed no major changes here, but one subtle one: a way to export the document from one word processor (e.g., LibreOffice) to another (e.g., Word). I don’t know if this will solve the problem of cross-word processor collaboration or not yet.</p>

<h2 id="features-i-dont-know-if-i-like--yet">Features I don’t know if I like – yet</h2>

<p>Zotero has redesigned the item pane to include icons, rather than text, as the main navigational tool. This saves space, but it makes things a bit less accessible.</p>

<p>They also changed the icons in the center column after many years of using the same icons. I might get used to picking out the differences between various item types at a glance, but I’m not sure I will get used to it. Fortunately, I can add “Item Type” as a column if need be.</p>

<h2 id="features-i-still-want-to-see">Features I still want to see</h2>

<p>There are still features I want to see – stuff I’ve been wanting for years.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/smartFolders.png" alt="A list of smart folders in Zotero" />
  <figcaption>Here's a portion of my smart folders, specifically tied to my Mastodon/fediverse book project. Note my pre-pending each with a "1" -- that's my way to keep them organized.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>First, I believe it would be great to have the ability to nest smart searches within traditional folders. Right now, the two folder types are traditional, where you create a folder and drag stuff into it, or smart, which dynamically updates based on search criteria. I use the latter almost exclusively, but this results is a long list of smart searches. As you can see from a screenshot, I use a simple fix – I prepend a number to the smart search folder titles to keep similar searches grouped together. I would much prefer to be able to make save these searches together in a top-level folder.</p>

<p>I also remain underwhelmed by the tag management system. It remains a small corner section in the layout. I recall Endnote’s system, which was a separate window with all tags listed alphabetically, making it much easier to scroll through them, delete unwanted tags, and merge tags.</p>

<h2 id="overall-7-looks-good">Overall, 7 looks good</h2>

<p>Overall, however, 7 looks like a great new edition of the most important software I use to do my FOSS Academic work. 7 appears to be a great addition to the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Zotero" /><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="FALD" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I took a family vacation, so I was away from my work laptop when I learned Zotero has launched version 7, a major upgrade. While I enjoyed my vacation, I was naturally eager to get home to try it out! In my initial review, I found an improved interface design with small changes that improve (instead of interrupt) my workflow, as well as some nice improvements to the PDF Reader (which is now really an Attachment Reader). I may do a more substantial review as I use Zotero 7 to get stuff done, but my first glance leaves me quite happy with this new version.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hitting a Nerve and Presenting at IETF</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/25/ASM-update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hitting a Nerve and Presenting at IETF" /><published>2024-07-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/07/25/ASM%20update</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/25/ASM-update.html"><![CDATA[<p>Nothing major this month, but I do want to note two things. First, I wrote a post on the fediverse that must have hit a nerve. It’s about corporations selling off academic work to AI companies. Second, I presented research to a panel at the IETF, talking about the development of ActivityPub by the W3C’s Social Web Working Group. The presentation is based on my <a href="/2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">forthcoming book</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="hitting-a-nerve">Hitting a Nerve</h2>
<p>A colleague of mine shared <a href="https://www.thebookseller.com/news/academic-authors-shocked-after-taylor--francis-sells-access-to-their-research-to-microsoft-ai">an article from <em>The Bookseller</em></a> that reports that Taylor and Francis – which is a major publisher of academic articles and books – is selling access to its catalog to Microsoft to train AI. [Note that <em>The Bookseller</em> provides free access to one article per month.]</p>

<p>I got a bit upset and <a href="https://aoir.social/deck/@rwg/112819578544558425">posted this</a> to the fediverse:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After 15+ years of hustling to publish #academic journal articles and books, a significant proportion of my work is now being sold off to #Microsoft to train #LLMs. I never consented to this, and of course when I started my career, I never predicted this.
That whoosh you’re hearing is me rushing to sign on to whatever class action lawsuit is in the offing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This hit a bit of a nerve on the fediverse, with quite a few folks boosting the post. That tells me I’m not alone in being angry about this.</p>

<p>It turns out that the Microsoft deal isn’t the only one. Taylor and Francis has <a href="https://www.thebookseller.com/news/taylor-francis-set-to-make-58m-from-ai-in-2024-as-it-reveals-second-partnership">announced another</a>. According to <em>The Bookseller</em>, “the business said it plans to reinvest a third of its AI-related profit into ‘accelerated technology, open research and AI product development… based on our unique content.’”</p>

<p>There’s that word. Content. For years I’ve resisted the appelation “content creator.” I find it to be insulting, frankly. I don’t spend my days filling containers. People who operate machines that deposit food into cans are content creators. (No insult meant to people who work in factories!)</p>

<p>But now my “unique content” is going to feed shitty AI bots that no doubt will help write bad journal articles or provide “expertise” via some chat or search applications.</p>

<p>This isn’t what I signed up for. This isn’t what being an open academic who publishes work for others to build on meant to me when I started.</p>

<p>I don’t know if there is any legal recourse. I’ll leave that to lawyers – and if there is a class action suit, sign me up!</p>

<p>But I do know that we academics really ought to withhold our work from massively profitable corporations who view us as content creators. That means no reviewing for T&amp;F, no submissions to T&amp;F journals, and no publishing books with Routledge.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, that means we’ll have to likely boycott SAGE and Elsevier, as well.</p>

<h2 id="ietf-presentation">IETF Presentation</h2>

<p>In happier news, I presented research to the IETF. I’ve never been to an IETF meeting and I think by and large it went well.</p>

<p>I presented a version of what will be the second chapter of my book, which focuses on the intertwined histories of ActivityPub and Mastodon. The presentation was part of a panel of folks studying standardization processes. I was especially impressed by the work of Diane Liao and Michelle Parkouda (as presented by Liao) on ways in which standards bodies could consider differential impacts of standards based on gender.</p>

<p>The panel was recorded – <a href="https://play.conf.meetecho.com/Playout/?session=IETF120-RASPRG-20240724-2000">you can see it here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="ActivityPub" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Nothing major this month, but I do want to note two things. First, I wrote a post on the fediverse that must have hit a nerve. It’s about corporations selling off academic work to AI companies. Second, I presented research to a panel at the IETF, talking about the development of ActivityPub by the W3C’s Social Web Working Group. The presentation is based on my forthcoming book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Threads’s Blocklist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/28/ThreadsBlocking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Threads’s Blocklist" /><published>2024-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/28/ThreadsBlocking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/28/ThreadsBlocking.html"><![CDATA[<p>Meta’s Threads, which is slowly enabling ActivityPub capabilities, has just posted a <a href="https://www.threads.net/moderated_servers">list of servers it is blocking</a>. The list (as of this writng) has over 660 entries. Since I am finalizing a chapter on Threads for my <a href="/2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">forthcoming book</a>, I will definitely have to consider this list in detail. For now, I wanted to offer a few comments on this development, since it’s a decidedly important moment in the ActivityPub-based fediverse.</p>

<!-- more -->
<h2 id="meta-is-being-transparent-sorta">Meta is being transparent… sorta</h2>
<p>I want to offer the most charitable take I can first: this public blocklist is one of the biggest moments of tranparency that Meta has ever engaged in. Maybe some of my academic colleagues who closely monitor Meta could correct me, but this strikes me as Meta offering quite a bit more insight into content moderation practices than they have in the past.</p>

<p>I think credit is due to the fediverse as a whole on this one, though. If Meta truly wishes to integrate with the fediverse, they have to follow the protocols, and I don’t just mean ActivityPub – they have to follow the <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400">social protocols of transparent, open moderation</a>. While typically this is in the form of simple, clear codes of conduct and open communication from moderators, posting a blocklist publicly a good step in the direction of transparency.</p>

<h2 id="this-may-be-the-first-time-millions-see-blocking-in-action">This may be the first time millions see blocking in action</h2>
<p>When I first started out on the ActivityPub-based fediverse back in early 2017, most Mastodon instances published their blocklists. Admins can still do this – indeed, Mastodon.social, the largest server, <a href="https://mastodon.social/about">does (scroll down and click on “moderated servers”)</a>.</p>

<p>However, over the past few years, many smaller servers stopped sharing this information publicly. Why? Well, it’s obviously a vector for harassment. For example, if as an admin I publicly say I block bad.instance, their friends could harass me with constant requests about why I did so, arguing that I need to change my mind. I have other stuff to do. Many admins just keep their blocklists to themselves.</p>

<p>So Threads is revealing something many of the millions of new fediverse members have not often seen: the fact that a healthy server <em>must</em> block many others in order to moderate effectively. It’s a fact of fediverse life.</p>

<p>This is a pretty radical change for Meta, to be honest: they now have to declare their relationship to the rest of the web, rather than just pretend that the web must flow through Meta properties.</p>

<h2 id="blocking-nazis-and-nudity">Blocking Nazis and nudity</h2>
<p>Of course, transparency allows for scrutiny. We can take a look at the 660+ blocks and see what sort of values Meta adheres to.</p>

<p>First of all, there are a lot of instances on their list that I completely agree need to be blocked, including overtly white supremacist instances. I won’t specify these, but if you look at the list, you’ll see what I mean just from the URLs. There are also instances geared towards sharing sexualized cartoon images of children (a practice tolerated in Japan, but not by the rest of the fediverse). You can likely guess from those URLs, too.</p>

<p>However, multiple fediverse members have pointed out that Threads is blocking many queer and trans instances. While we’d have to dig in to figure out why, the most likely answer is that Meta has policies against nudity. Indeed, Meta’s own Oversight Board found that <a href="https://gizmodo.com/instagram-meta-age-verification-system-ai-1849753822">Meta is too aggressive in blocking nudity among LBTQ* users</a>, including posts discussing top surgery.</p>

<p>In my interview with Mastodon founder Eugen Rochko, he saw such bans on consenting adult nudity as a very US-centric approach to global content moderation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[On the fediverse], there are thousands of other providers across the entire world, each giving a little bit of social space to the world, that is not controlled entirely from the US. And we know that US politics is not very stable – there’s a lot of turbulence. Trump was in charge, and that was not great for progressive laws.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some laws were passed, about 5 years ago, that affected a lot of sex workers – the SESTA and FOSTA bills – that basically erased sex work from social media because [so much] social media is based in the US. I think that’s not fair, because in Germany sex work is legal. Sex work <em>is</em> work.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Threads blocklist appears to be an extension of this logic: yet another attempt to moderate the globe from California.</p>

<p>Of course, if we think of Threads as another node on the fediverse, well… they can block whomever they wish for whatever reason. But the fact is, Meta is so large that if the rest of the fediverse tries to connect to it, we will defacto have US-based regulations on a highly localized, global network.</p>

<p>Indeed, Rochko’s own Mastodon.social should probably be blocked by Threads, since it allows for pornography. In fact, several folks on the fediverse saw that Mastodon.social was blocked for 30 minutes, though it didn’t seem to affect the connection.</p>

<p>Was that a mistake? Or a warning shot?</p>

<h2 id="you-blocked-what-now">You blocked what now?</h2>
<p>Threads blocking white supremacists and loli comics strikes me as a fine choice. I don’t agree at all with their blocking LGBTQ instances, but if they insist on blocking nudity, I suppose it makes some sense – if only in a bland, shopping mall sort of way.</p>

<p>But some of their blocking choices make no sense to me.</p>

<p>For example, Threads blocks Scholar.social. An instance dedicated to acadmics, Scholar.social is one of the oldest Mastodon instances, and it has been a model of content moderation, safety for marginalized folks, and thoughtful federation practices. I know it very well because it was my home instance for several years. And when I shifted to being an admin of AoIR.social, we asked for permission to copy Scholar’s code of conduct.</p>

<p>The only reason Threads offers for the block is Scholar “Violated our Community Guidelines or Terms of Use.” I have no idea what this could mean. But the good news is, I know for a fact that Scholar would never federate with anything Meta, anyway, so I imagine their being blocked by Meta is a badge of honor!</p>

<p>Other confusing blocking choices that jump out to me are Kolektiva.social and Tabletop.social, two instances I also find to be well-moderated. Again, the justification is violated community guidelines. And, again, I don’t think these servers care, since they are signatories to the <a href="https://fedipact.online/">Anti-Threads Fedipact</a>.</p>

<p>For the rest of us – those of us who haven’t been blocked by Meta – take these arbitrary choices as a warning: if you attempt to federate with Threads, perhaps have a plan for when Threads blocks you and your members.</p>

<h2 id="cross-referencing-ahoy">Cross referencing ahoy!</h2>
<p>Confusing decisions aside, it would be fascinating to cross-reference Threads’s blocklist with shared blocklists, like the Bad Space, Oliphaunt’s list, Sierdy’s, and Garden Fence. I myself drew on these lists when we started AoIR.social. As I mentioned above, this is at least a bit of transparency from a Meta property – we can learn a great deal about what they’re thinking. But we can also learn what the broader fediverse values by comparing Meta’s blocklist to those of other servers as well as shared lists.</p>

<p>As is clear from looking at the list, Meta continues to have a particular vision for global moderation. If you’re looking to emulate Meta-style blocking, you can copy their list. If you reject Meta values, take a long hard look at their list and ask yourself if you should block the same servers.</p>

<p>If this were just any fediverse server, I don’t think this blocklist would draw too much attention. But if it is an indication that this incredibly large, powerful social media corporation intends to reshape the fediverse in its image, and if they insist on blocking several well-moderated servers, it is a disturbing list – not because of the choices they made that are right, but because of the arbitrary choices they make that simply get it wrong.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Threads" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meta’s Threads, which is slowly enabling ActivityPub capabilities, has just posted a list of servers it is blocking. The list (as of this writng) has over 660 entries. Since I am finalizing a chapter on Threads for my forthcoming book, I will definitely have to consider this list in detail. For now, I wanted to offer a few comments on this development, since it’s a decidedly important moment in the ActivityPub-based fediverse.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Maven Ain’t So Mavenly</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/12/Maven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Maven Ain’t So Mavenly" /><published>2024-06-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/12/Maven</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/12/Maven.html"><![CDATA[<p>The ever-alert Liaizon Wakest has informed the rest of us on the ActivityPub-based fediverse of a new social media site, <a href="https://www.heymaven.com">Maven</a>, which has <a href="https://app.heymaven.com/discover/1190743">ingested millions of posts from fediverse accounts</a>, including mine.</p>

<p>Multiple people have pointed out how this violates consent on the fediverse. In response, the CTO of Maven, Jimmy Secretran, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@jsecretan/112604200409755575">has explained their reasoning</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We are trying to connect up to the Fediverse, to allow interaction with other ActivityPub servers.  This definitely seems to me to be within the spirit of what ActivityPub enables, but of course, I don’t want to have Maven connect to anybody who doesn’t want it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>[Note that I normally do not quote fediverse posts without permission, but in this case, I am making an exception, for reasons that I think will be obvious.]</p>

<p>I replied in the thread, arguing that, no, they are not really abiding by the spirit of ActivityPub:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This isn’t how this works. No one starts a fediverse (AP) server by ingesting a bunch of posts from others without their consent. They start servers and start federating with the rest of the network.
Please stop ingesting posts from AoIR.social (I’m the admin, btw).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>and</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The custom is to start a server with a code of conduct, including clear moderation rules, so that the rest of us can make informed choices about federating. What you’ve done with Maven is a pretty massive violation of norms, and likely it will result in your being defederated from many other instances. It’s a poor way to start an ActivityPub implementation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To be fair to Secretran and Maven, they have since stopped scraping my posts and, I presume, those of others who have asked them to stop. Still, I eagerly await Maven’s full ActivityPub implementation so that we can block them effectively.</p>

<p>This incident got me to thinking about norms and customs on the fediverse and how important they are.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="states-of-exception-versus-the-big-empty">States of Exception versus The Big Empty</h2>
<p>While the Maven incident was happening, the Mastodon instance I’m helping to run, AoIR.social, is gearing up for a wave of new members. The reason is that registration for the <a href="https://aoir.org/aoir2024/">2024 Association of Internet Researchers conference</a> is now open. Every paid AoIR member has access to our Mastodon server, and with every conference we get new folks who join the Association. So, we’re going to get new folks on the server. Our idea is that, since Twitter is now utterly garbage, our members need a new microblogging home to share their work.</p>

<p>There’s an important contrast to be drawn between the Maven incident and the new wave of AoIR.social members. As a start-up, Maven appears to have adopted a classic Silicon Valley logic of the “<a href="https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2799">state of exception</a>,” where one must quickly grow at all costs. One way to supercharge your growth is to simply steal content from other sources. It worked for YouTube back in the 2000s and for AI companies more recently. In the case of Maven, given its AI-based approach, it’s pretty clear the goal was to scrape a bunch of social content from an easy source (Mastodon.social) to train their models upon to produce their “interest-based” social media service.</p>

<p>In contrast, joining a Mastodon server for the first time is a bit of lonely experience. I can imagine that many new AoIR.social members may be looking at their big, empty feeds and wondering what’s next. Whom should I follow? How do I find my colleagues? Will anyone follow me? Even with things like trending topics and recommended accounts to follow, Mastodon and the fediverse is not going to do much to shape what a new user does. In the interviews I’ve conducted <a href="/2024/02/11/Move-Slowy-Preview.html">for my book</a>, I heard from many folks who said joining the fediverse was much colder than joining a corporate social media site.</p>

<p>So, perhaps the steal-and-grow approach is best? Perhaps Maven is justified to ingest a bunch of content to present to would-be new users? Doing so could jumpstart the hard process of making yet another social media site.</p>

<p>But I don’t think so.</p>

<h2 id="the-irony-of-maven">The Irony of Maven</h2>

<p>Let’s consider the supreme irony of Maven’s ingestion of posts without consent. As <a href="https://www.heymaven.com/about">they explain on their “About” page</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s not right that every alternative to the popularity contest on one site is just a popularity contest on another.  We deserve a place to go where you can connect to people simply because you share interests, where you can speak without 100% confidence because you aren’t “performing” in front of a bunch of judges, where you can simply hold a conversation because you’re curious about the subject matter, where everyone isn’t there to build a brand and become an influencer.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That is, they’re suggesting that social media is mired in empty performances in order to gain clout, but thanks to their innovative AI, we can have social media without such clout-chasing. Instead of what’s <em>popular</em>, we’ll get what’s <em>good</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Part of the idea behind Maven is that there is an enormous flux of ideas and interests out there on the internet that we never get to see or interact with because everything we experience is always based on popularity.  That changes with Maven.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This would mitigate</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>the fact that only a tiny elite 0.1% of the population (with say 10K followers or more) can get any substantial amount of engagement while everyone else are just supporting cast members.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That all sounds great: it’s addressing a key concern people have about corporate social media, that it’s just a platform for a handful of famous influencers.</p>

<p>But here’s the irony: in order to get their service off the ground, they ingested millions of posts from the fediverse to make their service seem… <em>more popular than it actually is.</em> They’re using fediverse content to gain attention. Hell, they’ll probably get some media coverage out this, at least.</p>

<p>In contrast, the new member of AoIR.social, staring down a blank feed, might think that the fediverse isn’t for them. There’s nothing to jumpstart the process of building out a presence on the fedi.</p>

<p>But the new fedi member posts once, and gets a reply. Then again, and some followers. Over time, with a bit of work, they’re entering into conversations.</p>

<p>And for those who want to start a fediverse instance, that will <em>really</em> be empty. But if you work at it – making a code of conduct, inviting people to join, doing the work of moderating – then your server will integrate into the fediverse.</p>

<p>Those are the norms of the fediverse: do the work. Explore. Reach out. Moderate. Learn. Grow slowly.</p>

<p>And don’t steal the work of others.</p>

<p>By effectively stealing posts from the fediverse in order to look more popular than it is, Maven has utterly blown their chance to be the alternative they claim they want to be. And even if they have stopped scraping and do a proper ActivityPub implementation, they’re going to be #fediblocked pretty severely from here on out.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Maven" /><category term="Ethics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The ever-alert Liaizon Wakest has informed the rest of us on the ActivityPub-based fediverse of a new social media site, Maven, which has ingested millions of posts from fediverse accounts, including mine. Multiple people have pointed out how this violates consent on the fediverse. In response, the CTO of Maven, Jimmy Secretran, has explained their reasoning: We are trying to connect up to the Fediverse, to allow interaction with other ActivityPub servers. This definitely seems to me to be within the spirit of what ActivityPub enables, but of course, I don’t want to have Maven connect to anybody who doesn’t want it. [Note that I normally do not quote fediverse posts without permission, but in this case, I am making an exception, for reasons that I think will be obvious.] I replied in the thread, arguing that, no, they are not really abiding by the spirit of ActivityPub: This isn’t how this works. No one starts a fediverse (AP) server by ingesting a bunch of posts from others without their consent. They start servers and start federating with the rest of the network. Please stop ingesting posts from AoIR.social (I’m the admin, btw). and The custom is to start a server with a code of conduct, including clear moderation rules, so that the rest of us can make informed choices about federating. What you’ve done with Maven is a pretty massive violation of norms, and likely it will result in your being defederated from many other instances. It’s a poor way to start an ActivityPub implementation. To be fair to Secretran and Maven, they have since stopped scraping my posts and, I presume, those of others who have asked them to stop. Still, I eagerly await Maven’s full ActivityPub implementation so that we can block them effectively. This incident got me to thinking about norms and customs on the fediverse and how important they are.]]></summary></entry></feed>