<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-15T14:42:20-05:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">You Can Post Your Way Out of Fascism if You Own the Means of Posting</title><link href="/2025/02/15/organizing-fascism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You Can Post Your Way Out of Fascism if You Own the Means of Posting" /><published>2025-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2025/02/15/organizing-fascism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/02/15/organizing-fascism.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been mulling over Janus Rose’s recent <em>404 Media</em> article, <a href="https://www.404media.co/you-cant-post-your-way-out-of-fascism/">“You Can’t Post Your Way Out of Fascism.”</a>. In many ways, she’s not wrong. But once again people are ignoring an entirely other way of doing social media that can, in fact, fight fascism.</p>

<p>Rose’s article made the rounds in the social media feeds I follow. And for good reason. Many folks are deeply troubled – and frightened – of what’s happening in the USA. People who pay attention know that the difference between a democratic state and an authoritarian one is <em>indifference</em>, which is to say that if institutions are indifferent about stopping someone like Trump from abusing his power, he is de facto an authoritarian leader. And there’s <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/world/trump-courts-guardrails-analysis-1.7457725">a lot of indifference in the US government right now</a>.</p>

<p>So people want to find a way to stop Trumpism, and they’re eager for guidance – hence the sharing of Rose’s article.</p>

<p>What is to be done? Well, Rose argues that there is no antidote to Trumpian poison to be found in merely taking to social media and posting about his (or Elon Musk’s, or Pete Hesgeth’s, or any other Trumpist’s) bizarre or cruel statements. “If there’s one thing I’d hoped people had learned going into the next four years of Donald Trump as president,” she writes, “it’s that spending lots of time online posting about what people in power are saying and doing is not going to accomplish anything. If anything, it’s exactly what they want.”</p>

<p>Rose points to the work of political theorists and sociologists, arguing that being outraged and overwhelmed is the point. “Thinkers like Jean-Paul Sartre and Hannah Arendt warned us that the point of this deluge is not to persuade, but to overwhelm and paralyze our capacity to act.” She draws on the work of <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/log-off-why-posting-and-politics-almost-never-mix-katherine-cross/78a509d4d3703d91?ean=9781736716861&amp;next=t&amp;next=t">Katherine Cross</a> to argue that corporate social media is all too happy to provide an outlet for the rage. Cross “documents how tech platforms encourage us, through their design affordances, to post and seethe and doomscroll into the void, always reacting and never acting.”</p>

<p>Cross’s language is an apt description of corporate social media – X and Meta properties are now full-on algorithmic outrage engines, designed to keep us looking, scrolling, and posting. (And never forget why: they sell our attention to marketers. That’s their whole purpose.)</p>

<p>Instead, as Rose argues, people need to get organized – to do actual, on-the-ground activism, rather than merely posting about the outage du jour.</p>

<h2 id="slactivism-20">Slactivism 2.0?</h2>
<p>One might be tempted to dismiss Rose’s argument because it’s not new. It’s basically a repitition of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slacktivism">“slacktivism”</a> complaint popularized by Evgeny Morozov in the early 2010s. (Morozov’s own argument repeated arguments made in the 1990s, but I will stick with 2010s on).</p>

<p>Against the backdrop of breathless proclamations about “Facebook revolutions” and “Twitter democracy,” Morozov argued that what was really happening was that corporate social media activism allowed people to confuse clicking “like” on a political post with actually doing something about it. Rose herself repeats this argument (by way of citing Cross): “the greatest [sin] is convincing ourselves that posting is a form of political activism, when it is at best a coping mechanism—an individualist solution to problems that can only be solved by collective action.”</p>

<p>The slacktivism critique probably reached its high water mark with the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/09/world/africa/online-joseph-kony-and-a-ugandan-conflict-soar-to-topic-no-1.html"><em>Kony 2012</em> phenomenon</a>, a short Youtube video which promised viewers that they could bring an end to  Joseph Kony’s use of children as soldiers with “just a click.” Clicking, it was argued, is a far cry from on-the-ground, collective organizing to combat the use of children in warfighting in Uganda.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://us1-browse.startpage.com/av/anon-image?piurl=https%3A%2F%2Fi.pinimg.com%2F236x%2F18%2F4f%2F1e%2F184f1ef000b76e01e7364897acc7ab9a.jpg&amp;sp=1739636813Tad45153b3cc7ed4d39ba00847d5f0d1ff5fbabf86b300c0542af991a999fd134">memes mocking this notion</a> soon followed. The memes encapsulate the major critique of slacktivism: raising “awareness” of social ills does nothing to actually address them.</p>

<p>“Slacktivism” was thus contrasted with “real activism” – marches, protests, communiting organizing, raising and distributing resources, and the like.</p>

<p>So, we have a dichotomy here: either you’re posting and liking on social media, or you’re on the streets, organizing and fighting back. It’s a dichotomy that we’ve been hearing about since at least the 2010s.</p>

<p>Indeed, Rose’s argument also goes in this direction, updating it for 2025. She points to anti-Immigration and Customs Enforcement actions and efforts to provide shelter for the unhoused. She argues that these arose from real organizing, not just posting. “Some of these efforts were coordinated online over Discord and secure messaging apps, but all of them arose from existing networks of neighbors and community organizers, some of whom have been organizing for decades.” Such real organizing is what we need: “when it comes to addressing the problems we face, no amount of posting or passive info consumption is going to substitute the hard, unsexy work of organizing.”</p>

<h2 id="beyond-the-dichotomy">Beyond the Dichotomy</h2>

<p>There are two ways out of the dichotomy between doomscrolling/posting and getting organized. One way is to argue that it is a false dichtomy – that posting and organizing aren’t mutually exclusive. Critics of the “slacktivism” complaint <a href="https://beyond.ubc.ca/online-activism-isnt-just-slacktivism/">have done that work</a>, arguing that online activism enables marginalized people to start getting involved, and that arguments that online activism is worthless discourage people from doing anything at all.</p>

<p>I won’t repeat these arguments, though I certainly talk about them when I teach classes about social movements. Instead, here I will point to another way out, one that I’ve been studying since before the “slacktivism” complaint gained prominence in the early 2010s.</p>

<p>It won’t surprise you to learn that I argue for alternative social media where its users – or, as I prefer, <em>members</em> – are in control. These systems have been around since the early 2010s – indeed, they arose right around the time of Morozov’s slacktivism complaint. The latest iteration is ActivityPub-enabled federated social media.</p>

<p>Can folks doomscroll on the fediverse? Yes. Can folks post on the fediverse? Yes. Might they post about the latest outrage of Trump? Yes, definitely.</p>

<p>Does that mean they are failing to fight incipient fascism? No.</p>

<p>In fact, I argue that the act of running, moderating, and participating in federated social media is precisely the sort of organizing that Rose calls for. It’s just taking place in a media environment, rather than, say, in an NGO’s offices in a city.</p>

<p>Communities who make their own codes of conduct collectively establish how they want to relate to one another. They make decisions about content moderation. They make decisions about federating and defederating with other instances. They are governing themselves online.</p>

<p>This is another example of the “hard, unsexy work of organizing.” Moreover, to quote Rose further: “We need to collectively decide what kind of world we actually do want, and what we’re willing to do to achieve it.” Exactly. And part of that world is the communication infrastructure. Who should own it? Who should govern it? To what purpose should it be put – marketing messages and consumerism, or collective sensemaking?</p>

<p>With Silicon Valley executives and media moguls openly allying themselves with Donald Trump – and with Musk, owner of a major communication platform, actively involved in the Trump administration – we need media that operates outside of corporate control. We need non-capitalist, non-centralized media.</p>

<p>Indeed, we already have it! It’s been around for quite some time! And if you want unsexy hard work, set up your own server, recruit people to it, and moderate it.</p>

<h2 id="the-art-of-forgetting">The Art of Forgetting</h2>
<p>It’s odd that I have to write this, because once again I feel like an actual, existing alternative to corporate social media exists.</p>

<p>But what’s odder to me still is that Rose ropes Bluesky into the same orbit as Twitter/X or Facebook:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Many Twitter refugees made a good choice in migrating from Musk’s X to Bluesky, carving out a new online space that is inhospitable to bigoted debate bros and time-wasting trolls. But in their enemies’ absence, many of these Left-leaning posters have just reverted to dunking on each other, preferring the catharsis of sectarian conflict over the hard work of organizing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I thought Bluesky was supposed to be the alternative that allowed people more control? That puts algorithms in the hands of end users? That gives people choices? Instead, Rose is equating Bluesky with other corporate social media – it, like Meta or X, does not encourage “the hard work of organizing.”</p>

<p>I increasingly tend to agree with that equation. Bluesky PBC has taken venture capital funding. It will face pressure to monetize. And along with that, it seems less and less invested in developing actual ways to decentralize.</p>

<p>However, you might disagree. Let’s set that aside. For now, I will point out that the critique of social media as a space for mere posting, doomscrolling, and algorithmic manipulation simply does not apply to the fediverse. The fediverse <em>demands</em> the hard work of organizing.</p>

<p>But for Rose to write this article, the only way the argument works is to forget the existence of the fediverse.</p>

<p>In my time studying non-corporate social media, I’ve seen this forgetting again and again. Fortunately, I’ve also seen the activists who make, run, moderate and participate in these non-corporate alternatives keep going, in spite of being forgotten or ignored.</p>

<p>That gives me hope that we can post our way out of fascism… on <em>our</em> social media.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="alternative social media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been mulling over Janus Rose’s recent 404 Media article, “You Can’t Post Your Way Out of Fascism.”. In many ways, she’s not wrong. But once again people are ignoring an entirely other way of doing social media that can, in fact, fight fascism.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing: the Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers</title><link href="/2025/02/01/asmNet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing: the Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers" /><published>2025-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2025/02/01/asmNet</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/02/01/asmNet.html"><![CDATA[<p>For years, researching alternative social media has been a bit lonely. But not anymore!</p>

<p>Over the past few months, I’ve been recruiting people to join an email list for academics who study alternative social media, broadly conceived. Every week or so, I’d send an update about the state of ASM, and folks would share articles they’ve written.</p>

<p>It’s gone quite well, and now we’re going public with it!</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-network-of-alternative-social-media-researchers">The Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/">Network of Alternative Social Media Researchers</a> is a home page, blog, archive, and bibliography all centered on ASM research. We have a growing <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/members.html">members</a> page with short bios. As for the archive, I’ve kept my older project, the <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/archive/">S-MAP</a>, where grad students and I collected screenshots of many past and current alternative social media.</p>

<p>These are early days for the project – as you can see, I still have a bit of fine-tuning to do on the website. But I believe this project will lead to collaborations, panels, and even entire conferences exploring the world of ASM.</p>

<p>If you’re an academic doing research in this space, please check of the <a href="https://socialmediaalternatives.org/">ASM network page</a> for more information on joining us.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="alternative social media" /><category term="asm update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For years, researching alternative social media has been a bit lonely. But not anymore!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Alternative Social Media in a Corporate Social Media World</title><link href="/2025/01/18/makingAlts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Alternative Social Media in a Corporate Social Media World" /><published>2025-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2025/01/18/makingAlts</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/01/18/makingAlts.html"><![CDATA[<p>In this week’s <a href="/tags/asm update.html">Alternative Social Media Update</a>, I want to share two things that happened this week and have a fundamental connection: they both indicate the challenges alternative social media developers face when they make ASM in a corporate social media world.</p>

<!-- more -->
<h2 id="item-one-algorithmic-choice">Item One: Algorithmic Choice</h2>

<p>Writing on the W3C <a href="https://www.w3.org/community/socialcg/">Social Web Incubator Community Group</a> email list, <a href="https://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-swicg/2025Jan/0016.html">Bob Wyman asks</a>, “How would algorithmic choice’ laws/regulations impact ActivityPub?” Wyman points to the Missouri Attorney General Bailey’s <a href="https://ago.mo.gov/attorney-general-bailey-promulgates-regulation-securing-algorithmic-freedom-for-social-media-users/">new regulation about “algorithmic freedom” for users of social media</a>. In that press release, the AG says,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Big Tech oligarchs have manipulated consumers’ social media feeds for their own purposes and exercised monopoly control over content moderation. To that end, I am invoking my authority under consumer protection law to ensure Missourians get to control the content they consume on social media.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While he notes this regulation will face implementation and legal challenges, Wyman nonetheless suggests that ActivityPub developers think seriously about new regulations that may affect them:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I think we should anticipate that the coming
to power of Trump and MAGA Republicans is likely to spawn many such
proposals in the coming years. Given this, I think it would be useful to at
least consider what impact such regulations would have on Social Media
systems that rely on ActivityPub and ActivityStreams.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Wyman’s message resonates with me, because I’ve already written about how regulations <a href="/2024/04/10/Online-Harms-Act.html">might affect the fediverse</a>.</p>

<p>In a world where the vast majority of people are only familiar with corporate social media, any new regulations are going to likely be written in ways that can have unintended consequences for alternative social media. The idea of “algorithmic choice” is likely applicable to corporate services such as Instagram or TikTok. It’s less clear how this idea would apply as a regulation of federated social media, which tends to eschew content sorting algorithms in favor of reverse-chronological ordering and boosting. <em>Requiring</em> small, federated instances to implement alternative ways to sort streams would place a major burden on them.</p>

<p>Moreover, if alternative social media continues to grow, corporate social media may lobby to have laws written in such a way that they <em>purposely</em> undermine small alternatives. After all, they have loads of money and power and lobbyists – as we’re seeing now with Meta’s attempts to ingratiate itself with Trump, as well as with Musk’s outright buying of Trump.</p>

<p>Finally, this Missouri AG regulation is clearly coming out of the right-wing “media is full of liberals” view. Consider this closing passage from the press release:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This is the first prong of a comprehensive offensive to protect free speech in 2025,” said Attorney General Bailey. “Now that we have a presidential administration coming into office that will not silence disfavored speech, we’re turning our focus to corporate censorship. Missouri will continue to lead the way in defense of our most fundamental freedoms.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If that AG thinks Meta is left-leaning (and thus “silencing disfavored speech”), keep him away from much of the fediverse! It certainly “silences” the “freedom” of trolls and bigots. This raises a third scenario: regulations that are written specifically by lawmakers to crush independent social media if their values don’t align with right-wing values (perhaps under the guise of protecting children or fighting terrorism).</p>

<h2 id="item-two-terms-of-servitude">Item Two: Terms of Servitude?</h2>
<p>Mark Zuckerberg is tripping over himself to bow down to Trump. The changes at Meta includes the end of fact-checking and <a href="https://www.404media.co/its-total-chaos-internally-at-meta-right-now-employees-protest-zuckerbergs-anti-lgbtq-changes/">explicitly allowing people to harass queer folks</a>.</p>

<p>As a result, once again, folks are looking around for alternatives to corporate social media and there it sits: <a href="https://loops.video/">Pixelfed</a> and <a href="https://loops.video/">Loops.Video</a>. Both are made by <a href="https://dansup.com/">Dan Supernault</a>. Pixelfed is an image-centric, ActivityPub-enabled service. That means that it is geared toward photographers who can share their pictures, but it also means that people on other fediverse systems, like Mastodon, can follow those photographers, see the pictures, and comment on them.</p>

<p>Loops is newer and under development – and it’s the one that prompted a controversy. Loops is meant to be a TikTok-like short video system that will also enable ActivityPub. While it’s in beta, it has been growing at a pretty rapid clip.</p>

<p>Such growth invites scrutiny. A blog post by Phil has taken a <a href="https://bajsicki.com/blog/loops-video-terms/">critical look at Loops.Video’s terms of service</a> and the analysis is troubling. Here’s a key bit of what Phil found: Loops.Video’s TOS includes the paragraph,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>By posting your Contributions to any part of the Services or making Contributions accessible to the Services by linking your account from the Services to any of your social networking accounts, you automatically grant, and you represent and warrant that you have the right to grant, to us an unrestricted, unlimited, irrevocable, perpetual, non-exclusive, transferable, royalty-free, fully-paid, worldwide right, and license to host, use, copy, reproduce, disclose, sell, resell, publish, broadcast, retitle, archive, store, cache, publicly perform, publicly display, reformat, translate, transmit, excerpt (in whole or in part), and distribute such Contributions (including, without limitation, your image and voice) for any purpose, commercial, advertising, or otherwise, and to prepare derivative works of, or incorporate into other works, such Contributions, and grant and authorize sublicenses of the foregoing. The use and distribution may occur in any media formats and through any media channels.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(Note that Phil’s post is absolutely accurate as of this writing – I checked <a href="https://loops.video/legal/terms-of-service">Loops’s TOS myself and saw this language</a>.)</p>

<p>If you’re like me and you regularly read terms of service agreements, I pity you, but also you and I have seen this language many, many times before: this is the language of surveillance capitalism. I <a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/882779130">wrote about this exact issue back in 2014</a>. Like so many corporations before it, Loops.Video is claiming the right to use your content basically forever and for whatever purposes it sees fit – including selling your data to advertisers or training generative AI.</p>

<p>Is this a secret plot by Dan Supernault to bring surveillance capitalism to the predominantly non-capitalist fediverse? Maybe not. To his credit, when this was brought to Supernault’s attention, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@dansup/113848396412970536">he said he’d fix it right away</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There have been several concerns raised about [these terms of service], and I want you to know that we will be replacing them with a better, more clearer set of rules and policies.<sup><a href="#note1">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>

<p>It turns out he used <a href="https://termly.io/">Termly</a>, an online resource to write terms of service agreements. “Please don’t assume the worst,” Supernault wrote. “I’m trying my best but don’t have a team to help me with stuff like this.” Basically, Supernault is saying that, in the absence of a legal team, in the heat of trying to spin up a new service, he went with a boilerplate solution to legal agreements.</p>

<p>I anticipate Supernault will fix this – after all, take a look at <a href="https://pixelfed.social/site/terms">Pixelfed.social’s terms</a>. They are nothing like the Loops terms.</p>

<h2 id="making-asm-in-a-csm-world">Making ASM in a CSM World</h2>
<p>The clash between the values of alternative social media and corporate social media go beyond things like avoiding surveillance capitalism or providing community-based governance and moderation. Increasingly, they will also involve how to manage state-based regulations and legal regimes.</p>

<p>In the case of state regulation, like that of the Missouri AG in the USA, alternative social media developers will have to think about how new regulations will affect them – and they may need to preemptively address them. And I’m not saying they should address them in code, but by advocating for ASM in front of regulators.</p>

<p>In the case of terms of service, it would be good if organizations who support ASM would offer boilerplate terms that are not based on corporate logics and instead reflect fediverse values.</p>

<p>In both cases, making alternative social media in a corporate social media world means more work from communities: not just coding, not just self-governance, but also engaging with regulators and working with lawyers across jurisdictions. This work is already happening, of course, but I imagine more will need to be done.</p>

<h2 id="notes">Notes</h2>
<p id="note1">1) Note that in almost all cases, I reach out to people on the fediverse to get permission to quote them outside of the fedi. In some cases, I do not think the consent is necessary. An example case is when a project leader makes a public statement about that project. I think this post falls under that exception.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="Loops" /><category term="ActivityPub" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this week’s Alternative Social Media Update, I want to share two things that happened this week and have a fundamental connection: they both indicate the challenges alternative social media developers face when they make ASM in a corporate social media world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Watching Threads, Bluesky and Decentralization, and ActivityPub Trust and Safety</title><link href="/2025/01/10/moreThreadsBskyAP.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watching Threads, Bluesky and Decentralization, and ActivityPub Trust and Safety" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2025/01/10/moreThreadsBskyAP</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/01/10/moreThreadsBskyAP.html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekly <a href="/tags/asm update.html">Alternative Social Media update</a> – the first of 2025! – is about getting caught back up with some things that have happened in the past month. First up, I’ll relate the latest changes at Meta to a specific interest of mine, Threads’s fediverse blocklist. Then, I’ll point you to a very fascinating back-and-forth discussion about Bluesky’s ATProto and ActivityPub (as well as OCapN). Finally, I’ll let you know the latest in ActivityPub Trust and Safety.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="monitoriing-threadss-blocklists">Monitoriing Threads’s Blocklists</h2>
<p>By now, you’ve likely heard the news that <a href="https://www.404media.co/its-total-chaos-internally-at-meta-right-now-employees-protest-zuckerbergs-anti-lgbtq-changes/">Meta is changing many of its policies</a> (and board members) – all likely due to the return of Donald Trump to the US Presidency. Aside from recruiting <a href="https://www.espn.com/mma/ufc/story/_/id/35427773/ufc-dana-white-says-criticism-physical-altercation-wife-100-warranted">a domestic abuser</a> to the board and <a href="https://www.aljazeera.com/economy/2025/1/10/metas-decision-to-end-fact-checking-captures-freewheeling-zeitgeist">ending fact-checking</a>, I find the most egregious change to be specifically stating that <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/meta-immigration-gender-policies-change/">calling LGBTQ* folks “mentally ill” is now allowed</a> (I’d say “encouraged” since it’s specifically called for).</p>

<p>I’ll set aside re-declaring my decades-long loathing of Facebook/Meta to talk about a specific project I started a while back, one that is relevant to my interest in alternative social media and has taken on new importance in light of all this.</p>

<p>I’ve been tracking <a href="https://www.threads.net/moderated_servers">Threads’s fediverse blocklist</a>. I first wrote about it <a href="/2024/06/28/ThreadsBlocking.html">midway through last year</a> and <a href="/2024/12/13/threadsmoderation.html">wrote an update last month</a>. Since then, I’ve been regularly collecting the Threads blocklist.</p>

<p>My idea is to see how it evolves over time. I’m curious to see what changes in the future, since the community standards of Meta as a whole have shifted to appease the US right (and thus apparently foist US right-wing views on the rest of the world). Watch this blog for updates.</p>

<h2 id="blueskys-decentralized-heaps">Bluesky’s Decentralized Heaps</h2>
<p>I won’t be able to do these posts justice, but I do want to flag an important blog-post-based conversation that has happened recently. One participant is Christine Lemmer-Webber, who not only was one of the co-authors of ActivityPub but is also <a href="https://spritely.institute/">actively working on new decentralized web protocols</a>. The other participant is Bryan Newbold, a Bluesky engineer.</p>

<p>This all started with Lemmer-Webber’s incredible post, <a href="https://dustycloud.org/blog/how-decentralized-is-bluesky/">“How Decentralized is Bluesky, Actually?”</a>. Again, I can’t do it justice – go read it, but note it’s long and gets technical. My takeaway from that post was that <a href="/2024/04/30/DecentralizedNoncentralized.html">I remain right in my basic claim</a> that Bluesky is “decentralized” in the sense that it is a center is spinning off parts of itself.</p>

<p>Reading Lemmer-Webber’s post leads me to see Bluesky as decentralized in the same way Bitcoin is: sure, you can get the entire blockchain, but it’s <a href="https://ycharts.com/indicators/bitcoin_blockchain_size">630GB and steadily growing</a>, so why would you? Likewise, if I read Lemmer-Webber correctly, Bluesky’s “shared heap” architecture would mean anyone hoping to run a fully-fledge ATProto-based service would have to replicate all the messages in the network. As she writes,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A world of full self-hosting is not possible with Bluesky. In fact, it is worse than the storage requirements, because the message delivery requirements become quadratic at the scale of full decentralization: to send a message to one user is to send a message to all. Rather than writing one letter, a copy of that letter must be made and delivered to every person on earth.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In response, <a href="https://whtwnd.com/bnewbold.net/3lbvbtqrg5t2t">Bryan Newbold notes</a> that this is not incorrect: Bluesky is making a mass public messaging system, which is distinct from small community networking found among self-hosters. “Smaller more densely-connected communities are super important, and are where folks should probably spend the majority of their hours,” he writes. But “Smaller communities are probably not well served by global public broadcast systems.”</p>

<p>To be fair to him, no, small communities aren’t well-served by massive global broadcast. (If only there was a way to build a global network out of many small communities who band together through an open protocol and shared values. Hmm.)</p>

<p>There’s more to this back-and-forth – a lot more. Including <a href="https://dustycloud.org/blog/re-re-bluesky-decentralization/">Lemmer-Webber’s reply to Newbold’s reply</a>, where she goes through the history of ideas of decentralization, all in support of her call for a new approach, <a href="https://ocapn.org/">OCapN</a>. It’s worth a read – go read it, too! – but I will note that it appears both Lemmer-Webber and Newbold agree that Bluesky’s architecture is, in fact, a “shared heap” – which is not amenable for federation (and thus, in my view, it’s not amenable for <em><a href="/2024/04/30/DecentralizedNoncentralized.html">noncentralization</a></em>.)</p>

<h2 id="activitypub-trust-and-safety">ActivityPub Trust and Safety</h2>

<p>Earlier this week, I took part in my first <a href="https://github.com/swicg/activitypub-trust-and-safety">ActivityPub Trust and Safety Task Force</a> meeting. This group, which is currently led by Emelia Smith and Darius Kazemi, has three foci. One is to <a href="https://github.com/swicg/activitypub-trust-and-safety/issues/32">write a report</a> on the current state of moderation practices on the fediverse. Another is to <a href="https://github.com/swicg/activitypub-trust-and-safety/issues/38">improve ActivityPub’s moderation tooling</a>. A third (which I will admit isn’t clear to me just yet) is to work on <a href="https://github.com/swicg/activitypub-trust-and-safety/issues/41">content warnings and labels</a>.</p>

<p>It’s early stages for this task force, although the folks involved have been working on these issues for years. Much of the discussion during my first meeting was about scope – a really important question, given the scale of “trust and safety”! For my part, I intend to contribute to the report. To do <em>that</em>, I will need to do a lot more work studying the various issues being raised in the task force’s <a href="https://github.com/swicg/activitypub-trust-and-safety/issues/">Github</a>, as well as <a href="https://codeberg.org/fediverse/fep">Fediverse Enhancement Proposals</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Threads" /><category term="Bluesky" /><category term="ActivityPub" /><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This weekly Alternative Social Media update – the first of 2025! – is about getting caught back up with some things that have happened in the past month. First up, I’ll relate the latest changes at Meta to a specific interest of mine, Threads’s fediverse blocklist. Then, I’ll point you to a very fascinating back-and-forth discussion about Bluesky’s ATProto and ActivityPub (as well as OCapN). Finally, I’ll let you know the latest in ActivityPub Trust and Safety.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Threads and the Failure of Global Content Moderation</title><link href="/2024/12/13/threadsmoderation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Threads and the Failure of Global Content Moderation" /><published>2024-12-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/12/13/threadsmoderation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/12/13/threadsmoderation.html"><![CDATA[<p>This week’s <a href="/tags/asm update.html">Alternative Social Media Update</a> turned out to be more of a critique of corporate social media, specifically Meta’s Threads.</p>

<p>It all started when I saw the news that Meta had <a href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-meta-zuckerberg-inauguration-donation-c540bf7c638def11b8428e633965c718">donated $1 million to Trump’s inauguration fund</a>. Look, I’m an American. I know how this works – the wealthy buy influence by giving to politicians. It’s not particularly shocking to see Meta doing this – it’s part of their longstanding practices of lobbying those in power so they can continue to operate with little to no regulations.</p>

<p>But it simply reaffirms my desire to explore the world of communication outside the control of a handful of corporations.</p>

<p>Searching for coverage of Meta’s donation led me to a bit of a rabbit hole of recent news about Meta’s Threads. Much of it comes from <a href="https://www.theverge.com/">The Verge</a>, and most of it is about Threads’s moderation failures.</p>

<p>Since Threads is slowly rolling out ActivityPub capabilities, this ASM Update about Threads does have a lot of relevance to the fediverse.</p>

<p>The TL;DR version is: after taking a second look, I continue to see Meta’s Threads as a bad actor and <a href="https://fedipact.online/">worthy of being blocked</a> by the rest of the fediverse.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="californian-ideology-at-scale">Californian Ideology at Scale</h2>
<p>Writing in the aforementioned <em>Verge</em>, <a href="https://fedipact.online/">Adam Heath reports</a> that Meta is now double-thinking their previous moderation practices. The story is nominally about how Meta was overactive in moderating during the COVID pandemic (though Meta blames Biden for that) as well as about how Meta’s automated moderation systems are too “ham-fisted.”</p>

<p>But the real problem is not explicitly stated. See if you can find it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nick Clegg, Meta’s president of global affairs, told reporters on Monday that the company’s moderation “error rates are still too high” and pledged to “improve the precision and accuracy with which we act on our rules.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You’re probably thinking I’m going to critique the fact that Meta hired Nick Clegg, but as I said, I’m an American, so I know little of him other than he helped raise tuition fees in the UK and helped preside over Brexit.</p>

<p>No, my issue is with the title “president of global affairs.”</p>

<p>I find it inconceivable that any corporation can engage in content moderation on a global scale. This is particularly apparent to me after experiencing the fediverse, where content moderation is achieved at a local level on a small scale. Meta, X, TikTok: all attempt to impose their corporate standards on all the world. Perhaps we can come up with global standards and ethics – but the vehicle for doing it won’t be through top-down, for-profit corporate behemoths.</p>

<h2 id="too-big-to-comprehend">Too Big to Comprehend</h2>
<p>As a result of attempting the impossible task of moderating the globe, Meta has grown to be huge and complex. It’s so big we need dedicated watchdogs. We need <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/10/9/24266096/instagram-threads-moderation-account-post-deleted-limited">investigative journalists</a> to report on trends in corporate social media, including trends about poor moderation.</p>

<p>Indeed, Meta is so big that its own executives don’t know what’s going on. Consider this exchange on Threads:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Social media consultant Matt Navarra — who was notified his Threads account is getting downranked after sharing a story about how Tom Brady fell for a Meta AI hoax — got a response to his public complaint from Mosseri. “Looking into it…” Mosseri said. Meta didn’t immediately respond to a request for comment on the issues.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If the system is so opaque the head of Instagram/Threads, Adam Mosseri, can’t figure it out… well.</p>

<p>Again, contrast this with the fediverse. On my previous instance, if I had a problem, I could contact the admin directly. I didn’t need to post publicly and hope the admin saw it. (On my current instance, AoIR.social, I <em>am</em> the admin, so people contact me for help.) The fediverse, at its best, is a far less abstracted, human system.</p>

<h2 id="bots-cant-moderate">Bots can’t Moderate</h2>

<p>Speaking of humans, Meta is <a href="https://www.facebook.com/help/1584908458516247/">increasingly using bots to moderate</a>. Unsurprisingly, this results in arbitrary decisions.</p>

<p>That’s the main complaint of posts tagged <a href="https://www.threads.net/@mikethebearded/post/DA2D_C4yaya">“Threads Moderation Failures,”</a> which has been steadily documenting the weird and wild world of AI-based content moderation. For a corporation already incapable of understanding what its own moderation practices are (“I’ll look into it!”), ceding more and more moderation decisions to AI seems like a bad choice.</p>

<p>We could ask Meta hire more humans to do the job, but then again… some of the last humans who did that work were summarily <a href="https://jacobin.com/2024/02/kenya-courts-meta-content-moderation-union">fired after trying to unionize</a>.</p>

<h2 id="your-voice-our-vote">Your Voice, Our Vote</h2>
<p>But perhaps all of this will be made right once Thread users have their voices heard via a <a href="https://www.threads.net/@oncescuradu/post/DDfgI0_o_3Y">survey on content moderation</a>. Since Meta attempts to moderate a global scale, perhaps getting tons of input from its users might shed light on how to tackle that task. The survey appears to ask about users’ attitudes towards sharing on Threads – whether or not they feel inhibited from sharing because they fear being “penalized.”</p>

<p>Maybe Threads will learn from the survey and improve their moderation?</p>

<p>I have my doubts. I’ve seen Facebook/Meta do this sort of faux popular polling throughout its history. As <a href="https://archive.org/details/UnlikeUs/page/n223/mode/2up">I wrote back in the early 2010s</a>, Facebook often held votes on changes to their Terms of Service agreements and, no matter the vote, they adopted the TOS they intended to the whole time.</p>

<p>Might they do the same with their Threads content moderation survey? Who knows? Their content moderation decisions are so opaque that it would be impossible to tell, anyway. I believe the real goal is to keep their metaphorical shopping mall aesthetic intact, and to keep regulators at bay. And probably to justify their cost-cutting AI-based moderation practices.</p>

<h2 id="you-block-me-no-way-man-no-way-i-block-you">You Block Me? No way, man. No, way. I block you!</h2>
<p>All of the above has renewed my belief that AoIR.social’s decision to preemptively block Threads (and sign <a href="https://fedipact.online/">the fedipact</a>) was the right decision. AoIR.social is a Mastodon instance I help run. We provide federated social media to members of the <a href="https://aoir.org/">Association of Internet Researchers</a>, a group of folks who have a pretty good idea about how Meta operates.</p>

<p>But I am a bit disappointed our block isn’t mutual. Readers might recall I wrote about Threads’s Fediverse Blocklist – their own list of blocked servers. I first looked at it <a href="/2024/06/28/ThreadsBlocking.html">six months ago</a>. I checked it again today – it has grown from 660 back in June to 843 today.</p>

<p>As I wrote back in June, many of the blocks make total sense. But some don’t. I mentioned Scholar.social as one that does not need to be blocked. Another one that’s been blocked this whole time is Writeout.ink, which is a small server with a clear code of conduct.</p>

<p>Another one that doesn’t – and was added to the list between June and now – is Darius Kazemi’s Friend.camp, the flagship Hometown server. The reason Threads’s blocklist offers is “no public timeline.” I asked Darius about it, and he says that’s true, but he thinks it’s been true for some time now.</p>

<p>And surely there are many many more servers without public timelines than 800. So why is Friend.camp blocked? Maybe it’s because Friend.camp blocks Threads. “We federated with threads for a long time but we defederated a few months ago based on user consensus,” Darius told me. So maybe blocking Threads triggered a mutual block?</p>

<p>But… AoIR.social blocks Threads! And we’re not on the list! What do I have to do to get AoIR.social blocked by Threads? I kinda want that badge of honor.</p>

<p>In all seriousness, while I praised Threads for publicly posting its blocklist, noting this is a very transparent move, it’s still pretty opaque how they’re making these choices. Just as Threads is being criticized by its users for clumsy AI-based moderation decisions, I anticipate Threads will automatically and arbitrarily block a fediverse server that does not deserve it but whose members really do want to connect to folks on Threads. I don’t see Threads putting a lot of effort into making informed blocking decisions. That’s not what Meta does. And for those instances that want to federate with Meta, be prepared to behave how Meta says – and even if you do, you may be arbitrarily blocked. And be prepared to <a href="https://help.instagram.com/contact/1574148669814359/">fill out a form and hope</a> that someone, somewhere considers your case.</p>

<p>If people are going to use blocklists – and <a href="/2023/09/20/blocklists.html">I think they should</a> – they need to be managed by people on behalf of coherent communities. Not by robots on behalf of a profit-seeking corporation. And they need to be documents that networks of communities gather around to discuss how to build out a federated network. Not dictated to the network by a powerful node.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Threads" /><category term="ASM update" /><category term="moderation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This week’s Alternative Social Media Update turned out to be more of a critique of corporate social media, specifically Meta’s Threads.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marp + BeautifulSoup</title><link href="/2024/12/07/marpbeautifulsoup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marp + BeautifulSoup" /><published>2024-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/12/07/marpbeautifulsoup</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/12/07/marpbeautifulsoup.html"><![CDATA[<p>The FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream just got a bit dreamier.</p>

<p>Previously, <a href="/2024/12/01/marp.html">I wrote about Marp</a>, which is a <a href="https://marp.app/">Markdown-based way to generate presentation slides</a>. When I wrote about Marp last, I was speculating that it would be very useful:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m going to do it: I’m going all-on on Marp for a while….  I suspect Marp is a future fixture of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, it’s true. On Friday, I gave a presentation over Zoom using a Marp-based slide deck. You can <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/ITS_presentation.html">see the files here</a>. It worked wonderfully!</p>

<p>And I did something more. Marp produces responsive, semantic HTML. HTML can be parsed with <a href="https://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/">BeautifulSoup</a>, a Python library.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Marp enables me to easily add slide notes with basic HTML comments, like this:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;!-- Slide notes go here --&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>After Marp processes the Markdown file and converts it into HTML, I could see that those comments with a class, “bespoke-marp-note.” Which means I could pull out all the notes directly from the HTML and create a new file, with the notes only, with BeautifulSoup.</p>

<p>I’m no programmer, but I can search for guides with the best of them. I wrote a python script to pull the comments and produce a second HTML with just my script. <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/ITS_presentationText.html">Here’s the result</a>.</p>

<p>This gives me a great time-saver: instead of writing a script and creating the slides separately, I just do it all in one Markdown file, and the scripts generate everything I need from that single file. This will save hours of work!</p>

<p>Another nice thing about this is that I can share the text of my presentation easily over the web. Prior to this, I rewrote the presentation as a new Markdown file and posted it to the blog. That would add hours to the task. The new way will be automated!</p>

<p>Here’s the Pyton script I wrote (if you see poor coding on my part, be gentle):</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>from bs4 import BeautifulSoup as BS
from bs4 import Comment


import requests
import getopt, sys

# This gets the system argument, which should be the Markdown file I'm exporting
filename = sys.argv[1]

# strips the final three characters, '.md', from the file name
filename = filename[:-3]

# changes file name for text
filenameText = filename + 'Text.html'

print(filenameText)

# adding local HTML file
with open(filename + '.html') as f:
    soup = BS(f, 'html.parser')

# parsing notes
# this will add a header, print to file

i = 0
presentation = (soup.find('h1'))
content = '''&lt;html&gt;
&lt;body&gt;'''
content += str(presentation)

# this will add slide headers and the notes

for note in soup.find_all(class_='bespoke-marp-note'):
  i += 1
  content += '&lt;h2&gt;Slide ' + str(i) + '&lt;/h2&gt;'
  content += str(note)
content += '''
&lt;!-- Some javascript here --&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
'''

# Writing the content to an HTML file
with open(str(filenameText), 'w') as file:
    file.write(content)
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>You might notice a variable, “filename = sys.argv[1]”. That is there because I wrote a bash script, exportPresentation.sh, to automate the whole export process:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>#!/bin/bash
~/.local/share/marp/marp --theme ./CSS/custom.scss --html $1
python pullComments.py "$1"

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>That little script invokes marp-cli to convert the Markdown file, and then the python script recieves the file name (e.g., I’d type “sh exportPresentation.sh presentation.md” into the shell).</p>

<p>Again, much like using CSS to build a presentation, coming up with these scripts took a bit of time, but in the long run, I’m making presentation creation – and sharing! – that much easier.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Marp" /><category term="beautifulsoup" /><category term="goal 1" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream just got a bit dreamier.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Update: Can this platform survive?</title><link href="/2024/12/06/survive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update: Can this platform survive?" /><published>2024-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/12/06/survive</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/12/06/survive.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a pretty packed week, between the end of the semester, my participation in a small conference, and a sick kiddo at home. So this week’s ASM update is a short one.</p>

<p>Along with some colleagues at American University, I have a new publication out.</p>

<h2 id="can-this-platform-survive-governance-challenges-for-the-fediverse">Can This Platform Survive? Governance Challenges for the Fediverse</h2>

<p>This is a new paper from the <em><a href="https://ijoc.org/index.php/ijoc/article/view/22254">International Journal of Communication</a>,</em> written by Thomas Struett, Aram Sinnreich, Patricia Aufderheide, and myself.</p>

<p>Here’s the abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the wake of recent crises at commercial social media platforms like Twitter and Reddit, the “fediverse” has gained adoption and visibility as a noncommercial alternative for individuals, communities, and institutions to develop channels of public communication, dialogue, and debate. In this article, we draw on illustrative examples from the history of digital civic discourse and identify 6 ways in which history shows us how the potential benefits of the fediverse are at risk of subversion. We discuss several potential threats to these spaces of civil discourse, including challenges inherent to distributed governance, commercial platform capture, inclusive access, moderation at scale, reputational assaults by commercial competitors, and the neoliberal technoromanticism familiar from previous digital innovations. These threats must be addressed collectively and proactively by key fediverse stakeholders in an ecology whose ruling values are noncommercialism, decentralization, open source, free association, and wariness of traditional governance.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Academic publishing is slow. We worked this up over a year ago. It’s interesting to see what parts of the paper hold up – frankly, I think all of our challenges are still at play.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="publications" /><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been a pretty packed week, between the end of the semester, my participation in a small conference, and a sick kiddo at home. So this week’s ASM update is a short one.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marp!</title><link href="/2024/12/01/marp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marp!" /><published>2024-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/12/01/marp</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/12/01/marp.html"><![CDATA[<p>As avid readers of my blog know, I am livin’ the <a href="/tags/fald.html">FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream</a>: I use FOSS tools to do my academic work. I use Nextcloud to manage files and <a href="/2021/09/25/Appointments.html">handle appointments</a>, Zotero and Zettlr to take notes, and LibreOffice Writer to write books and articles. This blog runs on Jekyll. I love it all!</p>

<p>But there has been one part of the Lifestyle that has consistently been a disappointment: <a href="https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/impress/">LibreOffice Impress</a>, the presentation software. While I use Writer all the time and enjoy doing so, Impress has always bothered me. But I’m not one to complain too much, since LibreOffice software is provided free-of-charge and with a FOSS license. I’ve soldiered on with it to make presentations for conferences and class teaching.</p>

<p>But that might change. <a href="https://marp.app/">Marp</a> – the Markdown Presentation Ecosystem – is poised to become a key part of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream. If you’re familiar with Markdown, Marp is a really awesome tool.
<!-- more --></p>

<h2 id="thank-you-linux-matters">Thank you, Linux Matters</h2>
<p>I learned about Marp from the <a href="https://linuxmatters.sh/43/"><em>Linux Matters</em> podcast</a>. Like any good podcast episode, their discussion of Marp made me drop everything to learn more. As Mark on <em>Linux Matters</em> explained, Marp allows for presentations to be built very quickly using Markdown. Since I use Markdown regularly to write up notes, particularly for class lectures, I was intrigued.</p>

<p>And when I started experimenting with Marp, I think Mark might have undersold it a bit!</p>

<h2 id="markdown-its-that-easy">Markdown: It’s That Easy</h2>
<p>So, let’s make a slide. Instead of firing up LibreOffice Impress, though, I just open a text editor a create a Markdown (.md) file.</p>

<p>First, I add “frontmatter,” which tells the system how to handle the file:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
marp: true
---
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>(You can do more with it than that, but we’ll keep it simple).</p>

<p>Next, I start adding slides:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
marp: true
---
# Slide Title

Slide Text
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>It’s that easy.</p>

<p>That sort of thing <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#3">looks like this</a>.</p>

<p>Let’s add another slide, this time with a list. Lists are handled in the Markdown way:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
marp: true
---
# Slide Title
Slide Text

---
# Slide with List
- List item 1
- List item 2
- List item 3
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here’s an <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#4">example of what that looks like</a>.</p>

<p>Of course, people often use more than just text in slides. I can add images, as well. Marp uses a syntax like this:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>![command](imagefile.jpg)
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Where “command” handles stuff like size, whether the image is in the background, opacity or the like. So a three-slide presentation with an image might look like this:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
marp: true
---
# Slide Title
Slide Text

---
# Slide with List
- List item 1
- List item 2
- List item 3

---
![command](imagefile.jpg)
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>However, as you’ll see, I prefer to do things with HTML, specifically the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;figure&gt;</code> semantic tag, and style with CSS.</p>

<h2 id="css-zen-presentations">CSS Zen Presentations</h2>
<p>I love CSS. It blew me away when I saw the <a href="https://csszengarden.com/">CSS Zen Garden</a>, which was launched in 2003 to promote the full separation of content and presentation. I am no designer – don’t ask me to come up with color schemes! But I did take the CSS Zen Garden idea and apply it to <a href="https://www.robertwgehl.org">my website</a>, where you can choose your style if you view it on a laptop/tablet.</p>

<p>Add in <a href="https://sass-lang.com/">SASS</a>, which allows for variables, and CSS is a really powerful tool.</p>

<p>So when I learned Marp uses CSS – with some SASS-like aspects – to handle the design of slides, I knew I would like it.</p>

<p>Marp comes with some default themes, but I was keen to build my own. It turns out that all I had to do was write a CSS file and point the Marp command line to it via a terminal:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>marp -w --theme ./CSS/custom.scss testPresentation.md
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here’s a tip for those of you wanting to style via CSS: Marp uses the HTML semantic tag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;section&gt;</code> for each slide. To customize the whole presentation, style <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;section&gt;</code>, rather than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;body&gt;</code>, and you’re good to go: the whole presentation will be formatted.</p>

<p>And what about specific slides? Marp uses an HTML-style comment you can add to Markdown: adding <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;!-- _class: CLASSNAME --&gt;</code> to the start of the specific slide adds a class that can be targeted. For example, I use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;!-- _class: title --&gt;</code> on title slides. <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#1">Here’s how that looks</a>.</p>

<h2 id="avoiding-death-by-powerpoint-the-css-way">Avoiding Death by Powerpoint the CSS way</h2>

<p>When I present, I do my best to avoid <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Iwpi1Lm6dFo">death by Powerpoint</a>. I use a lot of slides with minimal objects on a dark background.</p>

<p>Of course, with CSS, backgrounds are fully under my control. And since Marp allows SASS-like variables, I could just set a global value for the background (as well as other elements) in my custom.scss file:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>:root {
  font-family: "Cantarell Light", sans-serif;
  --text-color: #999999;
  --bg-color: #000;
  --standard-margin: 10%;
  --shadow: 20px 10px 10px #121212;
}
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here you’ll see I lazily set it to black. I will likely choose some other verydark color, but for now that will do. (And, if I want to change it, I just have to adjust that one value. That’s it!)</p>

<p>Avoiding Death by Powerpoint means I tend to use a lot of single images. Wth two little bits – some Markdown/HTML and some CSS – I can drop in images with formatting.</p>

<p>Here’s the example Markdown:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;!-- _class: one-column --&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="images/stage.jpg" alt="a picture of a theater stage"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A theater stage &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Notice I’ve moved away from the simpler <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">![command](image.jpg)</code> structure to an HTML5 semantic markup, complete with alt text and caption. It’s a bit more typing (or copypasting) but it will be worth it. Notice also the class, “one-column.”</p>

<p>Now here’s some corresponding CSS:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>section.one-column figure {
  float: left;
  width: 90%;
  margin-left:8%;
  margin-top: 4%;
}

img {
  width: 96%;
  float: left;
  z-index:-1;
}

figcaption {
  margin-top: -8%;
  font-size: 200%;
  width: 80%;
  line-height: 200%;
  float: left;
  text-align: center;
  background-color:var(--bg-color);
  opacity: .8;
  z-index:1;
}
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The result can <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#6">be seen here</a>. Here’s a screenshot, too:</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/presentationExample.png" alt="a screenshot of an example presentation slide. It's a picture of the woods on a black background." />
  <figcaption>A screenshot of the slide</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="i-can-make-it-do-things-libreoffice-impress-never-could">I can make it do things LibreOffice Impress never could</h2>

<p>Much like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lxNYAe85L20">Kurt with his magazines</a>, with CSS I can make presentations do whatever I like. Including something that has eluded me in LibreOffice Impress for years: captions for images. That picture of the woods above includes a caption, styled with CSS.</p>

<p>CSS has a lot of power, and I’m only scratching the surface of what could be done. Once my CSS template is complete, all I have to do from here on out is edit Markdown files. This can work for academic presentations as well as for class lectures (which I often base off Markdown files edited in Zettlr.)</p>

<h2 id="dont-forget-about-html">Don’t forget about HTML</h2>

<p>In the above example, I link to a <a href="https://robertwgehl.org/presentations/testPresentation.html#6">specific slide in the presentation.</a>. I can link to any point of the presentation. On the web. In beautiful HTML, with alt text for images.</p>

<p>This is so cool!</p>

<p>All I have to do is run a terminal command with marp-cli:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>marp -w --theme ./CSS/custom.scss testPresentation.md
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Marp autogenerates an HTML file with CSS included. I move that to a server and boom! The presentation is online. This is so cool!</p>

<p>And I’ve taken a look – it looks very similar across devices. Responsive!</p>

<p>Now, instead of futzing with a LibreOffice .OPD file (or worse, so much worse, a .PPTX file), I can just post my presentations to the web and run them from there. It includes a presentation view, which shows notes that I put in the corresponding Markdown file within HTML comments.</p>

<p>Or, if I want to run it off my local machine, I can just present a local HTML file.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h2>

<p>I’m going to do it: I’m going all-on on Marp for a while. If things go poorly, I’ll update this blog accordingly. But right now, I suspect Marp is a future fixture of the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="FALD" /><category term="Marp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As avid readers of my blog know, I am livin’ the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream: I use FOSS tools to do my academic work. I use Nextcloud to manage files and handle appointments, Zotero and Zettlr to take notes, and LibreOffice Writer to write books and articles. This blog runs on Jekyll. I love it all!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM update: libraries, libraries everywhere</title><link href="/2024/11/29/libraries.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM update: libraries, libraries everywhere" /><published>2024-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/11/29/libraries</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/11/29/libraries.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a simple, yet deep ASM update for this week. Last week, I posted about some <a href="/2024/11/22/ASMupdateResearch.html">recent research</a> in the realm of alternative social media. I also drew attention to the bibliography I maintain <a href="/bib.html">here on this blog</a>. In response to that post, folks on the fediverse alerted me to other bibliographic projects collecting research in related ideas. Here I want to highlight two of them.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="fediverse-observatory">Fediverse Observatory</h2>

<p>This is a <a href="https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861035/fediverse_observatory/items/LFCK293Q/library">Zotero Library</a> with dozens of entries, some dating back to 2005. As the name implies, much of it focuses on the fediverse, but there are sub-libraries focusing on topics like “migration” across social media, social media fatigue, and Musk and Threads.</p>

<h2 id="investigación-sobre-el-fediverso">Investigación sobre el Fediverso</h2>

<p>This is a <a href="https://www.pedrolr.es/research/infonomy2024/fediverseresearch.html">library</a> from Pedro Lázaro Rodríguez based in part on the citations from a <a href="https://infonomy.scimagoepi.com/index.php/infonomy/article/view/34">fediverse research paper</a> published in <em>Infonomy</em> 2024. It’s divided into two sections, one focusing on research that has emerged since the <em>Infonomy</em> paper, and the second with the original reference material for that paper.</p>

<h2 id="libraries">Libraries!</h2>

<p>While this ASM update is just these two links, as you can see, this area of research is rapidly growing. I am not going to lie: I will gleefully mine these libraries for use in my own. For new researchers and grad students, there is a wealth of materials out there to gain insights into the world of alternative social media. It’s such an exciting time!</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="Alternative Social Media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s a simple, yet deep ASM update for this week. Last week, I posted about some recent research in the realm of alternative social media. I also drew attention to the bibliography I maintain here on this blog. In response to that post, folks on the fediverse alerted me to other bibliographic projects collecting research in related ideas. Here I want to highlight two of them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM Update: New Research Edition</title><link href="/2024/11/22/ASMupdateResearch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM Update: New Research Edition" /><published>2024-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/11/22/ASMupdateResearch</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/11/22/ASMupdateResearch.html"><![CDATA[<p>Bluesky continues to blow up. I hear about it everywhere. It’s so backed up the <a href="https://github.com/snarfed/bridgy-fed/issues/1520">Brid.gy system has slowed to a crawl</a>.</p>

<p>But instead of focusing yet again on Bluesky, this week I wanted to do something that is long overdue: I want to draw your attention to some new research in alternative social media. You can find these works in the <a href="/bib.html">bibliography page</a> of this blog, or reach out to me if you want to join the corresponding Zotero library.</p>

<p>Here will highlight some new papers, mostly focusing on Mastodon (and to a lesser extent the rest of the fediverse). As you will see, there’s a variety of concerns: archiving and curation, moderation, and news sharing. Links are in the titles below.</p>

<p>Also, I am now building an email listserv focused on academic research on alternative social media (broadly conceived). Are you an academic who wants to join the list? We have 50 colleagues there now! If you want to join, <a href="https://www.robertwgehl.org/contact.php">contact me</a> (preferably with a university email address) and give me some background info and I can add you to the group.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="frost-arnold-karen-2024-beyond-corporate-social-media-platforms-the-epistemic-promises-and-perils-of-alternative-social-media-topoi-october-httpsdoiorg101007s11245-024-10102-2">Frost-Arnold, Karen. 2024. “<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11245-024-10102-2">Beyond Corporate Social Media Platforms: The Epistemic Promises and Perils of Alternative Social Media</a>.” <em>Topoi</em>, October. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11245-024-10102-2.</h2>

<p>ABSTRACT: “In recent years, we have witnessed increased interest in alternatives to the dominant corporate social media sites, such as Facebook, Twitter (now X), and TikTok. Tired of disinformation, harassment, privacy violations, and the general degradation of platforms, users and technologists have looked for non-corporate alternatives. Not-for-profit social media platforms emerging from free/libre and open-source software (FLOSS) communities based on non-centralized infrastructure have emerged as promising alternatives. For applied epistemology of the internet, these alternative social media platforms present an opportunity to study different ways of producing knowledge together online. This paper evaluates the epistemic potential for such alternative, non-corporate social media. I present an epistemological framework for analyzing the epistemic promises and perils of alternative social media. Then I apply this framework to the case of Mastodon, a federated, open-source microblogging platform. Mastodon’s structure and culture of openness present opportunities to avoid many of the epistemic perils of biased and untrustworthy large corporate platforms. However, Mastodon’s risks include techno-elitism, white ignorance, and isolated, epistemically toxic communities.”</p>

<h2 id="lister-pen-2024-creating-a-city-for-all-of-us-the-possible-role-of-the-fediverse-in-archiving-civic-urban-memory-digital-society-3-3-53-httpsdoiorg101007s44206-024-00137-8-open-access">Lister, Pen. 2024. “<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s44206-024-00137-8">Creating a City for All of Us: The Possible Role of the Fediverse in Archiving Civic Urban Memory</a>.” Digital Society 3 (3): 53. https://doi.org/10.1007/s44206-024-00137-8. OPEN ACCESS</h2>

<p>ABSTRACT: “This paper attempts to build a case for adopting the model of the Fediverse to archive digital citizen-generated urban memory. Examining literature from several relevant fields of debate acts as a pragmatic foundation for reasoning to then outline potential core technical functionality for provision of such an archive, using the Mastodon app as an example. This ‘civic urban memory’ archive is considered as open, curated by citizens themselves and owned by them through civic public ownership in a context of technological sovereignty. Reflecting on issues of citizen self curated and moderated memory collection archives, and the potential for opt-in or anonymous archive posting may offer some mechanisms for fair and open curation, moderation and privacy protection in such archives. Conceptual backdrop for a civic urban memory archive is placed in current debates concerning civic technological platforms acting as a digital public good in a context of a techno-social contract for learning, with a co-constructed shared civic urban memory forming part of open incidental lifelong learning in a future learning city.”</p>

<h2 id="quian-alberto-xosé-lópez-garcía-and-xosé-soengas-pérez-2024-periodismo-y-redes-sociales-alternativas-del-fediverso-estudio-de-la-presencia-de-medios-nativos-digitales-y-matriciales-en-mastodon-revista-latina-de-comunicación-social-no-83-september-140-httpsdoiorg104185rlcs-2025-2338">Quian, Alberto, Xosé López-García, and Xosé Soengas-Pérez. 2024. “<a href="https://nuevaepoca.revistalatinacs.org/index.php/revista/article/view/2338">Periodismo y Redes Sociales Alternativas Del Fediverso: Estudio de La Presencia de Medios Nativos Digitales y Matriciales En Mastodon</a>.” Revista Latina de Comunicación Social, no. 83 (September), 1–40. https://doi.org/10.4185/rlcs-2025-2338.</h2>

<p>ABSTRACT: “Introducción: Se analiza la presencia de periódicos en Mastodon, la plataforma social más popular del Fediverso y alternativa a X (Twitter) en este ecosistema de redes descentralizadas e interoperables. Metodología: De una muestra (n=38) de nativos digitales y matriciales de España se obtuvo una submuestra de periódicos (n=20) y cuentas (n=28) en Mastodon. Se identificaron cuentas oficiales y no oficiales, bots y no automatizadas, activas e inactivas, instancias en las que se alojan y accesos directos en los sitios web de los medios. También se identificó la fecha de creación de las cuentas para comprobar si aparecieron antes o después de la compra de Twitter por parte de Elon Musk, operación que disparó la popularidad de Mastodon. Resultados: Identificamos 13 cuentas oficiales (10 nativos y 3 matriciales), ninguna en instancias propias, y 15 cuentas no oficiales (9 matriciales y 6 nativos) conectadas por RSS por administradores de instancias de Mastodon. Los matriciales muestran mayor proporción de cuentas activas que los nativos digitales. La proporción de cuentas automatizadas es alta para ambas categorías. Se observa un “efecto Musk” en la creación de cuentas. Solo elDiario.es y El Salto (nativos digitales) ofrecen accesos en sus sitios web. El País (matricial) tiene la cuenta más antigua y El Salto es el que mayor compromiso muestra con esta red. Discusión: Los medios analizados no aprovechan todo el potencial de la soberanía tecnológica que proporciona Mastodon. Conclusiones: La plantilla usada y los resultados abren vías de investigación sobre una plataforma social (Mastodon) y un ecosistema (Fediverso) apenas explorados en el campo periodístico.”</p>

<p>My rough translation: this paper examines Spanish news organizations’ adooption of Mastodon, particularly after Musk’s purchase of Twitter/X. They find that most Spanish news organizations are present in the form of unofficial automated bots. They also find that “digital native” news organizations are the least likely to have embraced Mastodon. Overall, they find that news organizations are not taking advantage of the possibilities afforded by the fediverse.</p>]]></content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ASM update" /><category term="alternative social media" /><category term="bibliography" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bluesky continues to blow up. I hear about it everywhere. It’s so backed up the Brid.gy system has slowed to a crawl.]]></summary></entry></feed>