<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-17T12:16:33-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on Threads, or Is Mark Zuckerberg Jesus?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/12/16/ThoughtsThreads.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on Threads, or Is Mark Zuckerberg Jesus?" /><published>2023-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/12/16/ThoughtsThreads</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/12/16/ThoughtsThreads.html">&lt;p&gt;(Sorry about the provocative title, but I just had to do it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, a lot of people have thoughts on Threads, which is &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2023/12/14/mastodon-founder-touts-threads-federation-saying-it-makes-his-x-rival-a-far-more-attractive-option/&quot;&gt;actively testing ActivityPub federation&lt;/a&gt;. The reactions range from triumphant proclamations about this making the fediverse more legitimate to abject horror that a company so reviled is attempting to join the fedi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure: I’m more in the latter camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As readers of this blog know, I’m working on a &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html&quot;&gt;book about the fediverse&lt;/a&gt;, and part of my process is to share ideas out in the open. Since any book about the fediverse will have to talk about Threads, I figured this might be a good place to share a rough idea of how a chapter about Threads might go. Comments are welcome, of course!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Away we go…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recapitulation&quot;&gt;Recapitulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a term I heard a few months back, a bit by accident: “recapitulation.”&lt;a href=&quot;#note1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; I’ve been been rolling it around in my mind, like a marble in the palm of the hand. It’s so generative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today, as Meta’s Threads starts the long-awaited (or long-feared) process of federating via ActivityPub, I think I have a way to pick apart what’s going on with this term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, “recapitulation” is a kind of keyword in the sense &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keywords:_A_Vocabulary_of_Culture_and_Society&quot;&gt;Raymond Williams meant&lt;/a&gt;: a term that has multiple, contested meanings, meanings that are bound up with multiple problems. Look it up in the Oxford English Dictionary and you’ll find three ways “recapitulation” helps us pick apart Meta’s Threads and the fediverse:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a Christian theological meaning, where all of human history is recapitulated by Jesus Christ,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a summing up of previous arguments, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a unificiation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at each in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;theological-recapitulation&quot;&gt;Theological recapitulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the Oxford English Dictionary, the theological meaning of “recapitulation” dates back at least to 1629: “the summing up and redemption of all human experience in the life and death of Christ.” In this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pharosjot.com/uploads/7/1/6/3/7163688/article_1_vol_101__2020_.pdf&quot;&gt;theological theory&lt;/a&gt;, Jesus Christ is a second Adam, one who did not sin. In delivering the rest of us from sin, human history from the Fall of Adam to the present is summed up under the name of Christ. Our acceptance of Christ allows for a return to pre-lapsarian life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, what the hell does that have to with Threads?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, let me drop a few quotes from coverage of Threads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kalhan Rosenblatt, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/threads-meta-twitter-rival-app-reaction-nostalgia-chaos-rcna92867&quot;&gt;writing for NBC&lt;/a&gt;: “Threads has been chaotic yet blissful, users said, noting the app reminded them of the early days of the internet — especially since ads have yet to hit the platform.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tamara Palmer, &lt;a href=&quot;https://48hills.org/2023/07/threads-vs-twitter-look-ma-no-nazis-yet/&quot;&gt;writing in 48Hills&lt;/a&gt;: “Threads has a much lighter and nostalgic feel than Twitter at the moment; I even got to, um, Thread with a Vanderpump Rules star last night. (They’re just like us!) It almost feels like 2006 again.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jay Clouse, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creatorscience.com/&quot;&gt;writing in Creator Science&lt;/a&gt;: “For the last several days, I’ve actually published more on Threads than anywhere else. And not because I’m chasing an opportunity – because it was more fun for me!”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kari Paul, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/jul/06/we-tried-threads-metas-new-twitter-rival-heres-what-happened&quot;&gt;writing in the Guardian&lt;/a&gt;: “As a tech writer who has reported extensively on the privacy concerns surrounding Meta, the company’s shameless copying of competitors’ apps, and tech’s growing unchecked power, it pains me to say that I actually enjoyed using Threads.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a clear theme here: nostalgia for a more fun time online. It’s a time before something awful ruined it all. The nostalgic tone becomes even clearer when we consider the context: Threads started not long after Elon Musk purchased Twitter and turned it into a hellscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across much of the coverage of Twitter alternatives (including Bluesky and, to be fair, Mastodon), there’s a sense that the new thing is a return to a better, lost time. For some, it was Twitter before #gamergate. For others – I think journalists fall in this camp – it’s a time when they had authority and were respected. For others, it’s Twitter before Donald Trump. And for everyone, it’s Twitter before Musk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astute readers will see where I’m going with this: Mark Zuckerberg is here to cleanse us of our sins and take us back to the Garden of Microblogging Eden. Or I should put it like this: Meta, a major social media corporation, is swooping in to make microblogging great again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zuckerberg – or maybe Meta – is Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I apologize if those last few sentences made you want to smash your phone or computer against the wall.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Meta federates via ActivityPub, this sort of nostalgia might get amplified. If we could only return to Twitter before the Fall, many people seem to be saying. Who will lead us there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;repetition-of-the-argument&quot;&gt;Repetition of the argument&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s one meaning of recapitulation. But of course, it’s not the only one, and probably not the first one most readers thought of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common meaning is (again, per the OED) “The action or an act of recapitulating (something); a brief restatement or repetition; a summing up; a summary.” This is where we get the term “recap,” a restatement, a summary form of an argument or plot. (It’s also used in music in sonatas, – the repetition of a melody). The verb form is “to go through or repeat again, usually in a more concise manner; to go over the main points or substance of (an argument, statement, etc.); to summarize, restate briefly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to Meta and the fediverse, oh, yeah – there are a lot of repeated arguments happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yZoASOyfvGQ&quot;&gt;Derek Caelin has documented&lt;/a&gt;, the fediverse went through a massive debate when another large entity attempted to federate. That entity was Gab.com, a white Christian nationalist social networking site. Or, if you prefer, a Nazi site, since it does host self-described Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should have been easy to block Gab. However, while the story told about Gab today is that it was defederated quickly, people who lived through that period note how much benefit of the doubt Gab got. The counter-argument against blocking Gab was pretty simple: openness and free speech. That is, rather than preemptively blocking them, this argument goes, we should give them a chance. Ours is an open network. When they say racist stuff, we should counter it with rational, anti-racist arguments. If any of their users are truly bad actors, we will eventually see evidence of it, and then we can block those users. If after a period of time it turns out that the whole domain is a bad actor, then block them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, let them join, see how they act, and then block. That sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a naive view of free speech that critical theorist Herbert Marcuse would call &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marcuse.org/herbert/publications/1960s/1965-repressive-tolerance-fulltext.html&quot;&gt;“repressive tolerance.”&lt;/a&gt; As Marcuse argues, if we tolerate dominant ideas (e.g., white supremacy, transphobia), then we effectively eradicate marginalized ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who argued for preemptively blocking Gab recognized this. Rather than allowing for self-described Nazis to spout hate, the Gab-blockers rejected the free speech and openness argument in favor of supporting marginalized people so &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; could have a chance to speak. Because spaces for the marginalized to speak are rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who called for preemptive blocking were called tyrants, because they would violate the sanctity of openness and free speech. The naive free speech view, while naive, is powerful in its simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to today: we’re recapitulating that debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in June or so, vanta black created &lt;a href=&quot;https://fedipact.online/&quot;&gt;the Fedipact&lt;/a&gt;, asking admins to preemptively block Threads (full disclosure, my instance is on the list). Why? Well, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fedipact.online/why&quot;&gt;I’ll just quote her&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;that time [Meta] helped facilitate a genocide&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;that time they helped try to rig an election&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;that time they did creepy behavioral experimentation on their users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could add more to vanta’s list: Meta platforms hate speech (Libs of Tiktok is often invoked here). Instagram has a destructive influence on teen girls’s sense of worth. Meta attempts to moderate globally on the cheap with underpaid laborers (who get crushed when they try to unionize for their rights).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And none of this is to mention the idea that prompted my whole academic career back in 2008: on Meta properties, we do the free work of declaring what we like, and then Meta sells our attention to advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, blocking Meta’s Threads should be easy, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out, not so much. Fedipact has received a lot of criticism. Other people have summed up (or made) the arguments in favor of not blocking Meta, so I won’t exhaustively recap them, but here are the big ones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will be good for ActivityPub,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will legitimate the fediverse,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will allow fediverse members to increase their follower counts, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;of course: free speech and openness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of all the well-documented, terrible, awful, horrifying things that company has done, &lt;em&gt;we are recapitulating the same conflict we saw with Gab.&lt;/em&gt; Just like Gab, Meta’s Threads is also getting a great deal of benefit of the doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just that this time, there feels like a lot more is at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unification&quot;&gt;Unification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we do about this? Where do we go from here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, let’s look at a third (and admitedly obscure) meaning of “recapitulate”: “to come together into one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, this is the great fear that Meta’s Threads invokes. In my book, I’m arguing that Mastodon and the fediverse are a noncentralized system. Not &lt;em&gt;decentralized,&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;noncentralized&lt;/em&gt;. By that I mean the fediverse is actively resistant to centers. For example, if an instance gets to be too big – Mastodon.social comes to mind – people start openly critiquing it, arguing folks should move accounts from it. So much of the structure of the fediverse, from its open protocols to its FOSS code to its cultural practice, is about noncentralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with Meta in town? The fear is that this massive corporation will absorb the fediverse. It could do so in many ways: taking over the ActivityPub protocol. Drawing many of the most popular accounts away from the rest of the fedi and onto Threads. Overwhelming the fediverse with marketer and influencer content. Swamping the fedi with disinformation, conspiracy theories, and hate speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe the third meaning of “recapitulation” shows us a way out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if the coming together into one, the recapitulation of the fediverse, is to unify – once again – against an unethical actor? I noted that the defederation of Gab wasn’t a simple thing, but it did happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400&quot;&gt;a colleague and I argued&lt;/a&gt; that the emergent, shared ethical core of the fediverse represents a digital covenant. As instances develop their distinct codes of conduct, and as they federate, we see an emergent, shared, global-yet-thin set of deontological rules about content moderation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fediverse in 2023, I would argue, is an even stronger covenantal network than it was in the Gab days. Let’s look at what’s going on: Fedipact. #Fediblock. Communal blocklists. The Mastodon Server Covenant. There is a shared ethical core on the fediverse, and it is possible that this unity-through-federation could be successful in fending off Meta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the third meaning of recapitulation is my favorite. Because it’s not nostalgic or atavistic. It’s not about a sole figure (or a sole corporation) saving us. It’s not a rehash of an argument we endlessly have. It’s about unifying. And the fediverse could do the seemingly impossible: unifying through heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A noncentralized unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;note1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; My digging into the concept of recapitulation happened by accident. One of my interviewees used it to refer to how mainstream culture absorbs alternative practices. As a commenter on the fediverse noted, my interviewee most likely meant to say “recuperation”, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recuperation_(politics)&quot;&gt;term of art from the Situationists&lt;/a&gt;. Based on the context of the interview, I would say this is the case. I’ve edited this post to reflect this to respect the fact that my interviewee probably didn’t intend me to interpret him that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now consider this take on Threads to be the product of a happy accident, since looking at recapitulation led me to the idea of some savior coming to take us back to a lost time. I think the narrative around Threads outside of the fedi has been about nostalgia. I &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; think the narrative about Bluesky has been about nostalgia. Even the discourse about Mastodon in its early days was about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also like the idea of a unification-through-difference that the third meaning implies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I don’t think this post will form the basis of the chapter of the book. Some ideas will travel from it – including some ideas based on the feedback I got on the fedi – but this recapitulation idea is a bit to convoluted to make it into my book, which is intended for a broad audience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Meta" /><category term="Threads" /><category term="digital covenant" /><summary type="html">(Sorry about the provocative title, but I just had to do it.) Today, a lot of people have thoughts on Threads, which is actively testing ActivityPub federation. The reactions range from triumphant proclamations about this making the fediverse more legitimate to abject horror that a company so reviled is attempting to join the fedi. Full disclosure: I’m more in the latter camp. As readers of this blog know, I’m working on a book about the fediverse, and part of my process is to share ideas out in the open. Since any book about the fediverse will have to talk about Threads, I figured this might be a good place to share a rough idea of how a chapter about Threads might go. Comments are welcome, of course! Away we go…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ethics and Codes of Conduct on Mastodon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/22/EthicsAndCOCs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ethics and Codes of Conduct on Mastodon" /><published>2023-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/22/EthicsAndCOCs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/22/EthicsAndCOCs.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I taught one of the final meetings of my undergrad “Ethics and the Media” course at York. We’re using &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/p/books/digital-media-ethics-charles-ess/7513541?ean=9781509533428&quot;&gt;Charle Ess’s &lt;em&gt;Digital Media Ethics&lt;/em&gt; (3rd edition)&lt;/a&gt; as our textbook, and so we’ve had a good guide to ethical theories, such as virtue ethics, deontology, utilitarianism, and feminist ethics of care. (I also supplement Ess with readings and ideas from Shannon Vallor, Kwame Gyekye, Carissa Veliz, Michael Zimmer, and others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the course has been about learning the ethical theories and then discussing &lt;a href=&quot;https://mediaengagement.org/vertical/media-ethics/&quot;&gt;case studies&lt;/a&gt;. It’s been quite an enjoyable course to teach, particularly because I’ve seen the students go from the vague and intellectually unsatisfying statement “Ethics is a subjective, personal thing” to the more robust “Let me lay out how a virtue ethicist would think about this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wanted to have at least one day of the course dedicated to applied ethics. Instead of looking at a case that happened in the past, I wanted the students to apply the ethical theories to a concrete situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these days, we have a great situation in digital media ethics to consider: what to do when we start up a Mastodon server?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I’ll write up what we did in the class, in case anyone out there wants to try something similar.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mastodon-in-the-classroom&quot;&gt;Mastodon in the classroom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spun up a relatively inexpensive Digital Ocean server and installed the latest version of Mastodon. I also imported a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebad.space&quot;&gt;server blocklist&lt;/a&gt;, because I did not want to have the students – all of whom were new to Mastodon – experience some nasty trolling in their first foray. At the same time, I still wanted students to be able to follow accounts outside of our server, so blocking known bad instances made the most sense. I recommend anyone using Mastodon in the classroom do something similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then invited students to join and mess around with our server – post, share, make profiles, etc. I realized that they would see essentially an empty stream and few others – this is all part of the process. I wanted to stress to them that everything on the server is under our control, so we – not some big company – have to decide how active our server would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-a-code-of-conduct&quot;&gt;What about a Code of Conduct?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One step I skipped in setting up was setting server rules and a code of conduct. I did this on purpose: it was the point of the in-class discussion. After providing some background details about Mastodon and the fediverse and answering student questions, we then discussed codes of conduct. For background, I gave them a draft chapter of my &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html&quot;&gt;current book&lt;/a&gt;, which focuses on the history of codes of conduct (and thus draws heavily on an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://where.coraline.codes/&quot;&gt;Coraline Ada Ehmke&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we talked codes of conduct, I talked about how running Mastodon requires us to be active in making choices about content moderation. Running a Mastodon server is a moment of applied ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then asked them to break into four groups:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One group focusing on &lt;strong&gt;feminist ethics of care,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another focusing on &lt;strong&gt;deontology,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another on &lt;strong&gt;virtue ethics,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And the last on &lt;strong&gt;utilitarianism.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked the group to first summarize the ethical theory (not an easy task, I know).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I asked them to apply the ideas from their ethical theory to our potential Mastodon code of conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really, really liked the results!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are summaries of each:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feminist-ethics-of-care&quot;&gt;Feminist ethics of care&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feminist ethics of care (FEOC) rejects the idea (most associated with deontology) that ethical decisions are the sole purview of individual, autonomous rational actors. Instead, FEOC argues we make ethical choices based upon, and informed by, relationships we have with one another. Moreover, an ethical choice is not purely a rational matter, but also involves emotions. Finally, FEOC elevates care of others to the center (but it rejects the idea that only one segment of our society is responsible for care work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this theory, the students argued that our Mastodon server code of conduct should&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Describe how we can network with other servers who share our values.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take inspiration from the first clause of Canadian charter: your rights end where someone else’s begin. You can post so long as you don’t violate others’ rights.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emphasize contextual judgement (considering potential violations in context).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emphasize communication during moderation, using empathy for would-be violators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take: this is a great set of insights. It echoes what I’ve learned over the past few years doing interviews with fediverse admins. Many told me that their approach to moderation is to talk to people and find out what’s going on. They also talk about how they choose to federate/block other instances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deontology&quot;&gt;Deontology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deontology emphasizes individual rights and autonomy, as well as duties to do what is right. Intentions often matter more than consequences. Often deontology is expressed as rules (although that’s a bit reductive.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students in this group did offer rules, likely inspired by reading sample Mastodon codes of conduct:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post nothing illegal!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No discrimination based on age, race, gender, sexuality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No harassment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No trolling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No defamation or coercion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show some respect in the community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take: if there’s one ethical theory that Mastodon seems designed for, it’s deontology. Mastodon’s software prompts the admin to put in “Server Rules,” short statements about expectations would-be members should live up to. Many, many Mastodon codes of conduct have rules similar to the above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;virtue-ethics&quot;&gt;Virtue Ethics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtue ethics is less about intentions or consequences than it is about character. Virtues in a digital environment might include honesty, humility, courage, and compassion, and these are balanced against vicious extremes. Virtue ethics is also relational in that we teach children about virtues and provide advice to them when they have to make ethical choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students in this group suggested that our code of conduct should&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Call for displays of virtous traits, such as wisdom, courage, loyalty,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emphasize being polite and respectful, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have high standards for moderation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take: I was really curious what the students would say in this group, and they delivered some good stuff. What’s useful, I think, is contrasting the negative rules of deontology with these positive virtues and character traits. I could imagine a code of conduct that integrates virtue ethics to emphasize positive behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;utilitarianism&quot;&gt;Utilitarianism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside another consequentialist theory, libertarianism, utilitarianism is probably the most familiar theory to me, since I grew up in the USA. (I’m not saying I endorse either; just that I think I soaked in them). Utilitarianism judges acts based on their consequences: if an act creates the greatest happiness for the greatest number of people, it’s an ethical one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students in this group emphasized the greatest happiness principle in their code of conduct ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let’s promote inclusivity to make people safe, welcome, and heard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to listen to user feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to consider well-being of the community.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Server members should report stuff to the moderators.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should promote free speech but exclude hate speech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take: Students really leaned into thinking about the would-be Mastodon server as a community, and so this approach emphasized group happiness. I think this was a good addition to the other ideas, because social media can be fun and happy – why not build a code of conduct that emphasizes these aspects?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summing-it-all-up&quot;&gt;Summing it all up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We concluded the class by considering how these different approaches to a code of conduct could be synthesized. We kinda ran out of time for that, but I think we may have been able to write a pretty sweet code if we had more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did spend some time talking about enforcement, since no code of conduct is worth anything if you’re not willing to live up to it. I ran various scenarios past them – what if someone outside our server violates our code? What if someone outside our server reports one of our members?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their answers reflected the ideas I’ve heard from seasoned admins, including how admins discuss things with one another and how admins talk to members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think this experiment was really exciting. Unlike corporate social media – Facebook, TikTok, X, etc – &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; get to make decisions about moderation when we run our own instance. It’s a big responsibility, but these students showed they’re up for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="Codes of Conduct" /><summary type="html">Yesterday, I taught one of the final meetings of my undergrad “Ethics and the Media” course at York. We’re using Charle Ess’s Digital Media Ethics (3rd edition) as our textbook, and so we’ve had a good guide to ethical theories, such as virtue ethics, deontology, utilitarianism, and feminist ethics of care. (I also supplement Ess with readings and ideas from Shannon Vallor, Kwame Gyekye, Carissa Veliz, Michael Zimmer, and others). Much of the course has been about learning the ethical theories and then discussing case studies. It’s been quite an enjoyable course to teach, particularly because I’ve seen the students go from the vague and intellectually unsatisfying statement “Ethics is a subjective, personal thing” to the more robust “Let me lay out how a virtue ethicist would think about this.” But I wanted to have at least one day of the course dedicated to applied ethics. Instead of looking at a case that happened in the past, I wanted the students to apply the ethical theories to a concrete situation. And these days, we have a great situation in digital media ethics to consider: what to do when we start up a Mastodon server? In this post, I’ll write up what we did in the class, in case anyone out there wants to try something similar.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Universities Lost the Internet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/10/HowUniversitiesLostIT.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Universities Lost the Internet" /><published>2023-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/10/HowUniversitiesLostIT</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/10/HowUniversitiesLostIT.html">&lt;p&gt;My first full-time academic job was at the University of Utah. Utah is, of course, very famous. No, not because of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanley_Pons&quot;&gt;cold fusion&lt;/a&gt; or teaching Ted Bundy about the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is famous because it was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://it.utah.edu/node4/posts/2017/august/node4-history.php&quot;&gt;fourth node on the ARPAnet&lt;/a&gt;, the forerunner to the modern internet. The other three nodes were in California; connecting to Utah was a major test of the network’s ability to work across long distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it was a US Defense Department-funded project, the ARPAnet was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/5432117&quot;&gt;playground for academics&lt;/a&gt; who took its mission (command-and-control even in spite of a nuclear attack) and turned it into research into networking and collaboration. The pattern continued: academic exploration of computer technologies has produced a bewildering array of experiments, and no doubt students at institutions have benefited greatly from being able to play with local, experimental computer tools while they study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the early 2010s. I’m working at Utah, hired in part to teach a Web design class to Communication majors. Simple enough: each and every person affiliated with Utah had their own domain (something like domain.utah.edu/~username) on a local server, complete with FTP access via their email credentials. I taught students the basics of HTML and CSS. I got to see students who were openly scared of coding make things that appeared on their screens – and on the internet. It was fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until it was not. I was at Utah from 2010 to 2020. Over that time, it became harder and harder to get students into their web space. It turns out that Utah was winding down web hosting for everyone, centralizing its web presence and no longer providing web space to anyone. To support our class, the IT folks helpfully carved out some space on a server, specifically for our Comm Intro to the Web Design students, but we knew this was an exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of my time there, even the machines in the computer lab were outsourced. Instead of fully-functional desktops, students were accessing their servers over a convoluted “thin client” computer lab setup. I had to spend the first 2 weeks just showing them how to find their files – since they were no longer local – and then FTP into a server to move those files over a client-to-cloud-to-FTP setup. This was for students who had no networking or web design experience – it was &lt;em&gt;rough&lt;/em&gt;. (And if we needed software – such as basic text editor – good luck getting it when all the software was on a cloud somewhere).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sorry to say I spent a great deal of that time in an increasingly adversarial relationship with the IT folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this happened, my colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://seanlawson.net&quot;&gt;Sean Lawson&lt;/a&gt; and I would vent our frustration by jokingly saying, “Welcome to Node 4!” The irony being that Utah was once &lt;em&gt;25% of the freakin’ Internet&lt;/em&gt; but we could not get easy access to basic Web hosting. It was an ordeal just to get students to the point where they could move a text file they were working on to a server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to today. Now, I am happily employed by York University in Toronto. But just the other day, my colleagues met for a faculty meeting, and we discussed recruiting students. Someone suggested we post information about our faculty to our department website and social media. “No,” the chair said. “All of that would have to go through the central administration” – the implication being either it wouldn’t be allowed, or that it would take months to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;someones-gotta-write-this-book&quot;&gt;Someone’s Gotta Write This Book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would propose, were I to have time, to write a book called “How Universities Lost the Internet.” How did we get from many nodes to everything being dumped into California or Redmond, WA? How did we get from a system of experimentation to seeing digital media as a controlled environment to market a brand? How did we get to the point where university core functions were run by for-profit firms?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be a fascinating book. (Someone else can write it, though; I’m too busy with &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html&quot;&gt;my current project&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s quite a readership for this book, judging from a recent thread on the fediverse. I posted this &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social/@rwg/111308895829845440&quot;&gt;proposed book idea on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt; a few days back:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Does this book exist? “How Universities Lost the Internet”?
Or has someone done research on this topic? That is, the fact that many North American universities have ceded all technical capacity to Microsoft, Google, etc?
It used to be students could get web hosting, email, and even some cool experimental online stuff through their schools. Now every online communication channel is locked down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The response to my fediverse post was pretty intense. I’m not going to directly quote any of it here because I did not ask permission of the respondents (and of course you can see public comments if you follow the above link), but I will sum things up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University IT is being outsourced across the board. Instead of local email, storage, or HR systems, these services are subdomains of a corporate site, e.g., https://yorku.zoom.us/, or even just simply note affiliated with the university at all (e.g., when I login to York webmail, the domain is office.com and there is no York branding).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a global phenomenon. I originally mentioned North America because that’s the context I know, but folks from universities the world around have observed the same thing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For universities outside the USA, the outsourcing is doubled: they’re not only outsourcing things from the university to outside third parties, they’re outsourcing to companies outside the country.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The reasons given for this shift vary. In some places, faculty and students are told this is done for security purposes. In others, they are told it’s done for cost-cutting reasons. And in others, they’re told it’s done to protect the university’s brand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Timelines also vary. The pandemic sped things up, but such outsourcing has been going on for a while. Some note it began at their institutions as early as the 1990s.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are some bright spots: university-hosted Git repositories and local file storage are mentioned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I didn’t hear that the book on this shift exists, people helpfully pointed out &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.09462&quot;&gt;this article on the “Zoomification” of higher education&lt;/a&gt;. Poking around, I also found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/opinion/blogs/learning-innovation/2023/09/01/recoding-america-and-perils-outsourcing-it&quot;&gt;book review essay&lt;/a&gt; lamenting this process, a report in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/education/colleges-outsourcing-services/2021/01/07/c3f2ac6a-5135-11eb-bda4-615aaefd0555_story.html&quot;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2023/mar/07/australian-university-outsourcing-how-can-i-tell-if-my-online-course-is-being-run-by-a-third-party&quot;&gt;Guardian Australia investigation into outsourcing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic is definitely getting attention. Someone outta write a book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-care-about-this&quot;&gt;Why I Care About This&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers of this blog know I care about communication infrastructure pretty deeply. Goal 1 of my blog is to &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/11/27/introduction.html&quot;&gt;document the life of the “FOSS Academic”&lt;/a&gt; – my attempt to do most or all of my professorial work using FOSS tools and self-hosting. I use Nextcloud for document sharing, collaboration, and conferencing, Zotero for managing bibliographies, Thunderbird for managing emails and calendars, Libreoffice for writing. I use Syncthing, Wireguard, and Nextcloud on a local network to move data from home to office. Of course, all of this is running on Linux machines (Manjaro KDE, if you’re curious).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, this has worked, but I am sorry to say it’s increasingly hard. Zoom is a big culprit, of course, but I’ve accepted that. (I use &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/2021/09/25/Appointments.html&quot;&gt;Nextcloud Appointments and Talk pretty often&lt;/a&gt;, however).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I didn’t bargain for was how powerful Microsoft has become. Outlook, Teams, Sharepoint, Office. The assumption among my colleagues is that I use all of these regularly. I get why they think that – it’s what’s provided. But I’m starting to get pressure to put my calendar on Outlook, since people assume that if my Outlook calendar is open, I can meet. Whenever my colleagues want to work on documents, it’s in Office online, not a draft passed back and forth. And all of my department’s governance runs through Teams (a program so awfully designed it wastes time – I can hardly find anything in it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to hold onto my FOSS, self-hosted network as a living experiment – maybe if I can hold the line, chip away at things, convert a colleague or two to the “FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream” – maybe we can find an alternative to this mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But given that university IT outsourcing is a global phenomenon, I’m starting to lose hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lost-creativity&quot;&gt;Lost Creativity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest reason I’m concerned, however, is not just about my day-to-day work, but because of the loss of skills and experiments such outsourcing causes. This is the point of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/opinion/blogs/learning-innovation/2023/09/01/recoding-america-and-perils-outsourcing-it&quot;&gt;book review essay I cited above&lt;/a&gt;, in which Joshua Kim uses a book about US government IT outsourcing to lament the loss of IT skills in universities, as well as the reduction of University IT to mere “support services.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I would like to see is universities providing infrastructure for students and faculty to do interesting, creative things. I’d like to see this done for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; students and faculty, not just sequestered in computer science or engineering departments. I’d like to see folks be able to do everything from making websites to local document collaboration to running their own social media. On this latter point, there are efforts, notably in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.surf.nl/en/mastodon-pilot-for-research-and-education&quot;&gt;Holland&lt;/a&gt; and at &lt;a href=&quot;https://mastodon.mit.edu/about&quot;&gt;MIT&lt;/a&gt;. But I worry that these are exceptions, not the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than that, I would like to see universities run their own IT again, seeing it as central to the pedagogical mission, not just another budget line to cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;did-you-write-this-book&quot;&gt;Did you write this book?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to repeat my question above: did someone write this book and I just missed it? Hey, let me know: I’m buying!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">My first full-time academic job was at the University of Utah. Utah is, of course, very famous. No, not because of cold fusion or teaching Ted Bundy about the law. It is famous because it was the fourth node on the ARPAnet, the forerunner to the modern internet. The other three nodes were in California; connecting to Utah was a major test of the network’s ability to work across long distances. Although it was a US Defense Department-funded project, the ARPAnet was a playground for academics who took its mission (command-and-control even in spite of a nuclear attack) and turned it into research into networking and collaboration. The pattern continued: academic exploration of computer technologies has produced a bewildering array of experiments, and no doubt students at institutions have benefited greatly from being able to play with local, experimental computer tools while they study. Fast forward to the early 2010s. I’m working at Utah, hired in part to teach a Web design class to Communication majors. Simple enough: each and every person affiliated with Utah had their own domain (something like domain.utah.edu/~username) on a local server, complete with FTP access via their email credentials. I taught students the basics of HTML and CSS. I got to see students who were openly scared of coding make things that appeared on their screens – and on the internet. It was fun! Until it was not. I was at Utah from 2010 to 2020. Over that time, it became harder and harder to get students into their web space. It turns out that Utah was winding down web hosting for everyone, centralizing its web presence and no longer providing web space to anyone. To support our class, the IT folks helpfully carved out some space on a server, specifically for our Comm Intro to the Web Design students, but we knew this was an exception. At the end of my time there, even the machines in the computer lab were outsourced. Instead of fully-functional desktops, students were accessing their servers over a convoluted “thin client” computer lab setup. I had to spend the first 2 weeks just showing them how to find their files – since they were no longer local – and then FTP into a server to move those files over a client-to-cloud-to-FTP setup. This was for students who had no networking or web design experience – it was rough. (And if we needed software – such as basic text editor – good luck getting it when all the software was on a cloud somewhere). I’m sorry to say I spent a great deal of that time in an increasingly adversarial relationship with the IT folks. As this happened, my colleague Sean Lawson and I would vent our frustration by jokingly saying, “Welcome to Node 4!” The irony being that Utah was once 25% of the freakin’ Internet but we could not get easy access to basic Web hosting. It was an ordeal just to get students to the point where they could move a text file they were working on to a server. Fast forward to today. Now, I am happily employed by York University in Toronto. But just the other day, my colleagues met for a faculty meeting, and we discussed recruiting students. Someone suggested we post information about our faculty to our department website and social media. “No,” the chair said. “All of that would have to go through the central administration” – the implication being either it wouldn’t be allowed, or that it would take months to achieve. Someone’s Gotta Write This Book I would propose, were I to have time, to write a book called “How Universities Lost the Internet.” How did we get from many nodes to everything being dumped into California or Redmond, WA? How did we get from a system of experimentation to seeing digital media as a controlled environment to market a brand? How did we get to the point where university core functions were run by for-profit firms? It would be a fascinating book. (Someone else can write it, though; I’m too busy with my current project!)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Alternative Social Media Preconference at AoIR</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/10/19/AoIR_ASM_preconfernce.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alternative Social Media Preconference at AoIR" /><published>2023-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/10/19/AoIR_ASM_preconfernce</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/10/19/AoIR_ASM_preconfernce.html">&lt;p&gt;On October 18, at 8.30 am, a group of about 30 Internet Scholars gathered for a Association of Internet Researchers preconference, called “Building an Alternative Social Media Network.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organized by Jessa Lingel, Ashwin Nagappi, and myself, the preconference achieved one of its big goals: getting many researchers in a room to talk about alternative social media (ASM). Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other big goal was igniting a research agenda for ASM. Did we succeed?
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;asm-research-futures&quot;&gt;ASM Research futures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would say: “yes!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion during our roughly four hours was rich. First of all, Ashwin had the brilliant idea of building an ad-hoc timeline of social media, dating back to the 1970s through today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/smwall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A wall of post-it notes that creates a timeline of social media, starting with email in the 1970s through the fediverse today&quot; title=&quot;social media timeline&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The participants in the preconference remembered various social media, broadly construed, and posted notes about them to the wall.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This actually helped us see the variety of ways people were defining “social media” right away. It also showed us that there may have been bursts of activity in two key moments: the early 2010s (quite understandable) and right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-asm&quot;&gt;What are ASM?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This segued into a discussion about a key question: what are “alternative social media”? From my corner of the room, I heard two key words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;relational&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emergent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, ASM are always in relation to something typically considered mainstream. This actually replicates a paper Roel Roscam Abbing and I are working on, where we will conclude with a similar observation. ASM are in relation to a mainstream, a relation that can change over time. RRA and I presented an early &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextcloud.robertwgehl.org/index.php/s/qkZBjbznzkjTbkT&quot;&gt;version of that paper back in May of this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other key word was “emergent,” in that alternative &lt;em&gt;practices&lt;/em&gt; often appear across many locations, including on mainstream corporate social media. These practices can influence both corporate &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; alternative social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even with this relative consensus, much as the conception of social media was very broad, so, too the conception of alternative social media. Some of us felt that this would hinder the field, replicating the worst of the alternative media debates of the 1990s-2000s. Others of us felt that the variety of meanings could aid in research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methods-and-ethics&quot;&gt;Methods and Ethics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We next turned to ASM research methods – which were immediately tied to research ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, since ASM is hard to define, then it struck many of us that ethnographic or participatory methods are called for. We agreed that often we have to listen to communities as they define themselves as “alternative.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we also noted that we should be free to reject a community’s self-definition as “alternative” – it could be mere marketing. Or it could be a self-serving gloss on unethical replication of mainstream practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historical methods were also recommended, since tracing alternative practices (such as, for example, federated political practices) could shed light on contemporary social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also discussed approaches like the walk-through method or software studies approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there was controversy, it was over data-scraping methods. Readers of this blog know I am adverse to them on the fediverse (and I am working on a paper on this topic). However, participants argued that scraping may be warranted in situations where we study the alt-right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethics was, as it should be, a central consideration. The participants tended to agree with the basic idea of consent – a position I &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/06/25/ASMupdate-Warwick.html&quot;&gt;wholly endorse for the study of the fediverse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sticky bit, again, was in cases where researchers felt that consent would be hard to get, or interfere with the study: again, this tended to focus on studying right-wing alternative social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me (and many of the folks in the room, I believe), there’s a major upshot to ethical engagement with many ASM groups: we researchers can make a difference! We can do work that resonates with ASM communities: we can ask them what they need and how we could help provide it through research. I really don’t think Facebook or Twitter cares a bit about critical social media research… but people on the fediverse, for example, might. If we do this right, we can actually help grow a more ethical social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m down for that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-steps&quot;&gt;Future steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are now building an email listserv for researchers interested in the field of ASM, as well as a Zotero library. I particularly hope that collecting a bibliography might shed light on the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also talking about meeting again, either virtually or in person. Watch this space for more!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="alternative social media" /><category term="Association of Internet Researchers" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">On October 18, at 8.30 am, a group of about 30 Internet Scholars gathered for a Association of Internet Researchers preconference, called “Building an Alternative Social Media Network.” Organized by Jessa Lingel, Ashwin Nagappi, and myself, the preconference achieved one of its big goals: getting many researchers in a room to talk about alternative social media (ASM). Yay! The other big goal was igniting a research agenda for ASM. Did we succeed?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ActivityPub, the Non-Standard Standard</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/10/15/APnonStandard.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ActivityPub, the Non-Standard Standard" /><published>2023-10-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/10/15/APnonStandard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/10/15/APnonStandard.html">&lt;p&gt;In a couple days, I head to Philadelphia for the 2023 version of the Association of Internet Researchers conference. It’s my favorite conference. And to give AOIR even more credit, they were one of the first professional academic organizations to set up &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social&quot;&gt;their own Mastodon instance&lt;/a&gt; (I participate in that project by helping run the instance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there, I will present a paper about the creation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/&quot;&gt;ActivityPub&lt;/a&gt;, the protocol that allows the contemporary fediverse to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titled “The Non-Standard Standard: A Critical Genealogy of ActivityPub,” I will argue that ActivityPub is a very unusual standard. While it was created by a W3C working group, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg&quot;&gt;the Social Web Working Group&lt;/a&gt; during &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2023/Process-20230612/&quot;&gt;a W3C standard process&lt;/a&gt;, there were many non-standard aspects to its creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I’ll sum up my findings, arguing that there are four ways in which ActivityPub is a non-standard standard. This work is informed by reading the Social Web Working Group (SocialWG) meeting minutes, interviews with SocialWG members, and a study of historical documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments are very welcome, since this is going to be a chapter in my forthcoming book about the fediverse, &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Move Slowly and Build Bridges&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;four-non-standard-aspects-of-the-activitypub-standard&quot;&gt;Four Non-Standard Aspects of the ActivityPub standard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-corporate-social-media-was-not-involved&quot;&gt;1) Corporate social media was not involved&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporate social media wasn’t involved in the production of ActivityPub. At best, corporations like Facebook or Twitter (as they were known at the time) treated the SocialWG with benign neglect. At worst, they saw the group as utterly irrelevant to the future of social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t as if the SocialWG didn’t try to get corporate social media involved: they repeatedly reached out to Facebook, Twitter, Sina Weibo, and other major social media corporations. But none of these companies got involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very unusual in the world of internet standards. Companies such as IBM, Microsoft, Apple, Google, Meta, Oracle, or Samsung pay membership fees and regularly send employees to standards-setting bodies, such as the Internet Engineering Task Force and the World Wide Web Consortium, in order to shape the standards that govern their industries. In fact, as much as corporations like Apple, Microsoft, and Google appear to be competing with one another, in reality they often cooperate when building standards, because the general rule is that standardized technologies are good for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when it came to the SocialWG, as ActivityPub co-author Amy Guy told me, “None of the big players… no one took us seriously. No one saw [the SocialWG] as a threat. No one expected it to go anywhere…. The feeling was, it was small beans, and it wasn’t worth their time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-the-social-web-working-group-didnt-make-a-standard--they-made-seven&quot;&gt;2) The Social Web Working Group Didn’t Make a Standard – They Made &lt;em&gt;Seven&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of settling on one approach to standardizing social media – in other words, a single, standard approach – the group made &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/groups/wg/social/publications/&quot;&gt;seven standards&lt;/a&gt;. For a typical W3C working group, that is decidedly non-standard behavior – most groups make one or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on interviews, it’s clear this happened because of a lack of corporate involvement. Say what we will about corporate social media, they at least have a clear goal in mind: more users. More people’s lives to datamine, more eyeballs on behavioral ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the SocialWG members took a predominantly academic or theoretical approach, which initially resulted in multiple factions each championing their own approaches. The group easily could have produced zero standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in a compromise, the SocialWG decided to produce many standards. In a sense, as SocialWG member Bengo told me, the group succeeded &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt; – it made many standards, instead of just one or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this said, while lack of corporate involvement might have unmoored the group somewhat, the interviewees I spoke to said they were grateful to make standards that did not simply support the needs of corporate social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-activitypub-almost-didnt-happen&quot;&gt;3) ActivityPub Almost Didn’t Happen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the biggee. ActivityPub – the most successful product of the SocialWG by far – almost didn’t get done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big reason was that a federation protocol was considered to be optional by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2013/socialweb/social-wg-charter.html&quot;&gt;SocialWG’s charter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But an even bigger hurdle came in the face of resistance to ActivityPub from within the SocialWG itself. As an example of the pushback, consider this Mean Girls meme:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fetchfederation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mean Girls &amp;quot;Stop Trying to Make Federation Happen&amp;quot; meme&quot; title=&quot;Stop Trying to Make Federation Happen&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A variation on the Mean Girls &quot;stop trying to make fetch happen,&quot; adapted to refer to the federation protocol&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for us, ActivityPub advocates such as eventual co-author &lt;a href=&quot;https://dustycloud.org/&quot;&gt;Christine Lemmer-Webber&lt;/a&gt; weren’t taking no for an answer. Lemmer-Webber pushed back hard against the resistance to ActivityPub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even with Lemmer-Webber championing it, time was running out: the SocialWG charter set the end of the group to be mid-2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took Mastodon to save ActivityPub. &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackernoon.com/mastodon-and-the-w3c-f75f376f422&quot;&gt;Mastodon implemented a draft version of ActivityPub&lt;/a&gt;, and because this was a big deal, the W3C gave the SocialWG &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; deadline extensions, now known as the “Mastodon Extension.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastodon and ActivityPub connected because of their respective developers’ desire for safety for queer and trans people. Just as “the fediverse has historically been extremely queer,” &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossandcrafts.org/episodes/053-fediverse-reflections-while-the-bird-burns.html&quot;&gt;Christine Lemmer-Webber explains that ActivityPub was, as well&lt;/a&gt;. Lemmer-Webber says ActivityPub “was largely developed by queer people – myself included – and including also implementation developers.” Four of the five ActivityPub authors self-identified as queer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for Mastodon, Lemmer-Webber recalls that a large number of its “key contributors, kind of set the tone by pushing for certain features and pushing for kind of certain cultural norms that were to support queer communities that did not feel well-supported by Twitter.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, ActivityPub solved many problems for Mastodon – it functioned as a privacy-respecting upgrade over &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OStatus&quot;&gt;OStatus&lt;/a&gt; (the original protocol used by Mastodon), a means to break away from harassment coming from some &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@Trevatos/gnu-social-pleroma-and-the-mastodon-culture-conflict-3b10872937c2&quot;&gt;GNU social servers&lt;/a&gt;, and a way to further differentiate itself from Twitter. And Mastodon helped ActivityPub by giving its authors a big implementation – gold in the world of standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-mastodon-prompted-us-to-ignore-12-of-activitypub&quot;&gt;4) Mastodon Prompted Us to Ignore 1/2 of ActivityPub&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while Mastodon saved ActivityPub from oblivion, it has also effectively erased half of the ActivityPub standard from the internet. This is because the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.joinmastodon.org/api/&quot;&gt;Mastodon API&lt;/a&gt; is dominant across the fediverse, with non-Mastodon projects adopting it. This is in spite of the fact that the ActivityPub protocol includes an API for clients, which would allow end clients to connect to any fediverse server regardless of what software the server is running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This client-to-server portion of ActivityPub is cited by SocialWG members as their favorite part of the standard. But it is effectively ignored. So while ActivityPub’s creators are grateful to Mastodon for saving their work, Mastodon is also a cause for lament on the part of the ActivityPub authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications-for-the-future&quot;&gt;Implications for the Future?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I found the story of ActivityPub, the non-standard standard, to be fascinating. Obviously, it’s also important to the history of Mastodon. As Evan Prodromou told me in an interview, the meeting of Mastodon and ActivityPub at just the right moment in both their development “has changed history. It could be a very different story now. A different story for Mastodon and a different story for the social web.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wonder how this story will affect the future, as well. People are currently reviving the SocialWG, with debates happening right now about what its scope should be. Given the history I’ve observed, I would argue that concentrating on the SocialWG’s most successful product, ActivityPub, may be the wisest move.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="ActivityPub" /><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Move Slowly and Build Bridges" /><summary type="html">In a couple days, I head to Philadelphia for the 2023 version of the Association of Internet Researchers conference. It’s my favorite conference. And to give AOIR even more credit, they were one of the first professional academic organizations to set up their own Mastodon instance (I participate in that project by helping run the instance). While there, I will present a paper about the creation of ActivityPub, the protocol that allows the contemporary fediverse to run. Titled “The Non-Standard Standard: A Critical Genealogy of ActivityPub,” I will argue that ActivityPub is a very unusual standard. While it was created by a W3C working group, the Social Web Working Group during a W3C standard process, there were many non-standard aspects to its creation. In this post, I’ll sum up my findings, arguing that there are four ways in which ActivityPub is a non-standard standard. This work is informed by reading the Social Web Working Group (SocialWG) meeting minutes, interviews with SocialWG members, and a study of historical documents. Comments are very welcome, since this is going to be a chapter in my forthcoming book about the fediverse, Move Slowly and Build Bridges.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A defense of the humble, importable blocklist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/09/20/blocklists.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A defense of the humble, importable blocklist" /><published>2023-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/09/20/blocklists</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/09/20/blocklists.html">&lt;p&gt;So I tried to take part in Fediforum today, but I wasn’t really able to participate. My initial idea was to get into a debate with my friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://test.roelof.info/&quot;&gt;Roel Roscam Abbing&lt;/a&gt;, who is an incredibly deep thinker and is writing what will no doubt be a foundational dissertation about the fediverse. We were hoping to prompt a discussion about importable, instance blocklists on the fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He and I disagree their utility. He thinks they’re bad; I think they’re good. I’ll let him post his reasons why, but here I wanted to share my defense of them. What follows is a longer version of what I planned on presenting at Fediforum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, when people discuss ways to improve the fediverse, they talk about technical solutions – extensions to ActivityPub, say, or new layers on the network. Instead, my take is informed by my research for &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html&quot;&gt;my forthcoming book&lt;/a&gt;, where I explore the history, politics, and cultural practices of the fediverse. To defend blocklists, I draw on this history, politics, and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most powerful things that has emerged on the fediverse is the culture of Codes of Conduct. The fediverse would be a very different –- and worse –- place without this practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of using codes of conduct was not a technical achievement. It has little to do with ActivityPub. Instead, it came as part of the zeitgeist –- COCs were being &lt;a href=&quot;https://modelviewculture.com/pieces/codes-of-conduct-when-being-excellent-is-not-enough&quot;&gt;advocated for in tech circles in the mid-2010s&lt;/a&gt;, and of course Mastodon was developed right at the same time. Mastodon.social and others adopted COCs, and the pattern was set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, research shows that there are many overlaps across fediverse codes of conduct, such that we see what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iris_Marion_Young&quot;&gt;ethical theorists&lt;/a&gt; might call a thin set of shared global values. A colleague and I argue elsewhere that this practice gives rise to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400&quot;&gt;“covenantal fediverse,”&lt;/a&gt; where like-minded instances band together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another social innovation is the emergence of the instance as the fundamental unit of the fediverse. I know that there was a desire by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2013/socialweb/social-wg-charter.html&quot;&gt;authors of ActivityPub to have a client-to-server structure&lt;/a&gt;, but we ended up with instances as the key site of organization. This is a happy accident. Instances admins can gain knowledge about how the network works, where the good and bad actors are, and they can protect members –- especially new members who are just joining the network. For better or worse –-and I think it’s for better –- we think at the community/instance level, with admins as leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to blocklists. With the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/releases/tag/v4.1.0&quot;&gt;implementation of blocklist importing in Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;, we’re seeing a logical next step –- not just the sharing of codes of conduct, but cross-instance, inter-admin sharing of knowledge about what Ro aptly calls &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebad.space/&quot;&gt;“the bad space”&lt;/a&gt; of the fediverse. This is a recognition –- and blocking –- of the swath of the internet that fails to meet the thin set of global ethical values. Contemporary blocklists are a codification of early social practices, like #fediblock and backchanneling between covenantally-linked instances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextcloud.robertwgehl.org/index.php/s/G34Y5X2PoNBq5Xp&quot;&gt;noted elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve benefited from this history. When I set up AOIR.social in March, I was aided by imported blocklists. There is a great deal of knowledge on the fediverse about the patterns of “free speech absolutism” (read: racist, misogynist, transmisic, or CSAM-sharing). Free speech absolutism has a long history in free software social media. But because people have recognized the freezepeach pattern – indeed, because they’ve suffered from it – they have codifed their knowledge in blocklist form. Installing a blocklist on day one allowed AoIR.social to benefit from this painfully-gained knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are counterarguments, of course. The danger of a blocklist is that it is tied to personalities –- many people cite the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@obvious_humor/dont-use-randi-harper-s-blocklist-use-naziblocker-instead-db16cd666d49&quot;&gt;Randi Harper case&lt;/a&gt;. Others suggest that blocklists are too tied to centralized, corporate social media. But I think we run the risk of the genetic fallacy by assuming previous, harmful Twitter activities will necessarily be replicated on the fedi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countering the danger of the blocklist run by a single person, we’re seeing nascent governance structures around blocklists, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://nivenly.org/docs/papers/fsep/&quot;&gt;Ro’s The Bad Space collaboration with Nivenly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this brings me to my main point. Much the same as we’ve had an emergent set of ethical principles arise through the cultural practice of COCs, organized at the instance level, shared instance blocklists –- with governance structures that cross instances –- could result in another cultural innovation: affirmative, cross-instance governance. The blocklist becomes a vehicle for such collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won’t be easy, by any means. In fact, it is really hard (just ask the people helping to build the lists). But so was developing codes of conduct. And so too is running an instance. It’s all social practice. It’s all hard. Building a new way of being social is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re gaining skills, day by day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="moderation" /><category term="goal 2" /><summary type="html">So I tried to take part in Fediforum today, but I wasn’t really able to participate. My initial idea was to get into a debate with my friend Roel Roscam Abbing, who is an incredibly deep thinker and is writing what will no doubt be a foundational dissertation about the fediverse. We were hoping to prompt a discussion about importable, instance blocklists on the fediverse. He and I disagree their utility. He thinks they’re bad; I think they’re good. I’ll let him post his reasons why, but here I wanted to share my defense of them. What follows is a longer version of what I planned on presenting at Fediforum.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM update, Bibliography Edition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/09/08/ASMupdateBib.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM update, Bibliography Edition" /><published>2023-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/09/08/ASMupdateBib</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/09/08/ASMupdateBib.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a minor update, but I hope it’s useful to anyone interested in doing alternative social media research. I’ve long hosted a Zotero group, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/groups/542752/social_media_alternatives_project_bibliography&quot;&gt;Social Media Alternatives Project&lt;/a&gt;, which has a library. As much as I love Zotero, though, I’ve not had much luck with groups for fostering public discussion. Their libraries are a bit too tucked away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since many people are requesting resources about ASM, and that Zotero library may not be the easiest thing to find, I’m going to regularly port that library to a &lt;a href=&quot;../bib.html&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/a&gt; page on this blog. I’ve got to do some cleaning up, but there’s some good stuff in there. As Steve Brule might say: check it out!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html">This is a minor update, but I hope it’s useful to anyone interested in doing alternative social media research. I’ve long hosted a Zotero group, the Social Media Alternatives Project, which has a library. As much as I love Zotero, though, I’ve not had much luck with groups for fostering public discussion. Their libraries are a bit too tucked away. Since many people are requesting resources about ASM, and that Zotero library may not be the easiest thing to find, I’m going to regularly port that library to a Bibliography page on this blog. I’ve got to do some cleaning up, but there’s some good stuff in there. As Steve Brule might say: check it out!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Move Slowly and Build Bridges to be published by Oxford University Press</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Move Slowly and Build Bridges to be published by Oxford University Press" /><published>2023-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/08/17/OxfordUP</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/17/OxfordUP.html">&lt;p&gt;I am very excited to announce that my next book, &lt;em&gt;Move Slowly and Building Bridges: Mastodon, the Fediverse, and the Struggle for Democratic Social Media&lt;/em&gt; will be published by Oxford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, I sent a proposal (a short synopsis of the book, audience considerations, and two sample chapters) to Oxford. They moved &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;. They recruited two peer reviewers who turned around reviews very quickly, and then Oxford’s editorial board reviewed the project. I just received a contract based on these reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word I got from Oxford is that they are excited about the project – and about the fediverse. That’s really good news, because the normal advice an author would get is to promote one’s work on corporate social media. But I think that any book about the fediverse has to be talked about on the fediverse. Maybe this project can help other academic authors break away from Twitter/X and Facebook/Meta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, fediverse, watch for &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social/@rwg&quot;&gt;posts about this book from me on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;. I’m also committing to sharing details about the book here on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-im-writing-about&quot;&gt;What I’m writing about&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about the book, I’d first point you to &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/01/06/Goal2.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, which is the earliest description of this project. Things have evolved somewhat since that post, but for now, that post from early 2022 gives you some insight into what I’m writing about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have a series of posts I’m writing about the creation of ActivityPub – you can see &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/01/20/ActivityPub1.html&quot;&gt;part 1 here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/05/09/ActivityPub2.html&quot;&gt;part 2 here&lt;/a&gt;. Watch for more of these, since one chapter will focus on the creation of ActivityPub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, watch out for &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/tags/asm%20update.html&quot;&gt;“Alternative Social Media Updates”&lt;/a&gt; – those posts discuss news items that are relevant to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also have some co-authored journal articles on &lt;a href=&quot;https://robertwgehl.org/text/pubs/Zulli%20et%20al.%20-%202020%20-%20Rethinking%20the%20%e2%80%9csocial%e2%80%9d%20in%20%e2%80%9csocial%20media%e2%80%9d%20Insight.pdf&quot;&gt;rethinking social media&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2022.2147400&quot;&gt;codes of conduct&lt;/a&gt; that also give you some insight into the project. I do have a chapter focusing on codes of conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also plan on writing about specific chapters openly on this blog. Watch for such posts in the coming months. As an example of what that will look like, &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/02/10/bumpAndSlump.html&quot;&gt;this post on the “killer hype cycle”&lt;/a&gt; is now part of chapter 1 of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-im-writing-it&quot;&gt;How I’m writing it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have written about how I’m doing the research. I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html&quot;&gt;talked about my use of interviews here&lt;/a&gt; – that process is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/05/26/Subscribe.html&quot;&gt;wrote about my approach to using subscriptions&lt;/a&gt; as a way to support artists and creative folks on the fediverse – that is still ongoing, and will be relevant to a chapter on creativity on the fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have my &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/tags/goal%201.html&quot;&gt;“Goal 1” series of posts&lt;/a&gt; about using FOSS tools to write – I will continue to write about using Zotero, Zettlr, Nextcloud and other tools to write this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the next 12 months will be hectic, but I’m very gratified to have a publisher lined up for this book. This work has been a focus of mine for many years. I’ve met some incredible, smart, insightful people on the fediverse – I hope this book, and this process, will be up to their standards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">I am very excited to announce that my next book, Move Slowly and Building Bridges: Mastodon, the Fediverse, and the Struggle for Democratic Social Media will be published by Oxford University Press. Earlier this year, I sent a proposal (a short synopsis of the book, audience considerations, and two sample chapters) to Oxford. They moved fast. They recruited two peer reviewers who turned around reviews very quickly, and then Oxford’s editorial board reviewed the project. I just received a contract based on these reviews. The word I got from Oxford is that they are excited about the project – and about the fediverse. That’s really good news, because the normal advice an author would get is to promote one’s work on corporate social media. But I think that any book about the fediverse has to be talked about on the fediverse. Maybe this project can help other academic authors break away from Twitter/X and Facebook/Meta. So, fediverse, watch for posts about this book from me on Mastodon. I’m also committing to sharing details about the book here on this blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ASM update, August 12 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/12/ASMupdateFSEP.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ASM update, August 12 2023" /><published>2023-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/08/12/ASMupdateFSEP</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/12/ASMupdateFSEP.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while, thanks to drama with rent and apartments (welcome to Toronto, Robert), but I’m back with another Alternative Social Media update!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-challenges-in-moderation-and-new-responses&quot;&gt;New challenges in moderation and new responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Content warning: abuse mention&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine most readers of this blog saw news about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cyber.fsi.stanford.edu/io/news/addressing-child-exploitation-federated-social-media&quot;&gt;Stanford Internet Observatory report&lt;/a&gt; on child sexual abuse material (CSAM) on the fediverse. I know I did. I’m currently the admin of &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social/&quot;&gt;AoIR.social&lt;/a&gt;, and the report came out while I was in the middle of moving apartments – and in the middle of relying on dodgy mobile hotspot internet. Regardless of the bad connection and stress of unpacking, the report’s publication prompted me to immediately do an audit of AoIR.social’s instance blocklist to see if we were facing any risk of having CSAM hit our server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am quite confident AoIR.social is in good shape. Why? Because on day one of AoIR.social (months before the Stanford report), I imported blocklists. First, I grabbed &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeberg.org/oliphant/blocklists&quot;&gt;Oliphant’s Tier 0 Blocklist&lt;/a&gt;, and later &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebad.space/&quot;&gt;Ro’s The Bad Space&lt;/a&gt; list. Both of those are based on community consensus about who are the bad actors on the fediverse, and by importing the lists into AoIR.social’s moderation panel, bad actors – including the ones implicitly identified in Stanford report – were already blocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while the Stanford report was scary as hell, the community has been aware of bad instances for a while now. The community is sharing knowledge about the bad servers and is blocking them. As one admin put it to me, any fedi admin with any consciousness about moderation has been blocking the bad instances for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since the report came out, I’ve interviewed Oliphant, Ro, and other respected fediverse admins and they are advocating for easier use of blocklists to prevent the fediverse from being swamped with bad servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, a great response to moderation challenges is coming in the form of Ro’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://nivenly.org/docs/papers/fsep/&quot;&gt;Fediverse Safety Enhancement Project&lt;/a&gt;. This project is about automated, consensus-based subscription blocklists. The proposed interface looks a lot like one of my favorite tools, The &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/&quot;&gt;Pi-Hole ad-blocking system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;huge.&lt;/em&gt; There are so many interesting things to figure out, from the technical to social. Special attention should be paid to how such lists will be governed. The good news is there are folks working on that exact issue, including Ro and Oliphant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint, hint, fellow ASM academics: this is a good topic to study! I know Ro and people like him would welcome academic knowledge about how to improve this new form of moderation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, if you’re interested in supporting Ro’s project, I recommend giving (you gotta give!) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gofundme.com/f/a-new-way-to-social-media&quot;&gt;to his GoFundMe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aoir-workshop-is-a-go&quot;&gt;AOIR Workshop is a Go&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, Jessa Lingel, Ashwin Nagappa, and I are hosting an &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.org/aoir2023/preconfworkshops/&quot;&gt;Association of Internet Researchers Preconference focusing on alternative social media&lt;/a&gt;. This will take place in Philadelphia on October 18. From what we’ve seen, we’re just short of full capacity. If you’re going to AOIR, there may be still time to sign up if you haven’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still planning details but our focus will be on research project creation and ethics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Moderation" /><category term="ASM update" /><summary type="html">It’s been a while, thanks to drama with rent and apartments (welcome to Toronto, Robert), but I’m back with another Alternative Social Media update!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seeking Grad Students and Postdocs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/02/GradStudentsPostDocs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seeking Grad Students and Postdocs" /><published>2023-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/07/02/GradStudentsPostDocs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/02/GradStudentsPostDocs.html">&lt;p&gt;This is just a short note to announce that, thanks to some generous funding at York University, I am recruiting graduate students (MA and PhD) as well as post-docs. I’d like to work with folks on alternative social media, in particular. Methodologically, I tend to use qualitative approaches, such as digital ethnography, software studies, and grounded theory/situational analysis. I am a critical scholar, as well, so I prefer working with people who are actively examining power relations in technical systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grad students, York has two programs I’m affiliated with: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorku.ca/gradstudies/sts/&quot;&gt;Science and Technology Studies&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorku.ca/gradstudies/cmct/&quot;&gt;Communication and Culture&lt;/a&gt;, a communication and media studies focused program. My understanding is that STS in particular is eager for students, so if you have any background in STS, I would recommend that route. Either way, please do contact me via email (I have a protonmail account, robertwgehl) or &lt;a href=&quot;https://aoir.social/@rwg&quot;&gt;find me on the fediverse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-docs, York U has received a very generous grant called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorku.ca/research/connected-minds/opportunities/&quot;&gt;Connected Minds&lt;/a&gt; which includes many funding opportunities. Contact me if you have some interest there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.robertwgehl.org/text/gehl_vita.pdf&quot;&gt;Here’s a PDF of my CV&lt;/a&gt; if you want to get a sense of my work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="alternative social media" /><summary type="html">This is just a short note to announce that, thanks to some generous funding at York University, I am recruiting graduate students (MA and PhD) as well as post-docs. I’d like to work with folks on alternative social media, in particular. Methodologically, I tend to use qualitative approaches, such as digital ethnography, software studies, and grounded theory/situational analysis. I am a critical scholar, as well, so I prefer working with people who are actively examining power relations in technical systems. Grad students, York has two programs I’m affiliated with: Science and Technology Studies and Communication and Culture, a communication and media studies focused program. My understanding is that STS in particular is eager for students, so if you have any background in STS, I would recommend that route. Either way, please do contact me via email (I have a protonmail account, robertwgehl) or find me on the fediverse. Post-docs, York U has received a very generous grant called Connected Minds which includes many funding opportunities. Contact me if you have some interest there. Here’s a PDF of my CV if you want to get a sense of my work.</summary></entry></feed>