<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-16T15:27:37-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds, On Demand Edition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/29/FOSSFindsOnDemand.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds, On Demand Edition" /><published>2022-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/06/29/FOSSFindsOnDemand</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/29/FOSSFindsOnDemand.html">&lt;p&gt;As I’ve written before, I’m working on a book about the fediverse. To do that properly, I need to have a good understanding of ActivityPub, a key underlying protocol that enables servers to talk to one another. A member of one ActivityPub-enabled server, such as Mastodon, can connect with another on a different server – even if it runs different software, such as Pixelfed. It’s quite a technical achievement and – I believe – it really needs to be part of the conversation when we discuss things like moderation, platform governance, and the political economy of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to study how such software develops over time, so I’ve been going through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg&quot;&gt;meeting minutes of the W3C Social Web Working Group&lt;/a&gt;. It’s been fascinating to see how they, for example, discuss &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg/Social_API/User_stories&quot;&gt;user stories&lt;/a&gt; and how they inform the protocol’s functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I posted a short note about doing this work on my home Mastodon instance, scholar.social, and people noticed! This is what I love about scholar.social – when I talk about geeking out about something, people jump in. Another fediverse member suggested I take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://yewtu.be/watch?v=c17gjxEoyMQ&quot;&gt;this week’s FOSS Find&lt;/a&gt;. And now, I’m writing up notes about it – at the request of the author of the Find. Read more after the jump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;benjamin-goering-on-activitypub-w3c-recommendation-2022&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yewtu.be/watch?v=c17gjxEoyMQ&quot;&gt;Benjamin Goering on “ActivityPub W3C Recommendation.”&lt;/a&gt; 2022.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a recording of a presentation by Goering at “Papers We Love” earlier this year. Goering has been “working on decentralized social networking” for 15 years, and here the “paper” he’s lovin’ on is ActivityPub, a W3C standard. In these notes, I’ll include approximate minute markers, typically tied to the title of the slides. I’ll include summaries, and some of my own personal notes. This also includes some notes on Christine Lemmer-Webber’s comments during Q and A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goering’s agenda is to talk about ActivityStreams, the W3C Activity Streams 2.0, and then ActivityPub, past and future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history-of-activity-streams&quot;&gt;History of Activity Streams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.47 - “History (1997 and before) - Activity Theory”: He notes the connection between this protocol and sociology. The screen shows the book &lt;em&gt;The Russian Theory of Activity&lt;/em&gt; by Bedny and Meister, 1997. It’s about
human-computer interaction thinking from Russia. In the 1990s, Western researchers took these ideas up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.44 “I don’t know much about this,” he notes, but he likes the idea of sociology informing software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.47 - History (2005) - bengo blogging: He points to his blogging experience as a teen – the web wasn’t centralized. It was blogrolls, links, the “whole web was a social network” with RSS helping make connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.32 - History (2007) - Giant Global Graph aka ‘web 3.0’: Here we learn about Tim Berners-Lee’s work on the semantic web with the MIT decentralized group lab. The semantic idea is links between data within web documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.59 - History (2007) - https://diso-project.org: This is about the Distributed Social project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6.25 - History (2007) - OpenSocial, OpenID 2.0: OpenSocial was a Google project. OpenID is still around. Goering implemented these on his blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8.12 - History (2008) - OpenSocial Foundation: This was a foundation started by Google, Yahoo! and MySpace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8.46 - History (2008) - activity-streams mailing list: he uses the Internet Archive to find some of the original posts to this list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8.50 - History (2009) - Facebook Activity Streams: “Facebook Open Stream API” - this would allow applications to read the Facebook Stream, and it would run on ActivityStreams 1.0. ActivityStreams 1.0 was a description of social activities in XML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9.36 - ~2010 - GNU Social, status.net, pump.io. Here we’re talking about projects like diaspora*, ActivityPump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~11.23 - an open social web: In 2009, he notes, Google, Facebook, MySpace, Microsoft, Yahoo all tried implementing open social networking “using a common data model.” “That’s no longer the case. What happened? How can we get back? Should we even?” This is a very important observation. What about the business model precluded such a movement? He posts a Quora article that discusses how Google and Facebook fought over OpenSocial – FB saw it as encroaching on its turf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12.13 - Embrace, extend, extinguish: He notes that this was a real possibility at this point. Think about if Google were to really build out a decentralized social standard and then either abandon it or make parts of it proprietary. The idea here is that someone like a Microsoft takes up open standards, extends them with proprietary extensions and gains market share, then extinguishes the standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13.01 - OpenSocial Foundation PR: He posts the 2014 announcement that OpenSocial Foundation (the one started by Google, Yahoo, and MySpace) “moved” to the W3C Social Working group I saw “moved” because the IRC meetings show they didn’t know this was happening and that it put no obligations on them; it just dumped the money on the WG, from what I can tell. He notes that they were donating their documents and code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-2-w3c-social-web-wg&quot;&gt;Part 2: W3C Social Web WG&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14.24 - https://www.w3.org/2013/socialweb/social-wg-charter.html: He looks at the Charter for the Working Group. The Charter was meant to constrain and guide the group. He works through the Charter, talking about “user control of personal data,” federation, “embedded experiences”, and “enterprise social business.” The latter is about replacing email? Embedded experiences is about having social events trigger consumption “within the page itself.” Federation is what it implies – two or more organizations communicating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporate actors were involved: IBM, Yammer, Salesfore was making Chatter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~15.50 goals based on the charter: make a Social Syntax (in JSON-LD). Make a Social API (client applications). Make a federation protocol, so the servers could talk to one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16.52 - Activity Streams 2.0 Core: ActivityPub depends on AS 2.0, but AS 2.0 is also independent. AS is about “social data syntax” (in the charter). ActivityPub fulfills federation mandate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2014 was a time when JSON was being used to describe things, Actor Verb Object. He talks through debate over JSON versus JSON-LD. The goal was to make it extensible, so JSON-LD is attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;19.43 - Activity Streams 2.0 Vocabulary: He walks us through Core types, Actor Types, Activity Types, and Object and Link Types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;21.42 - ActivityPub - https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/: ActivityPub makes use of ActivityStreams 2.0. HTTP helps send the AS data around (though he will go on to note that AP is not necessarily tied to HTTP). “Honestly, it works a lot like email,” he says: there are inbox, outbox terms. He wonders if they should have extended or modified SMTP [that’s a really intriguing little thought experiment!]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christine Lemmer-Webber, who is in attendance (and who also contributed a great deal to this project) confirms that it could be pushed past http, like IPFS, but that it relies heavily on the HTTP verbs GET and POST. Goering responds: ah, this is why there are so many verbs in the protocol – to make it as independent of HTTP as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;25.25 - ActivityPub Actors - https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/: Here we discuss Actors. The Actor Model from computer science. This is taken up in blockchain stuff, too. “Really, ActivityPub is trying to find a way to describe all these actors.” A stream of inputs and a stream of outputs between actors. The Actor Model in computer science goes back to 1973. [As an aside, tt strikes me as very individualistic – the actor speaks, a stream comes forth. Is there a way to model collective knowledge?]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26.34 - ActivityPub Interactions - https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/: Section 5, Collections: servers maintain these – outbox, inbox, followers, liked, following. Section 6, Client-server interactions, how the client’s typing gets encoded in the syntax. Section 7, Server to server interactions: activities such as a follower activity means another server updates the follower collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;28.58 - ActivityPub “Security” [note: these quote marks in the original]: Security, he notes, is an afterthought after making the protocol. They wanted to publish the protocol and left security for the future. There’s a discussion of authentication schemes, signed keys. This was a bunch of suggestions, not “normative” (not required to abide by). He gets a question about authentication and identity, he notes that Oauth is the recommended approach but it’s an architecture, not a protocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;32.19 - Social Web Protocols: This is another document that the WG produced. Amy Guy, University of Edinburgh edited it. This compares a bunch of protocols – this helped the group keep track of competing protocols. He notes that this is a good doc to study, so I put it in Zotero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;33.11 - relationship to Tim BL’s Solid: Starts in MIT with decentralized web group. Solid tried to leverage AS, AP. Solid gets lots of coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-3-activitypub-today&quot;&gt;Part 3: ActivityPub Today&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;34.25 - https://github.com/BasixKOR/awesome-activitypub: List of projects running on the protocol. Nextcloud social is one. Castling.club – chess over activitypub, he cites this as an example of emergent, unexpected results of a protocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;35.53 - Mastodon wikipedia page: Mastodon was around before AP; they were using status.net, they were very early adopters of AP. He says he’s seen estimates that 10 million people are using Mastodon; he notes it could be much more. [I should ask him where he’s getting these numbers; everything I’ve seen estimates about 5mil users].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He points out Content Warnings as an innovation. Thus, he argues ActivityPub as a protocol helps set the base for these end-user features such as CWs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;37.58 - discussion of EU, Next Generation Internet: Billions of dollars to spread European values on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a server implements ActivityPub well, end users get a “lot of choice in how they participate in the network.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~40.00 - he talks about the term “fediverse.” He notes the fediverse may not necessarily all use the same protocol. The forum for activitypub is socialhub.activitypub.rocks – this defacto replaces the Social Web WG as an organizing site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;41.24 - ActivityPub Conf: He cites a talk “Architecture of Robust Kindness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-4-future-of-activitypub-its-up-to-you&quot;&gt;Part 4: Future of ActivityPub (it’s up to you)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;42.13 - OcaPup: Object Capabilities + ActivityPub. Christine Lemmer-Webber working on this project to pursue security for marginalized groups. “OcapPub: Towards networks of consent” [I need to learn more about this!]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;43.40 - Extensions?: Discusses ways AP can be extended. This can be done via websites without permission from the WG; and if an extension catches on, it may be added to the AP itself. This is a benefit of JSON-LD; easily extended via RDF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;45.04 - Possible Futures: This includes non-http, e.g., Bluetooth, Data integrity, portable identity. Discussion of URNs versus URLs. Concerns about man-in-the-middle attacks that rewrite HTTP. Discussion of a protocol that would delegate the ability to post to others/other devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;50.22 - Related Work/Current Events: Slide presents Bluesky (blueskyweb.xyz), Solid, Spritely. Discusses Elon Musk, EU regulations. Due to the EU regulation, interoperability is much more important&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~52.00 - Start Using ActivityPub: Discussion of clients, Mastodon instances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-and-a&quot;&gt;Q and A&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~56.00 - Christine Lemmer-Webber discusses the difference between the client-to-server part of AP and the server-to-server part. S2S is widely implemented; she notes that they were shocked that the C2S has not been well-implemented. Also notes they only barely got the federation part done. She explains C2S works like an email client: client to server, server to next server. She also notes that SMTP’s and ActivityPub’s “notions of trust” are “broken”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1:00.00 – Christine volunteers to clarify some things, noting Goering covered a lot of history she didn’t know. Christine was in Ostatus et al; Bengo was more familiar with Activity Streams. She notes Ostatus implementations often weren’t compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1:02 - ActivityPub: originally was requiring C2S and S2S implementation. These were divided later on. She talks about MediaGoblin, which promised federation. She hired Jessica Tallon to pursue it. They got involved in the W3C standards, and they were passionate contributors (they didn’t start that way) who got more and more involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not obvious ActivityPub was going to succeed. There were many competing protocols, none of which were talking to each other – and the common sense was that people weren’t going to get along.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">As I’ve written before, I’m working on a book about the fediverse. To do that properly, I need to have a good understanding of ActivityPub, a key underlying protocol that enables servers to talk to one another. A member of one ActivityPub-enabled server, such as Mastodon, can connect with another on a different server – even if it runs different software, such as Pixelfed. It’s quite a technical achievement and – I believe – it really needs to be part of the conversation when we discuss things like moderation, platform governance, and the political economy of the internet. I like to study how such software develops over time, so I’ve been going through the meeting minutes of the W3C Social Web Working Group. It’s been fascinating to see how they, for example, discuss user stories and how they inform the protocol’s functionality. I posted a short note about doing this work on my home Mastodon instance, scholar.social, and people noticed! This is what I love about scholar.social – when I talk about geeking out about something, people jump in. Another fediverse member suggested I take a look at this week’s FOSS Find. And now, I’m writing up notes about it – at the request of the author of the Find. Read more after the jump.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">(I’m) Mashing That Subscribe Button</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/26/Subscribe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="(I’m) Mashing That Subscribe Button" /><published>2022-05-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/26/Subscribe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/26/Subscribe.html">&lt;p&gt;One major goal for my Goal 2 book project is to learn from people who create things on the fediverse. They might create code and cultures by developing and running instances. Or, they might be using the fediverse to promote their &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixelfed.social/&quot;&gt;photography&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://funkwhale.audio/&quot;&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://writefreely.org/&quot;&gt;ideas&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an endowed research chair, I have the privilege of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.regents.la.gov/assets/docs/2013/05/BoRSF_Endowed_Prof_Policy_Rev_10-12.pdf&quot;&gt;generous research funding&lt;/a&gt;. For the purposes of my book project, research includes talking to people, running my own digital infrastructure (e.g., the incredible Nextcloud), and, of course, studying texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meaning of “texts” is quite open-ended. Obviously, I’m reading books and journal articles. But so, so much knowledge is being created on the Fediverse itself – including knowledge offered only to subscribers. There are artists, musicians, and writers using Patreon (or, maybe better, &lt;a href=&quot;https://liberapay.com/&quot;&gt;Liberapay&lt;/a&gt;) to share their work with subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the math, Robert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mash that subscribe button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;subscribing-as-research&quot;&gt;Subscribing as Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/subscribe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;subscribe button&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Mash it
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much as I would subscribe to an important journal (say, &lt;em&gt;New Media &amp;amp; Society&lt;/em&gt;) to stay up on the field, I’m increasingly finding I need to subscribe to Fediverse-based artists, writers, and musicians. So, I’m going to spend a part of my research budget buying these research materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This raises some important questions, though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do I do with the materials I purchase?&lt;/strong&gt; The obvious answer is that I archive it. But since I’m buying these items with public money, should they be made public? I think the answer here is “no,” because the authors intend that these items be for subscribers only. The exception might be if the creator specifically and explicitly consents to have the item shared. In that case, I think my next step is to talk to a library to see if they want to archive the item for future researchers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, how might I cite these items?&lt;/strong&gt; The answer here is similar: I cannot, unless the creator explicitly says I can. (I’ll write more about this in a later post).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m &lt;a href=&quot;2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html&quot;&gt;interviewing people&lt;/a&gt; as part of this project. How does subscribing affect my research prior to interviews?&lt;/strong&gt; Answer: I cannot really interview a creator without seeing their work, no? So, for example, if I want to interview an author of a book, I really ought to read that book, whether from a library or if I buy my own copy. The same is true of a Fediverse artist: I need to see their work to ask intelligent questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, are the people you subscribe to obliged to talk to you?&lt;/strong&gt; This is the biggest ethical question I’m dealing with. My plan is to make it crystal clear that my subscribing to an artist does not oblige them to talk to me, and that if I reach out with an interview request, their response (including “oh, hell no!”) will not result in my stopping my subscription. I’m committing keeping my subscriptions going for at least a year, regardless of response to interview requests. (This would only change if my funding changes).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very least, then, subscribing as part of the research process would give me more insights into the creative works of Fediverse artists while supporting their work. I also do hope that subscribing can lead to meeting artists and creators who do want to talk to me about their experience with the Fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very open to comments and critiques of this – if you’ve got comments, find me on Mastodon (or comment below with your Fedi account, so long as your comment is set to Public).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">One major goal for my Goal 2 book project is to learn from people who create things on the fediverse. They might create code and cultures by developing and running instances. Or, they might be using the fediverse to promote their photography, music, or ideas. As an endowed research chair, I have the privilege of generous research funding. For the purposes of my book project, research includes talking to people, running my own digital infrastructure (e.g., the incredible Nextcloud), and, of course, studying texts. The meaning of “texts” is quite open-ended. Obviously, I’m reading books and journal articles. But so, so much knowledge is being created on the Fediverse itself – including knowledge offered only to subscribers. There are artists, musicians, and writers using Patreon (or, maybe better, Liberapay) to share their work with subscribers. Do the math, Robert. Mash that subscribe button.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds, StoryCorps Edition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/23/FOSSFinds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds, StoryCorps Edition" /><published>2022-04-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/23/FOSSFinds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/23/FOSSFinds.html">&lt;p&gt;This month’s FOSS finds: I was listening to NPR (which makes sense since I drive an electric car and I am a communist) and StoryCorps came on. I usually hear it while dropping my kid off at school, and it’s always a conversation-starter between us. It has been for years. Which got me to thinking: the StoryCorps project must have &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of archived recordings of their oral history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, they do. They’ve been doing oral history for 20 years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which got me to thinking: if StoryCorps has been around for 20 years, they must have done an interview or two about FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the FOSS find this time are a few citations of those interviews. I haven’t had a chance to listen to them yet, so these abstracts will be from the StoryCorps site. I will listen to them soon, because I wonder if they can supplement my Goal 2 book project research. I’m &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html&quot;&gt;conducting interviews of my own&lt;/a&gt;, but the more voices, the better, yeah?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read on to see the ones I found in a few minutes of searching. Feel free to suggest more such interviews!
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;agarwal-ammar-2020-ammar-agarwal---computer-programming-interview-interview-by-luke-audio&quot;&gt;Agarwal, Ammar. 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.storycorps.org/interviews/ammar-agarwal-computer-programming-interview/&quot;&gt;Ammar Agarwal - Computer Programming Interview Interview by Luke&lt;/a&gt;. Audio.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT: “I interview Ammar Agarwal and ask questions related to computer programming.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beda-joe-2021-joe-beda-on-open-source-as-a-positive-sum-game-interview-by-amanda-casari-and-julia-ferraioli-audio&quot;&gt;Beda, Joe. 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.storycorps.org/interviews/joe-beda-on-open-source-as-a-positive-sum-game/&quot;&gt;Joe Beda on open source as a positive sum game Interview by Amanda Casari and Julia Ferraioli.&lt;/a&gt; Audio.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Joe Beda shares with Julia and Amanda about his multigenerational family history with computers, his changing experience with open source since submitting the first commit to Kubernetes, and how the future of open source contains both ‘danger and opportunity’.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goddy-samson-2021-samson-goddy-on-the-power-of-centering-open-source-on-community-needs-interview-by-amanda-casari-audio&quot;&gt;Goddy, Samson. 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.storycorps.org/interviews/amanda-casari-2/&quot;&gt;Samson Goddy on the power of centering open source on community needs Interview by Amanda Casari&lt;/a&gt;. Audio.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Samson talks with Amanda about his lifelong journey in open source, why growing a culture of sharing is so important, and how his early experiences influenced where and how he has directed his energy into re-centering the nexus of open source.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hashman-elana-and-amanda-casari-2022-elana-hashman-on-the-evolution-of-open-sourceaudio&quot;&gt;Hashman, Elana, and Amanda Casari. 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.storycorps.org/interviews/elana-hashman-on-the-evolution-of-open-source/&quot;&gt;Elana Hashman on the evolution of open source&lt;/a&gt;.Audio.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Elana Hashman recounts her first contribution to open source, the ecosystem’s potential, how norms have changed over the years, and what keeps her involved and contributing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keith-magee-russell-2021-open-source-stories-with-russell-keith-magee-interview-by-julia-ferraioli-audio&quot;&gt;Keith-Magee, Russell. 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.storycorps.org/interviews/julia-ferraioli-2/&quot;&gt;Open Source Stories with Russell Keith-Magee Interview by Julia Ferraioli&lt;/a&gt;. Audio.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Russell talks with julia about his open source origin story, how he became involved in his first project, and what he sees as current issues with maintainership in open source.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;patterson-aaron-2021-aaron-patterson-amanda-casari-and-julia-ferraioli-interview-by-amanda-casari-and-julia-ferraioli-audio&quot;&gt;Patterson, Aaron. 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.storycorps.org/interviews/aaron-patterson-amanda-casari-and-julia-ferraioli/&quot;&gt;Aaron Patterson, Amanda Casari, and Julia Ferraioli Interview by Amanda Casari and Julia Ferraioli&lt;/a&gt;. Audio.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Aaron Patterson talks with Julia and Amanda about installing Linux for the first time, the story behind first patch, initial hesitancy around forking, and shares some advice for fellow programmers. Features plenty of bad puns from everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transcript: https://www.opensourcestories.org/stories/2021/aaron-patterson/”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;steenhout-nicolas-2022-nicolas-steenhout-explores-the-intersection-of-accessibility-and-open-source-interview-by-julia-ferraioli-and-amanda-casari-audio&quot;&gt;Steenhout, Nicolas. 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.storycorps.org/interviews/nicolas-steenhout-on-accessibility-in-open-source-and-beyond/&quot;&gt;Nicolas Steenhout explores the intersection of accessibility and open source Interview by Julia Ferraioli and Amanda Casari&lt;/a&gt;. Audio.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Nic Steenhout recounts how barriers to access led him to getting involved in the open source community, reflects on challenges that accessibility advocates face in the ecosystem, and gives some advice to projects on how to prove their commitment to accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">This month’s FOSS finds: I was listening to NPR (which makes sense since I drive an electric car and I am a communist) and StoryCorps came on. I usually hear it while dropping my kid off at school, and it’s always a conversation-starter between us. It has been for years. Which got me to thinking: the StoryCorps project must have a lot of archived recordings of their oral history. Indeed, they do. They’ve been doing oral history for 20 years now. Which got me to thinking: if StoryCorps has been around for 20 years, they must have done an interview or two about FOSS. Indeed, they have. So the FOSS find this time are a few citations of those interviews. I haven’t had a chance to listen to them yet, so these abstracts will be from the StoryCorps site. I will listen to them soon, because I wonder if they can supplement my Goal 2 book project research. I’m conducting interviews of my own, but the more voices, the better, yeah? Read on to see the ones I found in a few minutes of searching. Feel free to suggest more such interviews!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Interview Workflow</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Interview Workflow" /><published>2022-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/17/InterviewWorkflow.html">&lt;p&gt;With my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/social-engineering&quot;&gt;last book&lt;/a&gt; wrapped up, I am now hard at work building the next book, which is the Goal 2 of this blog. (Goal 1, recall, is writing about being a FOSS academic. Goal 2 is writing a book about FOSS). My new book project will focus on what I’m calling &lt;a href=&quot;https://fossacademic.tech/2022/01/06/Goal2.html&quot;&gt;“ethical source alternative social media”&lt;/a&gt; – social media that allows ordinary people to be in control, that uses moderation for social, economic, and environmental justice and not to support oppression, and that runs on FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Methodologically, this project will demand I use my expertise in software studies, science and technology studies, and critical communication studies to analyze code, protocols, and network structures. But I also want to use participant observation and interviewing. And, I want this to adhere to the highest ethical standands as well as use FOSS technologies throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to include the voices of ethical ASM members, developers, and admins. It may be tempting to do what a lot of people seem to have done and quote fediverse posts. However, I’ve observed that many, many fediverse users do not consent to having their posts taken out of context. There are public forums I can quote – for example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/discussions&quot;&gt;Github issues forum for Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;. But I think the best vehicle to hear people talk about their experience with ethical ASM is via interviewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I will briefly describe how I will manage interviewing. I hope this resource is useful not just to other researchers, but also to anyone considering being interviewed by me who might be curious about my process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/microphone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Microphone and screen&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@willfrancis?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Will Francis&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/s/photos/interview?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-participant-observation&quot;&gt;Step 1: Participant Observation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first step has been going on for a long time: I’m participating in ethical alternative social media (and quite a few systems I would not categorize as ethical). As I do so, I take notes on the discourses happening on these systems, and I try to figure out which participants are passionate and invested ones. I want to talk to developers, administrators, and members of ethical alternatives. I note who they are with the intention of inviting them to participate in interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-inviting-people-to-a-conversation&quot;&gt;Step 2: Inviting People to a Conversation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After coming up with a list of interesting people to speak to, I reach out to them. Most likely, this will be via a fediverse DM or email. This is the moment when I explain my purpose in talking to them and how their ideas can contribute not only to the book project, but also to magazine articles or academic journal articles. I can also ask them to look at an informed consent form – a vital part of ethical research practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I invite people to talk via whatever their preferred medium. If they have no preference or are comfortable with Jitsi video chat, I have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/jitsi&quot;&gt;Jitsi plugin for Nextcloud&lt;/a&gt; ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-preparation&quot;&gt;Step 3: Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be ready for the interview, I should read/watch/interact with as much material from the interviewee as possible. I look at their public posts, blogs, artwork, videos, writings – just to get a sense of who they are and what they care about. Since so much of FOSS culture is pretty technical, I pay a great deal of attention to technical details so I am a bit more informed before we talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write out about a dozen questions, ranging from asking for names/pseudonyms and pronouns to open-ended questions meant to spark a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-4-the-interview&quot;&gt;Step 4: The Interview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are using my Jitsi app, I can record the interview (assuming of course the interviewee consents not only to talking, but being recorded). While it will record video, I am more concerned about getting audio. Jitsi’s Nextcloud app has one flaw: it records to Dropbox. I am not a fan of this but I can’t work around it just yet. (If anyone has advice about how Jitsi recordings could be routed to Nextcloud, I’m very interested).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I go through my questions, but in my experience conversations don’t always lend themselves to sticking to the script. That’s just fine – I use my questions as a general guide, but the discussion can go in other directions as the interviewee leads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I interview, I take notes on paper – after all, what if the recording fails? Paper notes also come in handy for the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will conclude the interview by asking if the interviewee has questions about me or my project, other things to add, and if they can recommend other people for me to talk to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the interview concludes, I remove the recorded file from Dropbox and store it on my Nextcloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-5-journaling&quot;&gt;Step 5: Journaling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the interview is over, I write a journal entry with my thoughts on the conversation – things like good stories, new ways of thinking about the topic, and a general summary of the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also happy to share my notes or the recordings with interviewees, so I follow-up via email to mention that and thank them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-6-transcribing&quot;&gt;Step 6: Transcribing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an area where I am tempted to use automated systems, but must refuse. After all, most transcription services, like Otter.ai, require me to upload audio to the cloud. No thank you. I think that violates confidentiality, and it also violates my desire to have this be as FOSS and self-hosted as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this is the stage where I either transcribe or at least take very detailed notes on the conversation. Full disclosure: I may start collaborating with a grad student; if so, they may get involved here at the transcription stage. But for now, it’s just me doing this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-critical-reflection&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Critical Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that’s that: the interview process. It’s almost entirely FOSS/self-hosted, with the exception of Jitsi recording to Dropbox. And I hope all of this is transparent and ethical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One practice I engage in throughout the above is: can this be better? For example, does my workflow adequately protect interviewee data? Am I doing a good job recruiting interviewees? Are my questions prompting a good conversation? And can I get away from Dropbox?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, what am I missing here? If you have comments on this process, please let me know via the Fediverse comment system below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">With my last book wrapped up, I am now hard at work building the next book, which is the Goal 2 of this blog. (Goal 1, recall, is writing about being a FOSS academic. Goal 2 is writing a book about FOSS). My new book project will focus on what I’m calling “ethical source alternative social media” – social media that allows ordinary people to be in control, that uses moderation for social, economic, and environmental justice and not to support oppression, and that runs on FOSS. Methodologically, this project will demand I use my expertise in software studies, science and technology studies, and critical communication studies to analyze code, protocols, and network structures. But I also want to use participant observation and interviewing. And, I want this to adhere to the highest ethical standands as well as use FOSS technologies throughout. I want to include the voices of ethical ASM members, developers, and admins. It may be tempting to do what a lot of people seem to have done and quote fediverse posts. However, I’ve observed that many, many fediverse users do not consent to having their posts taken out of context. There are public forums I can quote – for example, the Github issues forum for Mastodon. But I think the best vehicle to hear people talk about their experience with ethical ASM is via interviewing. In this post I will briefly describe how I will manage interviewing. I hope this resource is useful not just to other researchers, but also to anyone considering being interviewed by me who might be curious about my process. Photo by Will Francis on Unsplash</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Book, Old Book</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/26/NewBookOldBook.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Book, Old Book" /><published>2022-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/26/NewBookOldBook</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/26/NewBookOldBook.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve not written much about my most recent book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/social-engineering&quot;&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/a&gt; (MIT Press, 2022) on this blog. It didn’t seem like a good topic for this FOSS-centric blog. When I did write about it, I focused on the fact that my co-author, Sean Lawson, and I were able to use FOSS (particularly Nextcloud) to write it. In the parlance of this blog, that’s a decidedly Goal 1 topic – about using FOSS tools to do academic work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ve focused instead on my next project, the Goal 2 project of writing a book about FOSS alternative social media. My idea is to use this blog to publicly write that book. Such public writing is new to me – it’s even a bit intimidating – but seems appropriate for this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the more I’m digging into what it means to envision, make, and realize ethical, FOSS, alternative social media, the more I realize my latest book, &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering,&lt;/em&gt; is directly relevant to the project. So, this post is a way for me to make those connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/secover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover of book Social Engineering by Gehl and Lawson&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was prompted by the explosion of disinformation and manipulation we’ve observed over the past 10 years. The big events here, of course, were the Russian interference campaign and Cambridge Analytica, both reaching prominence during the 2016 US presidential election. (We also write about more recent events, but these are two very well-documented instances of attempts at mass manipulation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a better understanding of Russian disinformation or Cambridge Analytica “micro-targeting,” Sean and I turned to the concept of social engineering. We note that this term has been used in two distinct communicative contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First was the early 20th century propagandists who drew on the language of social reform and social science of their time. They proposed to adjust society using scientific techniques and mass persuasion, a process glossed as “engineering of consent” (to use Edward Bernays’s famous phrase).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there were the mid-20th century phone phreaks and hackers, who use the term “social engineering” to describe their practice of conning people out of passwords. This is an interpersonal sort of manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We argue that both the mass social engineering of propaganda and the interpersonal social engineering of hacking merge in contemporary corporate social media in a form we call “masspersonal social engineering.” We define &lt;a href=&quot;https://watermark.silverchair.com/c000400_9780262368926.pdf?token=AQECAHi208BE49Ooan9kkhW_Ercy7Dm3ZL_9Cf3qfKAc485ysgAAAsIwggK-BgkqhkiG9w0BBwagggKvMIICqwIBADCCAqQGCSqGSIb3DQEHATAeBglghkgBZQMEAS4wEQQMYRnDz0chEg8p6ccQAgEQgIICdeFTnQWL17PMR9vfCgwJHJa9mUSadJGxEZGbQ55WiOpspJXi-nE2GHUh-JJvtcwSpeWi5QYTPZ_uSyH7QtFX9z06Dukk9NxStvdw6D7eBGHQdgbFtz0_FkXoEhvJRdsvVoJnwwwO-vu3fvRdkHWjlX-Qdr5bMlNH_HQJxKW7TOvFkXolVhz0w9XEnGvEcE5npx1KLzlFPiCmHero5cufwHKB7d8im_4Q7zpPvHrZSDtJB5i1zjleafXz_UL28vM9JhjHeEurgOf-raryGnepdJqxvvZqqrHraRWghk9T90beKO-BDCCiMKy9qCp100OSNf9BB9a_STvST0PcPdpoy12vP5ZSwXE-9QaxP6I8PguUwXRm9Gb-Bos8n4WtHqgJZIPPUyVXe4Pwzlr0s7SHFO7K7NG866vjfJ3tWefx4fkQBFxKAJMaIGq3VoULFl0cT12XVdkK0sxJt_xRRDDzUi-s0fhW1SBEjRNnAhe_EpdBpmDVUjJLU5V4TCv1Y9p7h0ubLKcyc8JwPjanaUmLvd-t5k0UqImqHiFbVu68fzSFqsehqPt56UrnknXlc6HqFjB10EHzmQgxk4cJR46uhohOpyyysIr3RxwNwx_Zs4uOqYZo-9zdvsMcCLVNLMXAU4mu3x1PDTY3z1ututpvDf-m3UkRmEngvqe1ve7v6cwE9MWJ-NaYQvrdJ53QzsZ5muuoiJTEAjYI8PptRclByNJj5UMQ3i7uYoC_wVDzYivtleynpi66aEN0_2GQsNawYCvEGeLGzTt4ZLudF18AUnfawOxhcpkWJxpaP9jTNIma5bbPqR3uea5SQFTWV_MfC43MPlrF&quot;&gt;this concept in the book as&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;an emerging form of manipulative communication enabled by
the unique affordances of the internet and social media platforms.
It brings together the respective tools and techniques of hackers
and propagandists, interpersonal and mass communication, in
an attempt to shape the perceptions and actions of audiences. To
manipulate, masspersonal social engineers gather data on their
targets; create fake personas to share messages; mix deception,
accuracy, and friendliness as they engage with targets; and penetrate
communication systems. Manipulation, in this case, can involve a
range of goals, which might include attempts to change actions and
beliefs. But it could also include discouraging action (e.g., voting)
and amplifying or intensifying preexisting beliefs (e.g., racism,
sexism, or other social divisions) when doing so is in the perceived
interests of the masspersonal social engineers or their clients.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The connection to my current project on ethical alternative social media is now very obvious to me. Part of what we have to do when making a better suite of social media technologies is to remove the technologies, policies, and practices that aid and abet masspersonal social engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are obvious things, such as eliminating behavioral advertising, which encourages the use of reductive consumer profiling and links those profiles to viral messaging – a perfect breeding ground for the spread of misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also less obvious things that have to be done – such as bringing media control closer to the end users. I wonder how much disinformation and misinformation spread is aided by a lack of a sense of shared responsibility for the health of the “community” in corporate social media. Contrast this with smaller, federated social media systems, where users may feel that they have more ownership over the health of the instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this post is merely my flagging the fact that my old book may end up more important to the new one. I may refer to the ideas from &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/em&gt; more often here. Rest assured, this is not in an attempt to sell my book, but is rather a way to think about how ethical alternatives may help alleviate the scourge of manipulative communication (or, and let’s be honest, how they also might become vectors for manipulation in their own right).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of that, if you’re curious about the connections between the history of manipulative communication and what alternative social media might do to undermine such manipulation, keep watching this blog, and perhaps you should check out &lt;em&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/em&gt; – it’s in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.powells.com/book/social-engineering-9780262543453&quot;&gt;finer bookstores now&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://direct.mit.edu/books/oa-monograph/5281/Social-EngineeringHow-Crowdmasters-Phreaks-Hackers&quot;&gt;you can get it for free from MIT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">I’ve not written much about my most recent book, Social Engineering (MIT Press, 2022) on this blog. It didn’t seem like a good topic for this FOSS-centric blog. When I did write about it, I focused on the fact that my co-author, Sean Lawson, and I were able to use FOSS (particularly Nextcloud) to write it. In the parlance of this blog, that’s a decidedly Goal 1 topic – about using FOSS tools to do academic work. So, I’ve focused instead on my next project, the Goal 2 project of writing a book about FOSS alternative social media. My idea is to use this blog to publicly write that book. Such public writing is new to me – it’s even a bit intimidating – but seems appropriate for this topic. But the more I’m digging into what it means to envision, make, and realize ethical, FOSS, alternative social media, the more I realize my latest book, Social Engineering, is directly relevant to the project. So, this post is a way for me to make those connections.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/07/FOSSFinds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds" /><published>2022-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/07/FOSSFinds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/07/FOSSFinds.html">&lt;p&gt;This week’s FOSS finds: The big news – or maybe non-news – in this space is the pathetically inept rollout of Truth Social, Donald Trump’s $1,000,000,000 social networking site built on the free-as-in-beer but also free-as-in-freedom Mastodon software base. I watched Truth go online and I have thoughts, but here I will just share some resources I’ve gathered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;primack-dan-2022-trump-is-blowing-truth-socials-launch-axios-march-2-2022&quot;&gt;Primack, Dan. 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.axios.com/trump-blowing-truth-social-launch-c2d4f1f0-5440-478a-acfa-b9462b64568c.html&quot;&gt;“Trump Is Blowing Truth Social’s Launch.”&lt;/a&gt; Axios. March 2, 2022.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article summarizes the financial aspects of Truth Social, which received quite a bit of investment. Primack notes, however, that Trump has done little to nothing to promote Truth. (What else is new?) so that investors will start to get nervous that this might fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cramer-ruby-2022-the-emptiness-inside-donald-trumps-new-social-media-platform-politico-march-5-2022&quot;&gt;Cramer, Ruby. 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2022/03/05/truth-social-emptiness-donald-trump-00014355.&quot;&gt;“The Emptiness Inside Donald Trump’s New Social Media Platform.”&lt;/a&gt; POLITICO. March 5, 2022.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big problem with the Truth rollout was that they failed to meet the demand of new user signups. Instead, people were put on long waitlists. Ruby Cramer of Politico was one such waitlisted person and, as she reports, once she got into Truth, it seems to be a ghost town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caelin-derek-2020-decentralized-social-networks-vs-the-trolls&quot;&gt;Caelin, Derek. 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yZoASOyfvGQ&quot;&gt;“Decentralized Social Networks vs the Trolls.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start of Truth reminded me of course of the alt-right Christian nationalist Gab.com’s entry into the Fediverse – an entry quickly mitigated by fediblocking. It prompted me to study this video presentation from Derek Caelin, who unpacks the Gab/Mastodon incident with survey and interview data. If you want to understand the fediverse’s reaction to Truth, look to what happened with Gab.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">This week’s FOSS finds: The big news – or maybe non-news – in this space is the pathetically inept rollout of Truth Social, Donald Trump’s $1,000,000,000 social networking site built on the free-as-in-beer but also free-as-in-freedom Mastodon software base. I watched Truth go online and I have thoughts, but here I will just share some resources I’ve gathered.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coding Freedom, by Biella Coleman</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/15/CodingFreedom.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coding Freedom, by Biella Coleman" /><published>2022-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/15/CodingFreedom</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/15/CodingFreedom.html">&lt;p&gt;As part of Goal 2 of this blog, I’m writing a book about FOSS, specifically FOSS alternative social media. Like any good academic, I need to review the literature. I want to do so a bit more publicly than I have in the past – hence this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I’ve already started the process a bit: early on this blog went a bit viral &lt;a href=&quot;2020/12/06/Dreaming-In-Code.html&quot;&gt;thanks to my post about Scott Rosenberg’s &lt;em&gt;Dreaming in Code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was linked by Hacker News. I also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;2021/03/28/RMMess.html&quot;&gt;a review of sorts of Sam Williams’s &lt;em&gt;Free as in Freedom,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a biography of Stallman. I just so happened to finish reading that book when Stallman was reinstated to the FSF, which made my post a bit more polemical than review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I’m going to turn to a modern classic: Gabriella Coleman’s &lt;em&gt;Coding Freedom: The Ethics and Aesthetics of Hacking.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/coleman.gif&quot; alt=&quot;coleman.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coleman is a trained anthropologist, engaging in deep hanging out, and in the early 2000s she turned her attention to one of the most important FOSS projects out there: Debian. She focuses on the full range of Debian’s activities, from gathering at conventions to online networking to the common conception of the self as hacker. Her analysis of conventions as lifeworlds is very powerful. As she argues, “the hacker con is a condensed, weeklong performance of a lifeworld that hackers usually build over decades of experiences and interactions connected to various media, institutions, and objects” (57). Her observation is an antidote to the idea that FOSS hackers only interact virtually – they crave in-person meetings like any sociable human would (which is probably easier to understand in these days of Zooming and distancing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, she discusses the politics of licensing at great length, tracing the now-familiar history of proprietary software on one hand and the sharing of code (and eventual copyleft approach) on the other. And yet, which she notes the idealism of the Free Software crowd, she also documents the pragmatism of many FOSS users: “The majority of hackers I interviewed… came to free software at first merely for the sake of affordable, better-built technology and had little knowledge about the existence, much less the workings, of intellectual property law” (71). (Indeed, this echoes &lt;a href=&quot;2020/12/15/FOSS-Journey.html&quot;&gt;my own FOSS journey&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although people may have come to FOSS without thinking too much about the politics, Coleman also observed how pushback against sharing – particularly the crackdown on DeCSS and the arrest of Dmitry Skylarov – forced many FOSS users into a more political stance. I believe &lt;em&gt;Coding Freedom&lt;/em&gt; is best known for Coleman’s incisive analysis of what might be called “legal hacking,” or the treatment of law as a system susceptible to being tinkered with. For example, a well-known way that FOSS advocates drew attention to the strangeness of criminalizing code was to convert DeCSS into poems and printing it on t-shirts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-big-takeway-for-goal-2&quot;&gt;My Big Takeway for Goal 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to draw on from Coleman’s analysis. But I wonder if her work has become so influential that we take many of her arguments for granted. In some ways, she’s helped create the FOSS world we find ourselves in. Read her book to see what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One area that I think is only now being addressed in FOSS – an area I think Coleman was prescient of – is calls for diversity and concerns about Freedom 0. One of the surprises she experienced was that both Free Software advocates and Open Source, pro-corporate advocates were largely &lt;em&gt;apolitical.&lt;/em&gt; That is, as she discusses, they avoided Left/Right distinctions (pp 185-186). To be certain, there were the activists defending free speech, but little in the way of the left or right politics to be found among FOSS developers. She argues that this political neutrality was central to the growth of FOSS – it turns out to be software that socialists and big corporations see great potential in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of neutrality is tied to Freedom 0, of course, the first of the “Four Freedoms” of Free Software. For example, she quotes a Debian developer, who says, “I can’t control if the person using my software is racist” (187). (I’ve found similar sentiments among the FOSS people I have interviewed, who note their work is not activism, and it isn’t political – they’re just making neutral tools that anyone can use and contribute to.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as we’ve learned in the past decade, corporations and governments will readily adopt FOSS for unethical ends, whether it be manipulative forms of communication, the exploitation of free labor, or to monitor and incarcerate populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, there is currently a revolt against corporate and government surveillance and exploitation but the revolt takes many forms. The revolt against these practices can also be aided by FOSS – but it can also be unethical, with the use of FOSS for hate speech platforms being one example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, there is a call for FOSS &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; Freedom 0, and instead with the ability to prevent, for example, racists from using one’s code. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethicalsource.dev/&quot;&gt;Ethical Source&lt;/a&gt; is one example. Another is the network power of federation (and subsequently, de-federation). In both cases there is a very clear reaction against &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; corporate control &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Freedom 0. These projects, however, are arguably not Free Software by definition. As I think Coleman shows, the only advocacy in Freedom 0 is Freedom – again, no ability to stop bad actors from using one’s code. And, as diversity advocates are pointing out, the politics of “freedom” is often the politics of whiteness, masculinity, and economic exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like so many other aspects of where we are now, Coleman’s work anticipates this debate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Despite their official stance on licensing, some leftists have trouble accepting the formulation of nondiscrimination lying at the heart of F/OSS legal agreements. Some express discomfort or dismay that nondiscrimination, as articulated in F/OSS licensing, bars the type of control that would allow Indymedia to keep its work from being exploited for purposes of oppression (by the military, say) or corporate profit. In this guise, they echo the Marcusian critique of liberalism’s “pure tolerance” of free speech (Marcuse 1965).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that my work is taking me through code to running instances of alternative social media, I must necessarily understand this debate. Coleman’s work grounds the conversation, but I will need to read more. Watch this space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Lit Review" /><summary type="html">As part of Goal 2 of this blog, I’m writing a book about FOSS, specifically FOSS alternative social media. Like any good academic, I need to review the literature. I want to do so a bit more publicly than I have in the past – hence this blog. In fact, I’ve already started the process a bit: early on this blog went a bit viral thanks to my post about Scott Rosenberg’s Dreaming in Code., which was linked by Hacker News. I also wrote a review of sorts of Sam Williams’s Free as in Freedom, a biography of Stallman. I just so happened to finish reading that book when Stallman was reinstated to the FSF, which made my post a bit more polemical than review. This time, I’m going to turn to a modern classic: Gabriella Coleman’s Coding Freedom: The Ethics and Aesthetics of Hacking.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Have Settled on Zettlr</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/Zettlr.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Have Settled on Zettlr" /><published>2022-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/Zettlr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/Zettlr.html">&lt;p&gt;About a week ago, I took to my home Mastodon instance, scholar.social, and asked whether people preferred &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zettlr.com/&quot;&gt;Zettlr&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsidian.md/&quot;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt;. Both are Markdown editors which also provide valuable features on top, including linking together Markdown notes and varying degrees of Zotero support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked because I’m using Markdown more and more. I use it regularly to plan my weeks, I obviously use it for this blog (which is a static Jekyll site), and I started using it to jot down ideas in a journaling program called &lt;a href=&quot;https://rednotebook.sourceforge.io/&quot;&gt;RedNoteBook&lt;/a&gt;. I was hoping to streamline blogging, note-taking, and other Markdown tasks in one system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have tried both Zettlr and Obsidian – and I also tried a third system, &lt;a href=&quot;https://logseq.com/&quot;&gt;Logseq&lt;/a&gt; – and have decided to adopt Zettlr. It meets my needs quite well, which are probably a bit more minimal than people might expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, given what these projects are doing, I do not feel locked into my choice. In fact, I have all three installed and may hop between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-chose-zettlr&quot;&gt;Why I Chose Zettlr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought about writing up comparisons between these systems, but I think those sorts of posts abound – just DuckDuckGo “obsidian vs zettlr” or “zettlr vs logseq” and you’ll see what I mean. Moreover, I get the sense that all of them have some very zealous adherents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/80777352f93ad1f40b45edf2022a55e9.png&quot; alt=&quot;80777352f93ad1f40b45edf2022a55e9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obsidian in particular has a lot of fans on Youtube (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=njibNuFQwjw&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;), who share their complex workflows and talk about how network graphs reveal new ways of thinking. Logseq is based on “block-level” linking, which itself builds on RemNote. As its name implies, Zettlr is inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/introduction/#luhmann-s-zettelkasten&quot;&gt;“Zettlekasten” method of Niklas Luhmann&lt;/a&gt;. If you start searching those terms, be prepared for lengthy manifestos about how to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for me, I guess I’m keeping it simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take notes on things in Zotero, I jot down thoughts in Markdown (previously in the aforementioned RedNoteBook), and then I synthesize the lot in Libreoffice with the Zotero plugin. What was missing in the middle – the Markdown phase – was linking between notes as well as tagging, which is why I’m trying out Obsidian/Zettlr/Logseq in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three of them do wiki-style linking between Markdown files. They also allow for easy octothorpe (#) tagging. The differences appear in how they show those links to me – Obsidian and Logseq show network graphs, and Zettlr just shows backlinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much I think the graphs are cool, I don’t really see much value in them in my day-to-day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead, I’ve opted for the one with the most comfortable interface, and that is Zettlr. The Workspaces layout reminds me of good text editors, the autocomplete on links works quite well, and the right-hand sidebar gives me all the information I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the biggest reason I’m choosing Zettlr is that &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Zettlr/Zettlr&quot;&gt;it’s FOSS&lt;/a&gt;. Since I’m adopting the pose of the FOSS Academic – and since &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/01/06/Goal2.html&quot;&gt;Goal 2&lt;/a&gt; of this blog is to write a book about FOSS – I really have to choose it. Logseq is also FOSS. Obsidian, however, is not, and does not appear to be going in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with Zettlr in the mix, I use FOSS across the board, from my underlying OS (various Linux flavors) to Firefox to Zotero to Zettlr to Libreoffice to this blog. I’m really happy to be able to write like this while I write about FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-i-might-switch-at-any-moment&quot;&gt;But I Might Switch at Any Moment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while I’m using and enjoying Zettlr, the real power of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these systems is that I don’t have to choose. I’m not locked in. All three promise not to lock me in, and they are true to their word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because they’re built on top of simple text files, I can simply jump from Zettlr to Logseq to Obsidian, adding new notes to my collection, and not have the underlying file structure be damaged in any way. So, if I do want to see a network graph of my notes, I could fire up Logseq and take a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan on keeping Logseq and Zettlr on my system indefinitely. (I’m on the fence about Obsidian, since it’s not FOSS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for those of you interested in these systems, give ‘em a try.’&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="Zettlr" /><summary type="html">About a week ago, I took to my home Mastodon instance, scholar.social, and asked whether people preferred Zettlr or Obsidian. Both are Markdown editors which also provide valuable features on top, including linking together Markdown notes and varying degrees of Zotero support. I asked because I’m using Markdown more and more. I use it regularly to plan my weeks, I obviously use it for this blog (which is a static Jekyll site), and I started using it to jot down ideas in a journaling program called RedNoteBook. I was hoping to streamline blogging, note-taking, and other Markdown tasks in one system. So, I have tried both Zettlr and Obsidian – and I also tried a third system, Logseq – and have decided to adopt Zettlr. It meets my needs quite well, which are probably a bit more minimal than people might expect. However, given what these projects are doing, I do not feel locked into my choice. In fact, I have all three installed and may hop between them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FOSS Finds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/29/FOSS-Finds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSS Finds" /><published>2022-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/29/FOSS%20Finds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/29/FOSS-Finds.html">&lt;p&gt;This week’s FOSS finds: I’m starting to look back at the early days of ActivityPub, and chat apps get some coverage. So once again, don’t count on these posts as a news feed, but more a window into my thinking as I research my FOSS alternative social media book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;w3c-launches-push-for-social-web-application-interoperability-2014-w3c-blog-july-21-2014-httpswwww3orgblognewsarchives3958&quot;&gt;“W3C Launches Push for Social Web Application Interoperability.” 2014. W3C (blog). July 21, 2014. https://www.w3.org/blog/news/archives/3958.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the press release from the W3C announcing the start of the Social Web Working Group, which I understand gave us ActivityPub, the protocol that supports contemporary federated social media systems such as Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sv_meeting_title--14-may-2014-2014-may-14-2014-httpswwww3org20140514-social-minuteshtml&quot;&gt;“SV_MEETING_TITLE – 14 May 2014.” 2014. May 14, 2014. https://www.w3.org/2014/05/14-social-minutes.html.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This somewhat innocuous-looking site is the start of something big – the transcript first meeting of the Social Web Working Group, held over IRC. What immediately catches my eye is the forceful statement from Tantek Çelik, of Mozilla: “we don’t want to see a big company or 2-3 get a monopolistic control in this space.” Thinking about that from the outset likely affected the ultimate design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;massochin-manuela-2022-why-choose-rocketchat-for-your-open-source-chat-tool-opensourcecom-january-24-2022-httpsopensourcecomarticle221rocketchat-data-privacy&quot;&gt;Massochin, Manuela. 2022. “Why Choose Rocket.Chat for Your Open Source Chat Tool.” Opensource.Com. January 24, 2022. https://opensource.com/article/22/1/rocketchat-data-privacy.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is essentially a press release from RocketChat and published on Opensource.com. What caught my eye is that this system appears to be federated. I’m getting more curious about federated chat applications – it feels like a very active area of development, and yet chat feels so &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; – how long as XMPP been around? So it’s interesting to me that chat apps are cropping up in my news feeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;smithee-alan-2022-software-privacy-day-use-delta-chat-an-open-source-chat-tool-opensourcecom-january-28-2022-httpsopensourcecomarticle221delta-chat-software-privacy-day&quot;&gt;Smithee, Alan. 2022. “Software Privacy Day: Use Delta Chat, an Open Source Chat Tool.” Opensource.Com. January 28, 2022. https://opensource.com/article/22/1/delta-chat-software-privacy-day.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case in point. Here’s another chat app, Delta Chat. This one is intriguing. The author mentions Mattermost, Signal, and RocketChat and then points to the major differentiating feature of Delta Chat: it uses &lt;em&gt;encrypted emails&lt;/em&gt; to send the messages. So the backend is email, while the frontend appears to be chat application. It’s so crazy it just might work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">This week’s FOSS finds: I’m starting to look back at the early days of ActivityPub, and chat apps get some coverage. So once again, don’t count on these posts as a news feed, but more a window into my thinking as I research my FOSS alternative social media book.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Very Kool + Jellyfin</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/26/Very-Kool.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Very Kool + Jellyfin" /><published>2022-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/26/Very%20Kool</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/26/Very-Kool.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;kde&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a quick note to say that I took the plunge: after many, many years of using MATE desktops, I’ve tried KDE Plasma. I really, really like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’ve also had some fun with Jellyfin – so much so it’s goodbye, Plex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote about in a post about &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/12/27/Workflow.html&quot;&gt;my workflow&lt;/a&gt;, for years I used Devilspie to sort applications into various workspaces. After posting that, I half expected to get a comment that this would be natively possible in another desktop environment – and I expected someone to say “use KDE!” That didn’t happen, but I still suspected it might be the case – and that KDE would be the one to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/92acf6d56dbcc6b6824d7ee33117267e.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image not found: /assets/images/92acf6d56dbcc6b6824d7ee33117267e.png&quot; title=&quot;Image not found: /assets/images/92acf6d56dbcc6b6824d7ee33117267e.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I tried Manjaro’s KDE on a partition and… I haven’t switched back. And I put another installation on a second computer. I was concerned because the word on the street is that KDE is a death-by-a-thousand-options system, but after only an hour of figuring out lingo, I was able to get things set up the way I pleased. I can much more easily set up my preferred virtual workspace environments than mucking about with Devilspie – even on a two-screen setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, now I get better integration with KDE Connect, a great application. Running it over Wireguard makes for seamless connections between my phone and computer. KDE Connect worked in MATE, but it was always somewhat clunky to get going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And other KDE apps are quite good, too – Kate is a great text editor. Okular works far better than I remembered from the last time I tried it. Manjaro’s KDE has Online Accounts (either a fork or implementation of Gnome Online Accounts) so setting up Nextcloud was a breeze. And while I expected to use Kmail, Manjaro opted for Thunderbird for email. I gave up on Thunderbird in favor of Evolution a few years back because Thunderbird seemed resource-intensive, but I was pleasantly surprised to find Thunderbird is very snappy – and those tab views are great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jellyfin&quot;&gt;Jellyfin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been watching Jellyfin for a long time, but I kept using Plex to serve movies and TV shows from my Raspberry Pi to my TV and other devices. Lately, however, Plex stopped working as it used to – I recall seeing something about reinstalling it. (Maybe they made some sort of change and I didn’t notice?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/7eb77281fb804b4437507a7e39811b72.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jellyfin Logo&quot; title=&quot;Jellyfin Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I thought I’d try Jellyfin and… wow! Between it and Wireguard, I can serve movies, TV, and music to any of my devices, anywhere. It’s like my own personal streaming system. Jellyfin makes a nice app in F-Droid for Android devices, or I can use the web interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while I work on the new book project (by flipping through virtual workspaces in KDE) I can listen to Herbie Hancock’s magnificent album [&lt;em&gt;Maiden Voyage&lt;/em&gt;](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maiden_Voyage_(Herbie_Hancock_album).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very Kool. (sorry.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="KDE" /><category term="Manjaro" /><summary type="html">KDE Just a quick note to say that I took the plunge: after many, many years of using MATE desktops, I’ve tried KDE Plasma. I really, really like it. And I’ve also had some fun with Jellyfin – so much so it’s goodbye, Plex.</summary></entry></feed>