<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-27T07:55:26-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FOSS Academic</title><subtitle>A blog dedicated to two things. First, an exploration of Free and Open Source tools useful to academics. Second, an exploration of the culture, politics, and practices of FOSS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Staticman Comments Test Post</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/24/Staticman.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staticman Comments Test Post" /><published>2021-01-24T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-24T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/24/Staticman</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/24/Staticman.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is to test Staticman comments. I’ll edit this post later to update my progress. For now, if anyone stumbles across this and wants to add a “test” comment or something helpful, feel free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m basing this process of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://travisdowns.github.io/blog/2020/02/05/now-with-comments.html&quot;&gt;helpful blog post&lt;/a&gt; from Travis Downs of Performance Matters. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update 1: There are clearly problems in my configuration, and so I must keep debugging. But it’s time for a walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update 2: Success in posting a comment after turning ReCaptcha off. However, not sure if I set things up to &lt;em&gt;display&lt;/em&gt; the comment…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update 3: Success in getting a comment posted! But the workflow is very convoluted. I know Staticman uses Github pull requests to work, so I have to merge each comment. That’s fine. However, after I do so, I will have to move the data from my local version of my static site and then rebuild it via Jekyll. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=INX-KrjaNOo&quot;&gt;There has to be a better way&lt;/a&gt;! And I will figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I do know I will have to style the comments, as well. One thing at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update 4: I think it’s done! Comment forms are styled for desktop and mobile, and the workflow is now improved. I initially set up my Github repository to be only the contents of the _site folder, but now the whole thing (warts and all) is in Github, which makes moderating comments much easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, thanks go to Travis Downs for his exhaustive post on how to get Staticman going, as well as some of his code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have a few more tweaks – most notably, to de-Google-ify the whole thing, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JwZwkk7q25I&quot;&gt;system is not down&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Staticman" /><summary type="html">This post is to test Staticman comments. I’ll edit this post later to update my progress. For now, if anyone stumbles across this and wants to add a “test” comment or something helpful, feel free! I’m basing this process of this helpful blog post from Travis Downs of Performance Matters. Thank you! Update 1: There are clearly problems in my configuration, and so I must keep debugging. But it’s time for a walk. Update 2: Success in posting a comment after turning ReCaptcha off. However, not sure if I set things up to display the comment… Update 3: Success in getting a comment posted! But the workflow is very convoluted. I know Staticman uses Github pull requests to work, so I have to merge each comment. That’s fine. However, after I do so, I will have to move the data from my local version of my static site and then rebuild it via Jekyll. There has to be a better way! And I will figure it out. And, I do know I will have to style the comments, as well. One thing at a time. Update 4: I think it’s done! Comment forms are styled for desktop and mobile, and the workflow is now improved. I initially set up my Github repository to be only the contents of the _site folder, but now the whole thing (warts and all) is in Github, which makes moderating comments much easier. Once again, thanks go to Travis Downs for his exhaustive post on how to get Staticman going, as well as some of his code. I do have a few more tweaks – most notably, to de-Google-ify the whole thing, but the system is not down.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">20 Years of Wikipedia</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/20/20-years-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="20 Years of Wikipedia" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/20/20-years-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/20/20-years-wikipedia.html">&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia is 20 years old this year. Congratulations! Celebrations abound across the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a scholar of Wikipedia and a FOSS Academic, I wanted to weigh in on the birthday and provide a short history lesson. (This is, therefore, a &lt;a href=&quot;/tags/goal 2.html&quot;&gt;Goal 2 post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/20yearsWP.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia's 20 year celebration page&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reporting on the 20th birthday of Wikipedia (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.msn.com/en-us/news/world/as-wikipedia-turns-20-it-aims-to-reach-more-readers/ar-BB1cLIVf&quot;&gt;MSN&lt;/a&gt;) suggests that Wikipedia was always going to be non-profit. That’s not exactly true. Wikipedia’s URL was initially wikipedia.com, and it was intended to be a for-profit site. As I discuss in my book &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/books/reverse-engineering-social-media-software-culture-and-political-economy-in-new-media-capitalism/9781439910344&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reverse Engineering Social Media,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a key event in 2001, dubbed “The Spanish Fork Labor Strike,” pushed Jimmy Wales to make the site into a non-profit instead of a commercial venture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a mailing list discussion, Wales noted that Wikipedia would start selling ads around its content. He was a veteran of this type of venture, having &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bomis&quot;&gt;sold ads on a porn search engine back in the mid-1990s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The specter of ad sales around voluntarily-provided content upset many Wikipedians, most notably a growing community of Spanish-speaking editors who were working to make Wikipedia an international project. Because Wikipedia was licensed with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Licensing_update&quot;&gt;GFDL&lt;/a&gt;, Spanish-speaking Wikipedians could take the articles they were writing and port them to another site. They did so, moving to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://enciclopedia.us.es/index.php/Enciclopedia_Libre_Universal_en_Espa%C3%B1ol&quot;&gt;Enciclopedia Libre Universal en Español&lt;/a&gt; in protest over Wales’s announcement about ads (as well as their discontent with Larry Sanger’s management style).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales heard their grievances and agreed with them: there would be no ads, Sanger would be fired, and Wikipedia would be a non-profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edgar Enyedy and his colleagues deserve a great deal of credit for pushing the nascent Wikipedia to become a non-profit. And to be fair, credit should go to Wales for recognizing the legitimacy of the &lt;em&gt;Enciclopedia&lt;/em&gt; editors’ greivances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this important event is getting lost to history. Nathaniel Tkacz documented it well during the 10 year anniversary &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.co.uk/article/wikipedia-spanish-fork&quot;&gt;with his interivew with Enyedy&lt;/a&gt;, but since then, the Spanish Fork seems to be overlooked. It’s mentioned only in passing in the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikipedia20.pubpub.org/&quot;&gt;MIT Book W&lt;em&gt;ikipedia @ 20&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First, Wikipedia was conceived by Wales as a likely commercial undertaking. Wikipedia was originally hosted at wikipedia.com, and by 2002 Sanger and Wales were hinting that Bomis might start selling ads on Wikipedia, in part to pay Sanger’s salary. Wikipedians objected—Spanish Wikipedians even left to create their own. Given these objections and the deflation of the dot-com bubble, Sanger was laid off. Wales changed the site over to a .org domain and began work to establish the non-profit Wikimedia Foundation, which happened in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we should thank the Spanish Wikipedians for the site’s current non-commercial status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their strike has brought about many benefits. Unlike so many other websites, Wikipedia has no real infrastructure for behavioral advertising profiling. The Firefox plugin NoScript shows that it’s not tracking – a refreshing change of pace when compared to contemporary sites that are larded with tracking scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/noscriptWP.png&quot; alt=&quot;a screenshot showing that Wikipedia uses very few scripts&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;These are the two scripts Noscript finds on any given Wikipedia article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike many other sites, which are constantly tweaked to increase click-through rates on ads (a practice now dubbed “dark patterns”), Wikipedia’s  interface is remarkably stable. It looks pretty much the same as it did 20 years ago. Rather than seeing this as stagnation, those of us who decry changes in interfaces should celebrate Wikipedia’s now intuitive interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Wikipedians are not interested in tweaking the interface to increase attention on ads, they are constantly tweaking the social structures that help administer pages, with debates over policies, efforts to include more articles about women, efforts to translate the encyclopedia into yet more languages, and a de-facto social networking system where fixing grammar is celebrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Wikipedia did change its licence from GFDL to Creative Commons, the change has only cemented its place as a bastian of open cultural production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my part, I’ve donated to Wikipedia. I’ve contributed to it. I’ve encouraged students to edit it. I rely on it all the time. The FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream would be incomplete without it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a point that I don’t think we’re making enough as misinformation spreads like a deadly virus across corporate social media. Wikipedia was once the  poster child of misinformation. Back in the mid-2000s, Wikipedia-bashing was a popular sport. It was the wild and wacky Wikipedia where vandals and trolls reigned and misinformation was rampant. But very early on in its history, Wikipedia demonstrated the adage about many eyes and bugs: vandalism and uninformed opinion is rooted out rather quickly on Wikipedia, rather than being allowed to spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, I think back to the Spanish Fork and their labor strike: pushing the site to be non-profit and to never have ads has rescued it from the logic of corporate Web 2.0. While other sites mire in the muck of misinformation, while other sites track us, while they constantly develop more pernicous dark patterns, and while the commercial web exploits our emotions and attention, Wikipedia has just carried on, with people writing articles and citing their sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kudos.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Wikipedia" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">Wikipedia is 20 years old this year. Congratulations! Celebrations abound across the Internet. As a scholar of Wikipedia and a FOSS Academic, I wanted to weigh in on the birthday and provide a short history lesson. (This is, therefore, a Goal 2 post).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In Praise of Mastodon After an Insurrection, or, What if Donald Trump Had Joined Mastodon?</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/08/PraiseMastodon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Praise of Mastodon After an Insurrection, or, What if Donald Trump Had Joined Mastodon?" /><published>2021-01-08T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/08/PraiseMastodon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2021/01/08/PraiseMastodon.html">&lt;p&gt;In a previous post, I disparaged 2020. But hey, just wait: 2021 has already become pretty bad. As you probably have seen, pro-Trump supporters decided to invade the U.S. Capitol on January 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a tech determinist, which means that I do not seek to explain complexity by only considering changes in technology. So I am not going to say that corporate social media – including Facebook and Twitter – caused what happened yesterday. In other words, I am not going to say that the spread of misinformation was the reason for people to blithely walk past the cops and into the Rotunda. To do so would ignore a host of other factors, such as the history of racism in the United States and the desire for politicians to aggrandize themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m not saying Facebook and Twitter are to blame. What I will say, however, is that one contributing factor to the events of January 6, 2021 – not the sole determining factor – is corporate social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mastodon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Mastodon Logo&quot; title=&quot;The Mastodon Logo&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Mastodon Logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thus I come in praise of Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-attention-economy&quot;&gt;The Attention Economy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporate social media platforms like Facebook and Twitter have for years been developed to monetize the content that spreads the farthest keeps people’s attention – no matter what that content is. We all may have thought it was cute cat videos, but it’s turned out that the stuff that spreads wildly and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/money/2020/08/04/898596655/are-conspiracy-theories-good-for-facebook&quot;&gt;keeps eyeballs are beguiling conspiracy theories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn’t the only monetization happening. Corporate social media also privileges paid content – that is, advertising, and political actors have paid billions in order to get their messages out to their masspersonal audiences. After all, for a few bucks, you can have your message privileged in corporate social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combine the two and you get politicians paying to stoke conspiracy theories, which are spread by misinformed people, who flag their support for politicians, who pay for more ads ad infinitum, ad nauseam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As media studies scholar Gavin Mueller quipped (unfortunately, on Twitter in a Tweet I can’t find), the QAnon conspiracy was mired in a degree of obscurity on places like 4chan, but once it got to Facebook and its audience of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/internet-baby-boomers-misinformation-social-media_n_5f998039c5b6a4a2dc813d3d&quot;&gt;boomers with computers&lt;/a&gt;” started “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Conspiracy-Theorist-Just-Research-Shirt/dp/B07DG2NKXQ&quot;&gt;doing the research&lt;/a&gt;,” it exploded. And right-wing politicians gleefully amplified the messages, from Georgia’s Marjorie Taylor Greene all the way up to Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this week, Facebook and Twitter de-platformed Trump. It was intriguing to watch each corporation one-up the other. Twitter flagged Trump tweets as disputed. Facebook took down a Trump video. Twitter suspended Trump for 12 hours. Facebook banned Trump for the remainder of his time in office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem solved, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should have happened a long, long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it couldn’t have. Because these platforms &lt;em&gt;monetize content.&lt;/em&gt; And that means what’s popular, what spreads, what keeps attention is privileged. Full stop. And who or what has been the single greatest corporate social media sensation arguably of all time? Donald J. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;donaldjtrumpmagainstancesocial-a-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;@donaldjtrump@magainstance.social: A Thought Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with FOSS Academics? And with Mastodon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Trump would have been kicked off Mastodon ages ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, properly speaking, he would have been &lt;em&gt;defederated&lt;/em&gt; ages ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s do a thought experiment. In 2017, Trump (or one of his assistants) noticed the hype about Mastodon and decided to mirror his Twitter content there. Why not explore a new social network and reach more of the MAGA Nation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know how Mastodon works – how federation works – you immediately ask: &lt;a href=&quot;https://instances.social/&quot;&gt;which instance&lt;/a&gt; would Trump have used?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a big question. Many Mastodon instances have Codes of Conduct that Trump would have found to be abhorrent: no homophobic, transphobic, racist, fascist content allowed. So a triumphant post about Trump’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/trump-s-controversial-transgender-military-policy-goes-effect-n993826&quot;&gt;ban on openly transgender people serving in the military&lt;/a&gt; wouldn’t have been just flagged; it would be &lt;em&gt;blocked&lt;/em&gt; and Trump would be informed by the admin that he was violating the Code of Conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump might have just stopped there. Social media that would ban me? But I’m the greatest President ever! The First Amendment! These liberal Mastodons need to be put in jail!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s say he persisted. There are Mastodon instances out there that are more “free speech absolutist.” Trump could have found one – let’s call it magainstance.social – and started his account, and his posts would have spread across the Fediverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except, they wouldn’t have. The same Mastodon instances who would have blocked or outright banned Trump would avoid federating with the instance Trump joined, citing the fact that doing so would violate their local standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Trump would have kept posting anyway. After all, he’s shown an ignorance of how &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/think/opinion/trump-senate-gop-s-electoral-college-vote-objections-betray-conservative-ncna1252927&quot;&gt;federation works&lt;/a&gt;. But he’d probably not get his precious dopamine rush from seeing a bunch of reposts and likes, because, again, &lt;em&gt;his posts wouldn’t spread across the Fediverse&lt;/em&gt; – they would not get the eyeballs and accolades the man clearly needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe then he’d retreat back to Twitter and Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps, even after all this, Trump wanted to stick with Mastodon, believing that it was the next big thing, or perhaps enjoying the love of sycophants on magainstance.social. And maybe he figures, I can fix this, as I always have, with lots of money. I’ll just buy a bunch of ads on Mastodon and that will remind them of who’s paying the bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then he looks for a place to buy ads on Mastodon and finds… nothing. &lt;em&gt;Because it’s not made for advertisers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To be fair, there’s probably no reason individual Mastodon instances couldn’t have advertising. But again, those instances probably won’t get much federation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in a fit of Trumpian rage, he grabs a laptop and says, Mastodon’s open source! I will fork the code! I will make my own! And he fires up Notepad in Microsoft and furiously starts coding. (What coding language would Trump use? I’m not going to answer that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tildes.net/~tech/e0o/gab_is_throwing_away_their_existing_code_and_switching_to_a_modified_version_of_mastodon&quot;&gt;that doesn’t work, either&lt;/a&gt;. Same problem. magainstance.social – or Gab, or whatever you want to call it – would again just be shut out of the federation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;foss-is-political&quot;&gt;FOSS Is Political&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this is a blog about being a FOSS Academic, and I have &lt;em&gt;Goal 2&lt;/em&gt; – I want to write a new book about FOSS. And this is decidedly a Goal 2 post, because I’m talking about FOSS culture and politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come to praise projects like Mastodon, because I would argue they were designed to avoid the problems that Facebook and Twitter have helped contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know very well that many people in the FOSS world would bracket off these comments, arguing that they are political, that they have no relevance for a discussion about FOSS, and that all FOSS is about is making neutral tools. I’ve interviewed people in the FOSS world who make that argument, and I get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people make tools of &lt;em&gt;any kind,&lt;/em&gt; they are embedding cultural, political, and ethical assumptions into the tools. They might claim the tools are neutral – as in the observation that “a hammer can be used to build a house or to hurt someone.” But even the simplest tool reflects the cultural, economic, and political assumptions of its maker. A hammer extends our ability to apply powerful force in a concentrated area, reflecting a different relationship building than, say, thatching implies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the level of cultural, economic, or political embeddness goes up greatly with complex tools, like an open souce, federated social networking site with built-in moderation tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The production of FOSS tools is inherently political. Some FOSS developers recognize this, engaging in what I call “critical reverse engineering” – making tools that are meant to ameliorate the social, economic, and political problems we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others don’t recognize this, concentrating on the existential pleasures of making tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s fine, but think about this: Twitter started out as simply a way to centralize SMS for a large audience. Facebook started out as a way to rate pictures of girls and built some social stuff around that task. They didn’t think much then about what they wrought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, however, tech is not the sole determinant of what happens in society. But that doesn’t mean tech plays no part. So, it’s important for us to consider which technologies contribute to a better world. Mastodon, the federated, open source alternative social media platform that was &lt;em&gt;literally designed&lt;/em&gt; to disallow advertising and allow people to moderate the content, achieved from its conception what corporate social media are only just now blindly groping towards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Mastodon" /><summary type="html">In a previous post, I disparaged 2020. But hey, just wait: 2021 has already become pretty bad. As you probably have seen, pro-Trump supporters decided to invade the U.S. Capitol on January 6. I am not a tech determinist, which means that I do not seek to explain complexity by only considering changes in technology. So I am not going to say that corporate social media – including Facebook and Twitter – caused what happened yesterday. In other words, I am not going to say that the spread of misinformation was the reason for people to blithely walk past the cops and into the Rotunda. To do so would ignore a host of other factors, such as the history of racism in the United States and the desire for politicians to aggrandize themselves. So I’m not saying Facebook and Twitter are to blame. What I will say, however, is that one contributing factor to the events of January 6, 2021 – not the sole determining factor – is corporate social media. The Mastodon Logo And thus I come in praise of Mastodon.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Minor Update – New Publication, No More Hyvor</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/29/Minor-Update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Minor Update – New Publication, No More Hyvor" /><published>2020-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/29/Minor%20Update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/29/Minor-Update.html">&lt;p&gt;A minor update: I have a new publication about &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereboot.com/creating-decentralized-social-media-alternatives-to-facebook-and-twitter/&quot;&gt;alternative social media&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;The Reboot.&lt;/em&gt; The piece discusses two FOSS alternatives to Twitter: the amazing, and yet likely &lt;a href=&quot;http://twister.net.co/news/&quot;&gt;soon-to-be-defunct&lt;/a&gt; Twister, which is a P2P, distributed microblog. I also discuss my favorite project, Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/reboot.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Reboot logo&quot; title=&quot;The Reboot logo&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Reboot logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thereboot.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Reboot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; looks really promising – it’s a magazine dedicated to Internet criticism. I’ve been known to do a bit of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another little update: I installed the Hyvor comment system but then removed it. It worked, which is great, but I missed &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.hyvor.com/blog/removing-free-plan/&quot;&gt;the free window&lt;/a&gt; and I don’t know if I have the traffic to justify using a paid plan. I may go back to it, but I want to explore other options first. Next up: &lt;a href=&quot;https://staticman.net/docs/&quot;&gt;StaticMan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I am teaching my child how to use Linux and want to make a recommendation: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/slackermedia/bashcrawl&quot;&gt;BashCrawl&lt;/a&gt;! It’s a text-based game for the Bash terminal that teaches how to use bash commands. Within half an hour, my kid was showing me some cool bash techniques. Just download an archive, unzip it, and dive in.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="alternative social media" /><category term="publications" /><category term="BashCrawl" /><summary type="html">A minor update: I have a new publication about alternative social media in The Reboot. The piece discusses two FOSS alternatives to Twitter: the amazing, and yet likely soon-to-be-defunct Twister, which is a P2P, distributed microblog. I also discuss my favorite project, Mastodon. The Reboot logo The Reboot looks really promising – it’s a magazine dedicated to Internet criticism. I’ve been known to do a bit of that. Another little update: I installed the Hyvor comment system but then removed it. It worked, which is great, but I missed the free window and I don’t know if I have the traffic to justify using a paid plan. I may go back to it, but I want to explore other options first. Next up: StaticMan. Finally, I am teaching my child how to use Linux and want to make a recommendation: BashCrawl! It’s a text-based game for the Bash terminal that teaches how to use bash commands. Within half an hour, my kid was showing me some cool bash techniques. Just download an archive, unzip it, and dive in.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Workflow</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/27/Workflow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Workflow" /><published>2020-12-27T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/27/Workflow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/27/Workflow.html">&lt;p&gt;The year 2020. Damn. Damn, damn, damn, damn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put it in the dumpster, man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the end of the worst year ever is also the end of the 2010s, so maybe now’s a good time to reflect on my past decade as a FOSS Academic. As I mentioned in the &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/11/27/introduction.html&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve been using FOSS tools to do my job as a university professor for over a decade. Now, I’m looking ahead to the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I want to document my workflow. It’s a combination of desktop environments, workspace management, weekly planning and long-term goals. I’ve been developing it over the past decade, and I think it’s time I formally document just how I do what I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/workspaces.png&quot; alt=&quot;Zotero open in Workspace 1 in MATE&quot; title=&quot;Zotero open in Workspace 1 in MATE&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Zotero open in Workspace 1 of my MATE desktop environment.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a longish post, but then again, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/K9ZQhyOZCNE?t=486&quot;&gt;we’re talking about practice&lt;/a&gt;. That gets complex!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;workspaces&quot;&gt;Workspaces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter the underlying distro, I use the MATE desktop environment, which has a handy workplace switcher applet. This is fine, but out of the box is missing something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Devil’s Pie. It’s not just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EgvE6c7-2ag&quot;&gt;a documentary about the R&amp;amp;B singer D’Angelo&lt;/a&gt;. Devilspie is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.ubuntu.com/community/Devilspie&quot;&gt;small application&lt;/a&gt; that gives me total control over how applications load into various workspaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my typical MATE setup, I have 6 workspaces. I’m old-school, so I set them up horizontally in a top panel. I also set my keyboard shortcut to CTRL+Left or Right to switch between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I do is install devilspie and set it to run on startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devilspie works with scripts stored in ~/USER/.devilspie. Each application requires its own script (saved in .ds files). For example, my Firefox script is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
(if (is (application_name) &quot;Firefox&quot;) (set_workspace 3))
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That line is in a file called firefox.ds, and as you might have guessed, opens Firefox in Workspace 3. Now, no matter where I open Firefox, it gets pinned to workspace 3, and is at most a couple CTRL+direction keystrokes away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using similar techniques, I route my applications to the same places – Zotero, the citation manager, goes in Workspace 1. My “comms” workspace is 5, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNOME_Evolution&quot;&gt;Evolution&lt;/a&gt; email and chat applications routed there. Entertainment (music players, video players) goes to 6. Terminals and my IDE (currently Brackets) goes to 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exception of Brackets going to 4, most of my writing goes into Workspace 2. I route Libreoffice there, as well as my PDF reader. I also use some rules to move Zotero notes to Workspace 2. Devilspie allows me to control window geometry, so I set my PDF reader to 2/3s of the screen and a Zotero note to the remaining 1/3. Devilspie even supports &lt;a href=&quot;https://itsfoss.com/always-on-top/&quot;&gt;“always on top”&lt;/a&gt;, though I don’t use that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit concerned, however. The original devilspie is &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/DevilsPie&quot;&gt;apparently no longer being maintained&lt;/a&gt;, and neither is its successor, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nongnu.org/devilspie2/&quot;&gt;Devilspie2&lt;/a&gt;. I hope these handy applications stick around!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for now, with devilspie and the corresponding rules in place, when I launch an application (in my case, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fossmint.com/synapse-application-launcher-and-file-search-tool/&quot;&gt;Synapse&lt;/a&gt;, which appears with CTRL+Space), I know exactly which workspace it’s routed to. I can flip between a browser and a writing application with a keystroke – cutting, pasting, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pomodoro&quot;&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, switching from my writing space Workspace 2 to email or a Signal message in Workspace 5 is now &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; easy. Distraction is just a couple CTRL+Rights away. I find myself flipping over to email too often, and for no good reason. Because of this, I close Evolution and Signal, but to really help me focus, I also use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gnomepomodoro.org/&quot;&gt;Pomodoro Timer for Gnome&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pomodoro.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Pomodoro for GNOME timer&quot; title=&quot;The Pomodoro for GNOME timer&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Pomodoro Timer in action.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;Pomodoro Technique&lt;/a&gt; to be a simple and effective way to stay on task. It starts with a conscious decision to say “I am working on this task.” Then, I start the timer (set to the default 25 minutes) and do it. After 25 minutes, the Pomodoro Timer takes over my screen and says, “Take a break!” I take the 5 minute break to stretch, do some pushups, move my limbs. And then: back at it for another 25. If I do four Pomodoros, I take a longer, 15 minute break, usually by walking around campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nice thing about this approach is that it is open-ended. If I have a stack of emails: that’s the task. Once that’s done, I can switch to grading, or writing. 25 minutes seems like a good amount to knock out a lot of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how to decide which tasks need be done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cal-newports-weekly-to-do-list-workspace-5&quot;&gt;Cal Newport’s Weekly To-do List: Workspace 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think Cal Newport came up with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calnewport.com/blog/2014/08/08/deep-habits-plan-your-week-in-advance/&quot;&gt;weekly work plan&lt;/a&gt;, but I give him credit because I first learned it from his blog. As he writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
    On Monday mornings I plan the upcoming work week. I capture this plan in an e-mail and send it to myself so that I will be sure to see it and have access to it daily.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to do it via email, but now I put a task in Evolution. Every Monday morning, I spend about an hour assessing what I need to get done in the week, and then I develop a weekly schedule with time blocks allotted to the various tasks. I set the task to be “due” on Sunday. I don’t actually look at it then; I instead look back on last week’s plan on the subsequent Monday morning, reflecting on what I got done in the previous week. I also use the Sunday deadline to see if any tasks in Evolution are due &lt;em&gt;sooner&lt;/em&gt; than my weekly schedule – that means those tasks are high priority for the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of my weekly plan I list out projects I’m working on. Usually, these are long-term projects which require daily work to maintain progress towards deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then break the week down by day and assign blocks of time (typically an hour or two) as time to drive towards completing those long-term goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week then looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
2020 December 13

//Research
* WP met Tor
* Mastodon
* JOC
* DNS

//Teaching
* Comm 431:
        - Build at least one more week
        - grading
* Comm 101
        - find podcast episode
        - grading

//Service
* NMS review

-------------------------
Monday 13 Dec

2 hours DNS research and writing
1 hour Comm 431
1 hour Comm 101

-------------------------
Tuesday 14 Dec

2 hours DNS research and writing
1 hour Comm 431 grading
1 hour NMS review

-------------------------
Wednesday 14 Dec

2 hours research
1 hour email
...etc, etc
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice I’m following Newport’s advice to keep it flexible. Not every moment of the week is planned, but I do allot a good amount of time to “deep” tasks like writing. (And if you’re thinking that this will work well with Pomodoro – you’re right!). For me, I can do about 2 hours of intense writing a working day, so that’s all I schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of flexibility, I also like having at least 2 writing projects at a time – I agree with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chronicle.com/article/how-to-find-a-writing-routine-that-works&quot;&gt;Manya Whitaker’s suggestion to have a couple projects&lt;/a&gt; in order to switch from one when I inevitably get sick of it. (There is nothing better for writing, I find, then putting what I’ve written away for a while and coming back to it later.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of my day I tackle other tasks – “urgent” emails, grading, course prep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-routine-workspace-2&quot;&gt;Writing Routine: Workspace 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can tell, my work centers on writing. I do most of my work in Workspace 2. So let me say a bit more about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing I do is “pay myself first” – that is, whenever possible, I write first. If I have an early class, of course, I get ready to teach that, but my drive is always “write first” in a given day. Writing journal articles or books is a long-term practice that can feel like there’s no immediate payoff. That’s a danger, because knocking out 25 emails or grading 25 papers has an immediate payoff. The problem is that I have finite energy, and I spend a few hours on grading or emails, I will not be in the mood to do any deep writing. So, writing comes first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related to this: because answering an email has that immediate payoff (yay! another email answered!) and writing can feel like a long slog, I give myself credit for my daily writing. I keep a log of how many words I write in a day (a habit I think I picked up after &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2015/03/02/john-steinbeck-working-days/&quot;&gt;reading about John Steinbeck’s habits&lt;/a&gt;). I have a daily goal of 500 words a day. I can usually do that in two hours. I keep a log of these words in a LibreOffice spreadsheet, and I monitor my writing goals on a fortnightly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/writingspreadsheet.png&quot; alt=&quot;A portion of my writing spreadsheet&quot; title=&quot;A portion of my writing spreadsheet&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A portion of my writing spreadsheet. Notes, writing, and revision included.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may ask: 500 words a day? What if they suck? Aren’t you just setting yourself up to just write 500 bad words to fulfill some arbitrary goal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… maybe. But – and I can’t emphasize this enough – &lt;strong&gt;you don’t know if the words are any good until you write them.&lt;/strong&gt; They have to exist to be judged. By keeping track of my daily writing, I’ve learned over the years that probably 1/10th of my writing ends up actually getting published. The rest ends up on the proverbial “cutting room floor.” But I don’t get to publish the 10% if I don’t write anything in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words: I don’t believe in inspiration. Practice. Yes, AI, I’m talking about practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may also ask: what about taking notes? I consider that writing, so it counts (though I usually count half of my note-taking words). Taking notes is definitely writing – reading a journal article or book sparks ideas, and of course I must cite and build upon sources. So that counts, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may finally ask: what about revision? Surely you &lt;em&gt;cut&lt;/em&gt; words. Do you count them as negative word counts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. If I’m revising, I give myself credit for hours I spend doing that. Revision is so important that it gets its own column in my spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, there you have it. My workflow using FOSS tools – MATE Desktop, devilspie, Evolution, Zotero, Libreoffice. Weekly plans, long-term projects, and daily writing goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worked quite well for me over the 2010s. I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/contributors/robert-w-gehl&quot;&gt;written three books&lt;/a&gt;, a couple dozen journal articles, and a range of other publications, all while teaching courses and doing service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think it will work well into the 2020s. I think I can use this process to drive towards &lt;strong&gt;Goal 2&lt;/strong&gt;: my next book. A FOSS book.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="FALD" /><category term="Zotero" /><category term="MATE" /><category term="devilspie" /><category term="workflow" /><category term="goal 2" /><summary type="html">The year 2020. Damn. Damn, damn, damn, damn. Put it in the dumpster, man. But the end of the worst year ever is also the end of the 2010s, so maybe now’s a good time to reflect on my past decade as a FOSS Academic. As I mentioned in the Introduction, I’ve been using FOSS tools to do my job as a university professor for over a decade. Now, I’m looking ahead to the next decade. Here, I want to document my workflow. It’s a combination of desktop environments, workspace management, weekly planning and long-term goals. I’ve been developing it over the past decade, and I think it’s time I formally document just how I do what I do. Zotero open in Workspace 1 of my MATE desktop environment. It’s a longish post, but then again, we’re talking about practice. That gets complex!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Minor Update – Tagging System</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/20/Minor-Update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Minor Update – Tagging System" /><published>2020-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/20/Minor%20Update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/20/Minor-Update.html">&lt;p&gt;A minor update: I’m still learning how to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, and one goal I had was a usable tagging system. I think I’ve achieved it! I want to study the problem more and see if I can’t automate more parts of it, but so far, so good. If you have feedback, leave it in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next goal: improving the design. I want to hire a designer to make a permanent logo and build the site color scheme around it. Or, maybe I will learn how to make my own logo. I also want to improve the font.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="Jekyll" /><summary type="html">A minor update: I’m still learning how to use Jekyll, and one goal I had was a usable tagging system. I think I’ve achieved it! I want to study the problem more and see if I can’t automate more parts of it, but so far, so good. If you have feedback, leave it in the comments!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My FOSS Journey</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/15/FOSS-Journey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My FOSS Journey" /><published>2020-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/15/FOSS-Journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/15/FOSS-Journey.html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://destinationlinux.org/episode-198/&quot;&gt;recent &lt;em&gt;Destination Linux&lt;/em&gt; podcast&lt;/a&gt; interviewed Neal Gompa, a Fedora contributor, and their first question was: how did you start using Linux? I won’t recap Gompa’s story – I’d recommend listening to the show – but suffice it to say it involves an old copy of Red Hat he randomly found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about Gompa’s story and the question of getting started with FOSS and started reflecting on my own FOSS journey. As an academic – and a non-computer science academic, at that – I think my story is pretty unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Windows_Vista.png&quot; alt=&quot;Windows Vista, with Aero&quot; title=&quot;Windows Vista, with Aero&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Windows Vista, with Aero. I didn't have Aero, though. This image is from &lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/a/a3/Windows_Vista.png&quot;&gt;Wikipedia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all started with Windows Vista.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was pursuing my PhD in the mid-2000s, I was a stereotypical poor grad student. But I needed a laptop. I bought a Windows Vista computer – a &lt;a href=&quot;http://h10032.www1.hp.com/ctg/Manual/c01295900.pdf&quot;&gt;Compaq F700&lt;/a&gt;, to be exact. I spent more money on it than I had ever spent on a computer: $500. I bought it at Circuit City – that should tell you something right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved that computer. I wrote term papers and my dissertation on it. I took it apart and added RAM. I lovingly blasted dust bunnies out of it. The Compaq and I were friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was sloooooow. Vista was awful. So I installed Ubuntu on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-it-up-a-bit&quot;&gt;Back It Up a Bit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should back up, though. I didn’t just wake up one day and say, “Linux is what I need.” Rather, I got the idea because I was already using FOSS alternatives to proprietary software. I was taking little forays into FOSS well before becoming a Linux convert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when I started my PhD program (Cultural Studies at George Mason) in 2005, I was regularly using Endnote, a citation manager. Mason provided Endnote for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until, that is, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dltj.org/article/endnote-zotero-lawsuit/&quot;&gt;Mason was sued by Endnote&lt;/a&gt; because &lt;a href=&quot;https://rrchnm.org/&quot;&gt;GMU’s Center for History and New Media&lt;/a&gt; were making an open-source alternative. That alternative was &lt;strong&gt;Zotero&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I lost my free license to Endnote, and, being a poor grad student, switched to the free-as-in-free-beer Zotero. I imported my Endnote library and haven’t looked back. 30,000 library items later and I’m still using Zotero every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zotero wasn’t the only FOSS I was using. I was also regularly using &lt;strong&gt;Firefox&lt;/strong&gt; and realized it, too, was FOSS. Firefox was only a few years old at that point. Looking back at the mid-2000s, Firefox was so &lt;em&gt;exciting.&lt;/em&gt; It was so freakin’ cool that I could add an extension to it to change it. I can’t recall if that’s when I started using ad blockers. I think it may have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Zotero was riding piggy-back on Firefox at that point. It was integrated into Firefox as an extension. Firefox made Zotero possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firefox also got me away from Internet Explorer. I was learning Web design at that time, so I knew about Explorer’s problems with a lack of standards. Firefox was touted as standards-driven. (Although, at that time, I also like Opera quite a bit). I started developing websites in Firefox and it is still my go-to environment, even though I know I need to switch to Chrome. (More about that some other day.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward back to that Compaq F700. Though it had Windows, one thing it didn’t have was: Office. Again, I was poor. But I was ready for this problem. I looked to see if there was something like Zotero or Firefox, but for word processing and… there was &lt;strong&gt;OpenOffice&lt;/strong&gt;! And it worked!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point, I got into FOSS stuff more and more. And I took a hard look at the underlying OS, Vista. At this point, I’m starting to see how good FOSS software could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized maybe Linux would work better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-ubuntu&quot;&gt;Enter Ubuntu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I was lucky: Ubuntu was already going strong at that point, with a “Long Term Release” called “Dapper Drake,” Ubuntu 6.06. I believe that was the first Ubuntu I installed on my machine. I downloaded an image, burned it to a CD, popped it in the tray and… it worked! It booted up, and you could click on stuff and do Windows-ey things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Ubuntu-desktop-2-606-20080706.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ubuntu Dapper Drake Desktop&quot; title=&quot;Ubuntu Dapper Drake desktop&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Ubuntu Dapper Drake. The human theme takes me back.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, it mostly worked. There were struggles, mostly with wifi chips. Oh, I recall those struggles. But they were ok, because I could &lt;em&gt;dual boot.&lt;/em&gt; I could partition the disk, check out Ubuntu and get the wifi working, and if there were any issues, I could go back to Vista to get some work done. “How cool is that,” I thought to myself. “Two operating systems!” Weird, wild stuff. It felt like a secret, a hidden part of my computer that only I knew about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then… if I could keep files on the Microsoft side while goofing around on Linux, why not try other things? Like: Xubuntu! Or Mint!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was now “distro hopping.” And it was &lt;em&gt;fun.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I actually miss the Xubuntu splash screen of that era. As I recall, it did a kind of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dedoimedo.com/images/computers_new_2/xubuntu-9-10-splash.jpg&quot;&gt;firefly animation&lt;/a&gt; and then the desktop appeared.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time I switched to Linux Mint, mainly because they would ship the “restricted” bits and allow for media playback and had better hardware support. I think I stuck with Mint for quite some time (that is, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zdnet.com/article/linux-mint-the-right-way-to-react-to-a-security-breach/&quot;&gt;until they had a security breach&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a certain point, around 2009 or so, I wondered what the point of keeping Vista was. I was spending more and more time in Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of you who used Vista know: it was &lt;em&gt;awful.&lt;/em&gt; Awful, awful, awful. I missed XP so much. (Hell, the one I miss is Windows 98SE. That was my jam).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to just &lt;em&gt;delete&lt;/em&gt; Windows and only use Linux… that was a big deal. I can still recall my nervousness. There was no going back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I did it. Vista was gone. And I haven’t gone back to Windows since. As of now, I use Linux everywhere I can. Ubuntu, Mint, Manjaro, Fedora, gimme gimme gimme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way, I learned more and more about the other freedom – the free-as-in-freedom – aspect. I started to understand how my operating system worked, and how to get more control over my digital life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for me, the institutions I’ve worked for have tolerated my Linux use. This means that I’m free of proprietary software requirements. With the increasing surveillance of workers – including academics – my little Linux setups are safe havens (a point I will talk about some time later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, I’m living the “FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.” And I can’t imagine doing otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;foss-had-an-impact-on-my-research&quot;&gt;FOSS Had An Impact on My Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While all of this has a sort of &lt;strong&gt;Goal 1&lt;/strong&gt; aspect – it’s about specific tools used to do my academic work – the story is also a &lt;strong&gt;Goal 2&lt;/strong&gt; story, because FOSS affected my career and research interests. At Mason, I started exploring the discourses and economics of “Web 2.0.” Recall that Web 2.0 was, in part, about “user-led production,” where Internet users would contribute to online systems. Examples included the aggregated intelligence of Google searches, amateur videos on YouTube, social bookmarking (Digg), social networking on Facebook, or the collectively produced Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to see all of this through the lens of &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.mit.edu/schock/www/docs/18.2terranova.pdf&quot;&gt;Tiziana Terranova’s “free labor” concept&lt;/a&gt;: we were all giving our labor to these sites in exchange for access and enjoyment. And I started to think of this as highly exploitative. After all, Youtube was “user-led” and it sold for $1.65 billion dollars. Facebook was “free,” but it was valued at $38 a share at its IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Web 2.0 looked a bit like FOSS: get communities of people to contribute and you get valuable products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also looked really rapacious: I give you access, and you provide content and data. Toss in the burgeoning surveillance economy, and you get a disturbing picture. I give you access, you give me your data, and I sell your eyeballs to the highest bidder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where does your data go? On a Linux box, your data is… there. But in the Web 2.0 (or cloud) approach, your personal data is stored on corporate servers. And can you get it back? Not really. (Keep in mind, this is before things like the GDPR). While “communities” were building things like Facebook and Digg, they didn’t get the same benefits as FOSS communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only exception seemed to be Wikipedia. I wondered why. It turns out, we type wikipedia.org and not wikipedia.com because of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.co.uk/article/wikipedia-spanish-fork&quot;&gt;labor strike&lt;/a&gt; and because of FOSS-style licensing. (Imagine if that was the case with Facebook!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there I was, using FOSS and starting to understand how contributing to a project meant you got something even better back, something that gave you more – not less – control over your digital life. I was watching as that ethos was twisted into something more sinister. Facebook was starting to look pretty bad. Google was looking like was, in fact, doing evil. All the more so when I saw how FOSS-licensing plus some political consciousness changed the course of Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote my dissertation in 2009-2010 as a critique of Web 2.0, exploring these topics at length. But, in the spirit of the FOSS alternatives I was using to write my diss, I didn’t stop at critique. I called for alternatives to the dominant, corporate Web 2.0 sites. I started calling this “critical reverse engineering” and the work eventually &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/books/reverse-engineering-social-media-software-culture-and-political-economy-in-new-media-capitalism/9781439910344&quot;&gt;became my first book&lt;/a&gt;. If a labor strike and the GNU/FDL helped Wikipedia avoid becoming a for-profit, surveillance-driven monster, what about projects that start out as FOSS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Reverse-Engineering.png&quot; alt=&quot;The cover of Reverse Engineering Social Media, a book by Robert W. Gehl&quot; title=&quot;The cover of Reverse Engineering Social Media, a book by Robert W. Gehl&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;My first book! It came out in 2014. I was hating Facebook before it was cool.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using FOSS and critiquing Web 2.0, I started to see a need for “alternative social media” – a &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1461444820912533&quot;&gt;research program that I’m still pursuing&lt;/a&gt;. To my mind, it’s not enough to critique Facebook. We have to do something about it – make something better. That is the promise of FOSS thinking. We can experiment to move past what limits us now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up my FOSS journey: I came for the freedom (that is, the cost) and stayed for the freedom (that is, the ethics, the new ways of thinking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words: thanks, Vista!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="FALD" /><category term="Goal 1" /><category term="Goal 2" /><category term="Ubuntu" /><category term="Windows Vista" /><category term="Web 2.0" /><category term="Alternative Social Media" /><category term="Zotero" /><category term="Firefox" /><category term="OpenOffice" /><summary type="html">A recent Destination Linux podcast interviewed Neal Gompa, a Fedora contributor, and their first question was: how did you start using Linux? I won’t recap Gompa’s story – I’d recommend listening to the show – but suffice it to say it involves an old copy of Red Hat he randomly found. I thought about Gompa’s story and the question of getting started with FOSS and started reflecting on my own FOSS journey. As an academic – and a non-computer science academic, at that – I think my story is pretty unique. Windows Vista, with Aero. I didn't have Aero, though. This image is from Wikipedia. It all started with Windows Vista.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Tuxies, Academic Style</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/10/The-Tuxies-Academic-Style.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Tuxies, Academic Style" /><published>2020-12-10T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/10/The-Tuxies-Academic-Style</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/10/The-Tuxies-Academic-Style.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://linuxunplugged.com/&quot;&gt;Linux Unplugged podcast&lt;/a&gt; is hosting their first-ever Tuxies award. They’re &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdJImbr7PdPA5oHwv4HUtVA6nspYYqYnG5W0hqrjaSI1AZebw/viewform?usp=send_form&quot;&gt;soliciting votes&lt;/a&gt; for a range of categories of FOSS projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tuxintux.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tux the Penguin Wearing a Tuxedo&quot; title=&quot;Tux the Penguin Wearing a Tuxedo&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it might be good to nominate things from the FOSS Academic point of view, celebrating projects that help me do my academic work. So, here are the votes I cast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-open-source-project&quot;&gt;Best Open Source Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their prompt is: “Not just released in 2020, but your very favorite open source project of all time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost gave a nod to &lt;strong&gt;Mastodon.&lt;/strong&gt; Mastodon has done so much to offer a better alternative to corporate social media. Think about it: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/10/technology/facebook-antitrust-suits-hurdles.html&quot;&gt;the US government and 40 states are suing Facebook for violating anti-trust laws and becoming a monopoly&lt;/a&gt; – and rightfully so, in my view. Facebook got that way by a) expoiting user-produced content and b) buying up the competition. Mastodon, on the other hand, is a non-commercial, FOSS alternative that is decentralized. And it works really well. (I’ll have more to say about Mastodon in the future).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have to go with my old friend &lt;strong&gt;Zotero,&lt;/strong&gt; which has been a mainstay of my “&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/12/01/Zotero-Tips-and-Tricks.html&quot;&gt;FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream&lt;/a&gt;” for over decade. I wish I could tell the crew at Unplugged what Zotero means to academics. Indeed, I would suggest they check it out for their own research purposes. They may not understand how important a good citation manager is to an academic. So, if Chris and Wes are reading this: Zotero deserves some Tuxy (Tuxie?) love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-newcomer-project&quot;&gt;Best Newcomer Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one was meant to be for a project made in 2020. I screwed it up. I said &lt;strong&gt;Jekyll&lt;/strong&gt;, because I read in some listicle slideshow article that it was a new system in 2020. Turns out it’s not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it’s a great system. Once it’s up and running, writing up blog posts is quick and distraction-free. I can compose in any text editor. And it hooks in with Github.io, so you don’t need a hosting service to run your blog/website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, maybe we can pretend I’m right and say this is a newcomer project and give ‘em a Tuxy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to think of it, I’m probably the worst person to ask about bleeding-edge things. &lt;a href=&quot;https://luddites.latenightlinux.com/&quot;&gt;I still miss the Linux Luddites show&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-text-editor-of-2020&quot;&gt;Best Text Editor of 2020&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are many, but only one of them can be the winner. Which text editor did your fingers rock in 2020?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty certain I am wading into a Religious War (a &lt;strong&gt;Goal 2&lt;/strong&gt; topic for another day), but I will suggest &lt;strong&gt;Nano.&lt;/strong&gt; In 2020, I started using it more and more, not only to handle editing configuration files, but also in some cases for jotting down ideas in Markdown. It’s a really easy to use terminal text editor. I don’t live in the terminal, but for those of us who, like me, dip in from time to time, Nano helps us get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-desktop-distro-of-2020&quot;&gt;Favorite Desktop Distro of 2020&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What was your favorite distro this year?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an “Other” field, and I’d likely use that to say &lt;strong&gt;Linux Mint.&lt;/strong&gt; This past year I’ve experimented with &lt;strong&gt;Fedora 33&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Endeavour OS.&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve used various *buntus over the years. This year, however, when I sit down to get work done, I find myself using Mint more and more. I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2020/03/linux-mint-network-file-sending-tool&quot;&gt;Warpinator&lt;/a&gt; to be really useful around the house and office for quickly sharing files. I also like the built-in backup system. Once I sit down at a Mint MATE box, I feel at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-server-distro-of-2020&quot;&gt;Favorite Server Distro of 2020&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What was your go to server distro this year?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going with &lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu,&lt;/strong&gt; because I’ve set up Ubuntu servers to handle Nextcloud for my personal cloud and frankly, I don’t think about them all that much. Even as a colleague and I used Nextcloud to share files to write a book. We had no problems with the server. Ubuntu server was, in fact, boring: but that’s a good thing in a server!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-desktop-environment-of-2020&quot;&gt;Best Desktop Environment of 2020&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Which desktop environment was the real MVP for you this year?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;strong&gt;MATE.&lt;/strong&gt; I was one of the many &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zdnet.com/article/linus-torvalds-finds-gnome-3-4-to-be-a-total-user-experience-design-failure/&quot;&gt;who didn’t like the Gnome 3 switch&lt;/a&gt;. I had my desktop dialed in in Gnome 2, so I was so happy to find that I could do the same in MATE. If I try a new distro, I usually do so on MATE just to see if I could set up the same workflow, and it almost always works. I can get the panels and workspaces set up in the way I like in minutes, and toss in some &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://help.ubuntu.com/community/Devilspie&quot;&gt;Devilspie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and I’m good to go. All my applications load in their respective workspaces and are just a CTRL+right away, allowing me to shift from Zotero to Libreoffice to Firefox and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-linux-game-of-the-year&quot;&gt;Best Linux Game of the Year&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Favorite game that plays on Linux released in 2020, old games now working via Proton this year count!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I skipped this one. I play Mario Kart on a Retropi. That’s about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-of-tech-2020&quot;&gt;Best of Tech 2020&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What tech or perhaps open source project has really impressed you this year?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;PinePhone.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, it’s not perfect. Not at all. I almost threw mine across the room at one point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can see it, like a vision: all of us distro-hopping on our phones. Easily. In fact, I already have tried out four or five distos on it. I can spend a few hours installing them via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dreemurrs-embedded/Jumpdrive&quot;&gt;Jumpdrive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the idea that my phone won’t talk to Google or Apple makes me giddy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who know me will tell you that I hate phones. I hate them mainly because I find them insulting. They’re computers, but I can’t really mess with ‘em. I just… &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; them. And they use me. They are designed to suck up as much data about me as possible, and &lt;em&gt;there’s nothing I can do to stop them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PinePhone is changing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;most-life-changing-hardware--device--gadget&quot;&gt;Most Life-Changing Hardware / Device / Gadget&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Did you get something that upgrades your workflow? Or a new gadget that’s changed your game?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi 4&lt;/strong&gt; has been excellent. I think the “game” that’s changed for me is doing research on the Web. I’m probably not supposed to admit this, but I use a Pi-hole in my office to absorb all the krufty ads that hit my machines. I’m quite certain it is helping speed up browsing and thus speed up research online. Plus, I’m using another Pi 4 as a home media center. That actually could be good for teaching, too: I could VPN into my home network if I want to show a video from my library in class.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Tuxies" /><category term="Zotero" /><category term="Mastodon" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="Nano" /><category term="Linux Mint" /><category term="MATE" /><category term="PinePhone" /><category term="Raspberry Pi 4" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">The Linux Unplugged podcast is hosting their first-ever Tuxies award. They’re soliciting votes for a range of categories of FOSS projects. I thought it might be good to nominate things from the FOSS Academic point of view, celebrating projects that help me do my academic work. So, here are the votes I cast.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dreaming in code</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/06/Dreaming-In-Code.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dreaming in code" /><published>2020-12-06T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/06/Dreaming%20In%20Code</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/06/Dreaming-In-Code.html">&lt;p&gt;There have been a lot of books that have influenced my career: Fred Turner’s &lt;em&gt;From Counterculture to Cyberculture,&lt;/em&gt; Gabriella Coleman’s &lt;em&gt;Hacker, Hoaxer, Whistleblower, Spy,&lt;/em&gt; Karl Marx’s &lt;em&gt;Grundrisse,&lt;/em&gt; John Law’s &lt;em&gt;Aircraft Stories,&lt;/em&gt; and Patricia Hill Collin’s &lt;em&gt;Black Feminist Thought.&lt;/em&gt; These works are a kind of well to return to, again and again, to quench intellectual thirsts: thinking historically about communication technologies, and thinking about heterogeneity in the cultures of communication technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps the closest to my heart, one of the books that came along at just the right moment in my career – a bubbling spring of the well – is Scott Rosenberg’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dreamingincode.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dreaming In Code&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dreamingincode.com/&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/codepagetop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dreaming in Code, by Scott Rosenberg&quot; title=&quot;Dreaming in Code, by Scott Rosenberg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        Dreaming in Code -- image used as fair use
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dreaming in Code&lt;/em&gt; tells the story of the development of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chandlerproject.org/&quot;&gt;Chandler&lt;/a&gt;, an open source, cross-platform “personal information manager.” This software was the brainchild of Mitch Kapor (of Lotus 1-2-3 fame, and the founder of a short-lived non-profit called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.osafoundation.org/&quot;&gt;Open Source Applications Foundation&lt;/a&gt;. While the OSAF was well-funded (to the tune of millions), and while Chandler was eventually built, it was marked by blown deadlines and cost overruns. And the project is now moribund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, as Rosenberg wryly notes, Chandler is another in a long line of failed software projects. Unlike building bridges, he notes, software engineering is &lt;em&gt;hard.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this is not a &lt;strong&gt;Goal 1&lt;/strong&gt; post, because the software at the center of &lt;em&gt;Dreaming In Code&lt;/em&gt; is no longer available. Yes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chandlerproject.org/&quot;&gt;the website is still live&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, the project did get far enough along to be useable. Maybe it could still be used if the code could be put into a container (Snap, Flatpak) – then, it could run in a modern Linux installation. If so, perhaps it could contribute to the #fald (FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then again, I’m not sure I would want such old software handling my email and calendars without the latest encryption. The last time I got Chandler to work was around Ubuntu 16.04 (though I may be wrong about the date), and I remember being underwhelmed by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why the project failed. Perhaps Chandler failed because it didn’t adhere to the &lt;strong&gt;Unix Philosophy&lt;/strong&gt; (a decidedly &lt;strong&gt;Goal 2&lt;/strong&gt; topic) – it did not do just one thing and do it well, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chandlerproject.org/vision/&quot;&gt;tried to do lots of things&lt;/a&gt; and thus did them poorly. Indeed, Rosenberg cites Linus Torvalds, who argues that open source production is best done with small goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or perhaps it was too centralized and did not attract a big enough base of contributors. Kapor reportedly threw a lot of money at Chandler, and part of his reasoning was to have his developers largely on-site in San Francisco. The project did not attract, as far as I can tell, a large base of contributors around world. (Indeed, if it had, perhaps we’d be on version 5.0 at this point).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, Chandler has faded out of consciousness, replaced by a whole host of other “PIMs”. The features it largely offers are replicated by email clients – not to mention the monstrosity that is Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But tracing the failure of one relatively obscure FOSS project is not the real payoff of the book for me. &lt;em&gt;Dreaming In Code&lt;/em&gt; is important to me in a &lt;strong&gt;Goal 2&lt;/strong&gt; way because it started me out on the path of what I came to recognize as &lt;strong&gt;software studies.&lt;/strong&gt;  Although it’s not an academic book – Rosenberg is a journalist and founder of &lt;em&gt;Salon.com&lt;/em&gt; – the book is deep and exceptionally well researched. Academics have cited it – including luminaries like Rob Kitchin, Judy Wacjman, and Tim Jordan. Rosenberg’s research is excellent. His endnotes are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dreamingincode.com/endnotes/&quot;&gt;still online&lt;/a&gt; – it’s a wealth of what might be called “classic software studies” citations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He draws on Donald Knuth, Fred Brooks, Eric Raymond, Martin Campbell-Kelly, Vannevar Bush, Doug Englebart, Ellen Ullman, and many, many more. By tracing these citations, I could get a good grasp on the history of software engineering. Perhaps the most influential citation Rosenberg draws on is the late 1960s NATO conferences on software engineering. Along with Sarah Bell, I myself drew on that conference to write about &lt;a href=&quot;http://computationalculture.net/heterogeneous-software-engineering-garmisch-1968-microsoft-vista-and-a-methodology-for-software-studies/&quot;&gt;the engineering of Microsoft Vista as a form of “heterogeneous engineering”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s more than just a wealth of citations. Rosenberg embedded himself with the Chandler team, watching their struggles and connecting those struggles to the history of software engineering. The chapters often start with an episode in the development of Chandler – say, a debate over which programming language to use – which is followed by a deep dive into the history and politics of programming languages. At times, readers might find these too much of a diversion from the story of Chandler. Indeed, Rosenberg’s next book, &lt;em&gt;Say Everything,&lt;/em&gt; tends to avoid these sojourns. But I really, really dig them. The discussion of the NATO conference, for example, was just a great bit of history that prompted me to go and learn more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to placing Chandler into a larger historical context, Rosenberg is also a compassionate, but critical, student of the history of Chandler. It’s a model of analysis of the people and technologies that go into software engineering, told in a beautiful narrative style that I would aspire to myself, and again, the citations are rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find myself returning to &lt;em&gt;Dreaming in Code&lt;/em&gt; again, and again, over the years. The first time I read it, in fact, I was so enthralled that I was nose-deep in it while my partner was giving birth to our son (at one point, she knocked the book out of my hands and said, “no more reading!”). I remember this in part because my Zotero note is dated the day before my son’s birth. As I set off on a new project – my &lt;strong&gt;Goal 2&lt;/strong&gt; project – I have decided to return to &lt;em&gt;Dreaming In Code.&lt;/em&gt; And I find myself at the well, again, and it is definitely not dry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Dreaming in Code" /><category term="FALD" /><category term="Software Studies" /><category term="Goal 2" /><summary type="html">There have been a lot of books that have influenced my career: Fred Turner’s From Counterculture to Cyberculture, Gabriella Coleman’s Hacker, Hoaxer, Whistleblower, Spy, Karl Marx’s Grundrisse, John Law’s Aircraft Stories, and Patricia Hill Collin’s Black Feminist Thought. These works are a kind of well to return to, again and again, to quench intellectual thirsts: thinking historically about communication technologies, and thinking about heterogeneity in the cultures of communication technologies. But perhaps the closest to my heart, one of the books that came along at just the right moment in my career – a bubbling spring of the well – is Scott Rosenberg’s Dreaming In Code. Dreaming in Code -- image used as fair use</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zotero tips and tricks</title><link href="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/01/Zotero-Tips-and-Tricks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zotero tips and tricks" /><published>2020-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/01/Zotero%20Tips%20and%20Tricks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fossacademic.tech/2020/12/01/Zotero-Tips-and-Tricks.html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re not using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;… I don’t know what to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are, you’re well on your way to living the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zotero.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Zotero Logo&quot; title=&quot;The Zotero Logo&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Zotero logo is in the public domain.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zotero is a citation manager. And I’ve been using it so long I have a library of nearly 24,000 items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zotero is a core part of my academic work. I run &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; through it. If I see a talk at a conference – the citation’s going in Zotero. Did I hear a good podcast? Put it in Z. Hey! that’s a relevant blog post. Put it in Z. My colleague shared a great syllabus? Zot! Was that intertesting a TV show? Oh, you know it’s gonna go in there. And of course, I put all the books and journal articles I read in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, you guessed it: Zotero is FOSS (in this case, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.html&quot;&gt;GNU GPL 3.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;strong&gt;Goal 1&lt;/strong&gt; post, I want to talk Zotero tips and tricks – things I &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; do when I install and run this excellent piece of software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;add-in-more-columns&quot;&gt;Add In More Columns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thing’s first: My number one tip is adding more columns to the main pane. It’s a simple trick, but it’s really powerful, especially if you add “Date Added.” Zotero is &lt;em&gt;really good&lt;/em&gt; at pulling metadata from websites – including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org&quot;&gt;WorldCat&lt;/a&gt; and Google Scholar – so a problem you might face is gathering too many things at a time. You might see a citation in passing that you really want to read. But which one of the 50 you grabbed in the past two days was it? For me, sorting with the newest added on top allows me to quickly scan through the latest entries and remember which ones I wanted to examine further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-classic-add-citation&quot;&gt;Use “Classic Add Citation”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zotero integrates with word processors, like LibreOffice or, if you must, Word or Google Docs. The default way of adding citations is an unobtrusive search bar. But I cut my teeth on the old way – the “Classic Add Citation” window. The nice thing about that window is that you can add the same columns as you use for the main Zotero window, with the same sorting capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zoteroscreen.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of a Zotero library&quot; title=&quot;A Zotero screenshot&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A screenshot of my library.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tagging-tagging-tagging&quot;&gt;Tagging, Tagging, Tagging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I recall, Zotero was modeled after iTunes, and an iTunes feature is tagging. Zotero features that, too – and it’s &lt;em&gt;essential.&lt;/em&gt; Tags are very flexible. You can tag based on keywords supplied by the authors, tags based on which project you’re working on, tags based on wacky ideas you might have about how things should relate. I recommend tags because of…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;smart-folders&quot;&gt;Smart Folders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can sort your citations into folders, certainly, but I much prefer smart folders. The vast majority of mine are based on tags, even Boolean combinations of tags, or combinations with other things (tags + types of items, type of items + publication date).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tip I picked up somewhere over the years is to have a smart folder that includes items added in the past 5 days (a more focused version of sorting by date added).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tags.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Zotero tag window&quot; title=&quot;A Zotero tag window&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Some tags I've applied to an item in Zotero. Bonus points if you can figure out what citation they refer to.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;note-titles-yyyymmdd&quot;&gt;Note Titles: YYYYMMDD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Zotero to take notes. I know there are many other ways to take notes – and I will explore Linux-friendly, FOSS options soon – but for the past decade I’ve taken thousands of notes in Zotero and converted that raw material into books and articles. I have a system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the basic thing I do with every note is have something like 20201201 – the date I’m taking notes – as the first line. The first line becomes the title of the note. I do that so when I return to the citation later, I know how long ago I read it. Did I read it back in 2009 – that is, back in grad school? Might be wise to reread it (and create a new note, with a more recent date). Or did I read it just a year ago? I can probably just review my notes instead of rereading the article or book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are the tips. There’s more… syncing libraries, working with groups. But these tips are the absolute heart of what I do with this excellent bit of FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>RWG</name></author><category term="Zotero" /><category term="Goal 1" /><summary type="html">If you’re not using Zotero… I don’t know what to say. If you are, you’re well on your way to living the FOSS Academic Lifestyle Dream. The Zotero logo is in the public domain.</summary></entry></feed>